Bitcoin could potentially die tomorrow,
especially if this crazy person starts
doing like this. It is going to
throw things absolutely wild. I don't
want to see this happen. The reason I
don't want to see this happen is you
start bombing power plants that starts
putting people into all s serious and
bad situations, hospitals, the whole
works. It's not something we want to
see. It's not funny. It is quite
disturbing to say the least, and not
something I thought I would see in my
lifetime from um someone of that status.
But again guys, I don't really want to
give my view on all this. I just want to
give you guys the facts, the data of
what's actually happening. And I'll be
be very intrigued if this does occur. If
this does occur, whole different
situation on the markets. I personally
don't think a ceasefire is going to
occur. I think we're more along the
lines of seeing a ground invasion, which
is going to then potentially play out
exactly what I'm seeing on Bitcoin.