Ever since Sunday, Bitcoin dominance has
moved up about 1.7% which doesn't really
feel like a lot in terms of crypto
because we've seen charts pump 20, 30,
50, 100%. But dominance is a different
animal together.
And the reality is that as Bitcoin
dominance shoots up higher,
we should be expecting more pain for
alts, not more bullish good times and
vibes. This is actually not a positive
thing to happen for the market. I'm
going to explain why this affects your
altcoin here on Coin Bureau Trading.
What's up? My name is Aaron Dish from
The Better Traders. Go ahead and hit
that subscribe button, like the video.
We're going to get right into it.
Here's the thing. Bitcoin dominance is
essentially part of the cryptosphere
that makes everything really, really
important.
Um we need to actually draw a circle cuz
this is actually the best way to do it.
We're going to do this. Perfect. Now
that beautiful orange circle.
If this was all crypto
and we just put a nice big fat line down
the middle, that'd be 50%.
Meaning that 50% of the entire crypto
market cap is dominated by Bitcoin, but
that's actually not the case. It's at
59%.
Now I can't really do a perfect drawing
of this, so cut me some slack. But
something like this. This is all
Bitcoin.
You have to understand the implications
of this before I even get into
explaining why this is a bad sign for
your alts. Yes, your alts.
Now
the one thing that makes Bitcoin
dominance really unique compared to
every other dominance levels that
Bitcoin dominance is not, I repeat, not
directly tied or basically um correlated
to price action. We can see Bitcoin
dominance pump to crazy, crazy amounts.
Hey, look over here. What happened on
the 10/10 dump? We actually saw Bitcoin
dominance rocket all the way up 7% to
63.48%
and of course it fell back down. Just
because btc.d is pumping doesn't mean
Bitcoin is either. Obviously on the
10/10 dump, everything crashed, but you
can see what Bitcoin dominance does
during times of stress. Actually, it's
accumulating.
And what happens after that? A lot of
pain.
Now, let me go back to this pizza pie
analogy up here.
The reality right now for btc.d
is that the higher this thing goes, the
more pain, not the more profit, the more
pain is in store for alts. And the
reason why is simple because as we see
the dominance increase for Bitcoin,
we'll just go oops, that's a terrible
straight line. There we go. Right about
halfway. As we see this line get moved
up more,
I wish I could rotate it, but I can't.
More and more and more, it means that as
we see dominance scooted up to like 70%
or even scooting up to 75% which has
never happened. Please God, don't let
that ever happen. That means that
there's only this amount left to
basically represent
a lot of coins. Think about it.
Bitcoin's at the top right now at 59%.
So let's go ahead and just make this
somewhat like 59%-ish
for
the sake of an example, okay? So this
entire span over here, which would be
41%
or just say 40% to make it easier to
understand, that accounts for everything
else. Like everything everything else.
Bitcoin in terms of its dominance is
insane if you think about it
in the whole span
of crypto. Now here's where things get
crazier.
stable.c.d
represents all stablecoin's grouped
together as one single dominance. This
is at 13%.
Okay? So adding these two up together,
we get to 72. So this is going to be a
little bit harder, but 13% slice. Maybe
it's like that, okay?
And this is stablecoin dominance, but
essentially it's just dollars, okay?
Then we have Ethereum making up another
slightly smaller 11%. Okay? That's
Ethereum.
That means that after we add up
stablecoin dominance, Ethereum
dominance, and Bitcoin dominance all
together, we're looking at roughly what
we have? 69 and then 79, 82. So we have
18% left. This is not 18%. I can't draw.
It's too hard. But 18% left.
18% of the total crypto market cap
is everything else that's here.
Literally everything else.
And the problem with this
the big problem is that the more we see
Bitcoin dominance increase, that means
that dominance has to be taken away from
other parts of crypto more and more the
higher it goes.
This presents a massive problem for
alts. It doesn't mean it's bullish. It
actually means the opposite. It's
bearish for alts.
Now you might be thinking, well, I mean,
of course there's going to be some coins
that are outliers. There's going to be
some incredible coins that are pumping
today. SYS,
Centrifuge, Chill Guy, Edge, Dexi, Huma.
Okay, cool. There are some coins that
are doing well. And if we look at the
the flip side, once you get rid of all
of the dead weight,
we have me which is dumping. Tao is
dumping right now 11% plus because of
some drama that's happening. True, Nom,
HLS, Rad, blah blah blah blah blah blah
blah. We get it. We get it, okay? What's
the big deal? How does this actually
affect things negatively? You still
don't get it.
The higher that Bitcoin dominance goes,
the more that
altcoins are being sold off
and or money is moving into stablecoin
dominance which is not yet. It's still
bullish at 10% or depending on which one
you look at, 13%. It's still very
bullish.
But this poses a massive problem for
alts
in a time where the market seems
relatively bullish.
Now, I'm going to give you
my outlook, what I'm actually expecting
to see happen next for Bitcoin dominance
which will
basically give us an outcome for state
Oh, not stable. We'll stablecoin
dominance a little bit, but most likely
others dominance which is the next most
important charts to look at right now.
Which is the entire market cap excluding
the top 10 coins. Again, 7%
7%
We're going to look at all of that and
way more, but before we do, I need you
to go down to the description below.
Why? Because there's going to be a lot
of really good trading to happen in the
weeks to come, maybe in the next couple
of days. Not necessarily saying it's all
bullish, but I'm just saying that things
are going to start poppa-loppin and it's
going to be good. So make sure that
you're signed up to TwoBit. Use the link
that's provided in the description
below. And if you use that link, you can
sign up and trade to earn over 15,000
USDT. There's also way more options
available to you here on the Coin Bureau
Oh, sorry. coinbureau.com/deals
page. Other exchanges, other wallets,
other decentralized exchanges, other
tools, as well as education like our 10%
off discount here for 50 minutes
financial freedom through The Better
Traders which happens to be 40% off
right now.
Literally right now and it's ending
really soon. So
I need you to understand the weight of
this.
If we're adding up
out of 100%
13% basically 60%. So we're looking at
essentially
63%,
73%
we get 80%. Yeah, but then we have our
top 10 dominance. It's just about there.
It's okay.
The problem is this.
The higher that Bitcoin dominance goes,
the lower alts are going to fall. Now
alt Some alts are going to be outliers
like I showed you before. Some are
pumping really high and hard right now.
Cool, that's great. But those are
outliers. We know that and generally
speaking,
if we're looking at like halfway through
this list of 600 coins if not more,
we're red. We're mostly red if not very
red on the majority of all coins.
Okay? Things are not generally bullish.
Now here's the other side of this, too.
There will be coins that are on the
super duper cheap side
in terms of their ex-
almost basically non-existent price
at all. Like Mog, Vinu, Sats, NFT, BTTC,
Cat, Pepe,
Balk, Balk Ship, Pepe. These are all
large market caps, okay?
>> [sighs and gasps]
>> You guys have to understand something
though. Like these are still massively,
massively at risk. You will get some
outliers that do well.
But
there are some that the lower you go
down the market cap rankings,
they're actually going to completely
ignore whatever Bitcoin dominance is
doing and Bitcoin in general. SYS, I
don't even know what this is. Sys-
Syscoin token on KuCoin. Now today it's
up 25%, but this is after it's already
been dumping
for what? 77% over the last 17 days.
Centrifuge is only really only the one
that's pumping that looks good right
now. Chill Guy is up
as well 75% Edge. But now we're starting
to get to these weird coins that no
one's really heard of, but they just
kind of keep going.
Why does Dexi go up higher ever since
February
being up 350%? How is that humanly
possible when Bitcoin dominance is
looking so bearish, you ask? Well,
this is the name of the game. If we're
thinking about the total crypto market
cap, let's play this game differently.
Bitcoin dominance is set right now to
increase, possibly even going up as high
as 60.8%.
It could actually push up a lot higher,
>> [sighs and gasps]
>> which would cause a lot of pain to
everything that's in the top 50, top
100, in my opinion.
But everything else below that is
actually fair game to pump higher and
harder, if not like that chart we looked
at before, was it DEXIE or whatever? I'm
not saying like this is the chart to
trade,
but I'm saying that
you know, they're also clearly not
impervious to market manipulation. This
is the 10 10 dump where DEXIE dropped
98%, and after that dump, it fell down
84%. Is it back up? Not even back up
yet. So please hear me out. I'm not
advocating for you to go dumpster diving
at all,
but don't be surprised over the next
couple of weeks, low caps that you've
literally never ever heard of before,
just start to rally up higher and
harder. Why does this happen?
It happens because
the most popular coins are very much
dependent on Bitcoin's price action.
Yes, Bitcoin is going up higher, but you
would think, well, Bitcoin's going up,
so why isn't BNB going up higher? Why
isn't Tron going up higher? Bitcoin
Cash, Cardano. Why is XMR looking red?
Why do we have these other charts that
are failing like AVAX, HBAR, World
Liberty Financial? That's a different
thing altogether. TAO is dumping, but
that's a different thing altogether. M,
NEM core,
ASTAR, ICP. Why are these charts looking
so weak? Bitcoin's looking so good.
That's exactly the problem. If Bitcoin
dominance is going up higher, you don't
understand, it's sucking up liquidity
and attention and mindshare away from
ICP. It's sucking it up from ASTAR, from
M, from TAO, from World Liberty, from
HBAR, from AVAX, from XMR, from ADA,
and it's just taking it away more and
more.
But the further you go down the list,
you'll notice that quickly, even here,
just looking at this watchlist, notice
how much is red in the top 20, top 30,
and then we start to go a little bit
below that. Now we're getting into some
much lower coins. Notice their
percentages are way higher, considerably
higher
on average than everything else that's
in those top coins. Why is this the
case?
It's how crypto works, guys. This is the
beauty of crypto. When I say that
there's always a good time to trade,
when I share that link for 2 bit with
you, I am literally not kidding. There's
always going to be another runner,
there's always going to be another
opportunity to trade coins that are
absolutely pumping while everything else
is dumping. There's going to be an
escape hatch opportunity, there's going
to be some sort of rally that's
happening, but don't miss this.
What will happen next is this.
Assuming we're going to continue to get
some more motion, and Bitcoin dominance
pushes above 60, which is a big deal, it
will most likely shoot up here to 61,
something like this, something crazy,
and then the moment it starts to fall,
this is when it becomes an extremely
opportune time to scale or pivot into
alts, but the problem is the timing.
And this is the biggest part. Now it's
time to get rid of our big, fancy
schmancy drawing over here.
This is the problem, is timing.
Where are we right now? We are in April,
currently April 10th. What happens in
May?
Typically what happens in May is sell in
May and walk away.
So what we're seeing right now is a
massive setup, if you haven't been able
to distinguish that already. Even if we
have a little bit of a drop in Bitcoin
dominance,
maybe even takes a little bit longer,
hopefully not that long. I'm sure you're
going to do this instead, cuz I don't
want it to take that long in my example,
but let's just say Bitcoin dominance
continues to push up higher towards 61%,
which would be a massive move,
and we have a quick drop.
Whenever we see a quick drop in Bitcoin
dominance like this, it is a fantastic
time to pivot quickly to alts.
The problem though
is that these rallies end very quickly,
particularly in a bear market.
Think back to the rallies that we've
seen recently. The most recent one was
over here in January. What happened? We
saw Bitcoin dominance drop January 1st,
all the way down 1.63%.
Now, of course it moved right back up,
and it went down a little bit more. Yes,
but this big drop, or this big drop
here, third, fourth, fifth
of February, well, that was also with
that big fat dump that happened.
We're going to see these drops in
dominance, and whenever dominance starts
to sink lower, like we've been
witnessing over here, ever since about
the beginning of March, seeing it drop
and drip lower and lower,
it actually gives alts, or rather that
big pie, when we see a decrease in the
space that Bitcoin dominance takes in
that pie, that means dominance is
shifting to most likely others,
which is others.d, others dominance.
This is a big deal. What happened over
here
in January? Well, we saw initially a
nice little rally of 6%, and we got
rugged.
And then that's Yeah, that's what
happened next. And then we got this guy
going up here in February. We have some
fun little dumperooney happening, and
then we get some pullbacks, right? My
expectation is actually for
others dominance to actually go lower
while Bitcoin dominance goes up higher,
but it will have a quick, sharp move up
before the end of April, and then things
are going to get
pretty messy, at least that's what I'm
expecting to see happen starting in May,
or rather at the end of April. Why? Go
back and look at the charts.
May is typically going to be a bearish
time. May and June should be pretty
bearish for BTC. I've more coming out
about this over the weekend on my
channel.
But the main thing you have to
understand is that this is the setup.
It's a massive setup right now.
If you think about the seasonality of
BTC, if you think about chart patterns,
and this isn't just crypto, this is
tradfi.
This is tradfi sell in May and walk
away. Bitcoin follows. Bitcoin's too big
to be ignored by tradfi. So all those
big trading desks,
what do you think they're going to do?
They They They want to see the price of
BTC go up so they can push the price up
higher, then they can reverse their
positions and short it on the way down,
pushing it up higher to cause euphoria,
pushing it back down to cause fear.
Tale as old as time. Seriously. I know,
I should take up a singing career, you
guys are right, but before I do sing
some more, you want to click away and
watch this video that I shared
[laughter]
that will help you understand where we
are in the market, as well as when it's
a good time to start accumulating some
other cryptocurrencies which I shared in
this Slash Wallet review. So watch this.
Until next time, you know to do, stay
awesome and stay in the green. Peace.