The level I'm watching on BNB is one of
my fun critical levels. The 707, the fat
order zone that is sitting here, and of
course the 200 weekly EMA, which also
lines up with the monthly 50 EMA as
well. I'm going to show you guys this on
the monthly because
this here to me looks juicy,
right? I've got multiple alerts stacked
here already at 546
558. I want to get a deep wick into this
area and I want to load a bag of B&B and
I think personally from a risk
perspective that there for me is
definitely a high value trade. Right?
What's happened here is BNB has been
following the 50 EMA on the monthly.
This is also the big order zone that is
sitting here. also the retracement point
from this large scale breakout that's
taken effect which is the 707. So I am
watching BNB quite closely. I want to
grab the wick.