All right, team. We are live. So, thank
you for those guys. Thank you for
everyone that has joined. Apologies, I
was a 1 minute late. Um but guys, we
have a massive session planned because
the entire situation since we caught up
last Wednesday has absolutely flipped on
its head. Like completely changed the
whole sentiment. This weekend we had
some major interruptions within the
market that I'm going to break down for
you all today. I'm going to show you
guys exactly what I'm trading. I'm going
to show you guys how I nailed a banger
trade on Pepe.
How I took profit perfectly.
And also what the current environment is
looking like and why it continues to
change so fast. Right, there is heaps to
cover. And as my big thumbnail says it,
buy BTC cuz Mr. Donald Trump is
absolutely going mayhem at the moment.
And he's causing the markets to go
absolutely wild. So, I've got to break
it down for you all. I'm going to give
everyone a minute to jump in.
I've gone live. We're here. We're ready.
We've got heaps to break down. And we
have been nailing these entire moves. I
think honestly, you guys can go back and
do your own research on these. Check out
the past calls. We've been nailing this
every week. So, thank you to every
single one of you that continue to join.
Um I also did a giveaway last week. I
put that up on my socials. I can't
believe no one has claimed them. So,
just an FYI, guys. I put the giveaway
out there. I shared it with everyone.
But no one actually claimed the
giveaway, which sort of blew my marbles.
Um so, if you haven't and you
done so yet, hit me up on X.
Um or hit me up on Instagram because I'm
going to show you guys what's happened
to my X profile, which again blows my
marbles. So, team, let's get into it.
Let's dive in. I've got a lot to cover.
There's a lot on the charts that I want
to go through today. Um in particular
Bitcoin. And like I said, I want to show
you guys some of the trades that I'm
looking at as well. So,
let's get into it. So, first things
first, you guys should be able to see my
screen. Just making sure of that. I'm
going to move you guys over to my other
one.
So, then everything is functioning as it
should. But if you guys need anything,
let me know. Make sure you can see
everything on the chart. I had someone
last week tell me that I could not see
the price action on the chart. From what
I can see, you guys should be able to
see everything. So, nothing should be
cut off whatsoever.
So, the big one, guys, as well. Before I
get into this chart, this is the
Ethereum, but we've got 86 viewers on
today. That is huge. We hit 100 again.
We're doing a 100 USDT giveaway. I'll
leave it up to you guys in the comments.
Do you want to do two $50 ones or you do
one $100 one? Let me know in the
comments. Again, to be eligible for the
giveaway, you need to make a comment.
That's how I pull the winners out. I
pull the winners from the comments.
Okay? I don't pull the winners from you
guys just watching. So, if you are
there,
whack your comment in. It makes you
eligible. Right? Share the stream out
there. Like it. And let's get into it.
So,
the big one to cover today is buy BTC.
You saw the giant thumbnail I put out
there. This is why. All right? You can
see everything that I've got open here.
I've got tabs open everywhere. Right?
And the reason I have that is because a
lot of this fundamental news is going to
impact what is happening in the market
right now. I'm going to show you guys
how I bring all this together. All
right? So, first things first, you can
see Mr. Donald Trump, you know, wants to
blockade the Strait of Hormuz. And in
doing so, what he is trying to do is
basically economic warfare. He wants to
stop the the flow of money going into
Iran. All right? Why does this impact
the global markets? Why does something
all around the world impact the global
markets? I'm going to bring that into
you guys soon. Right? You can see it
starts to get it's getting wild. Right?
It's getting wild. This the whole
ceasefire
probably going to be blown up within the
next 48 hours. It's getting mayhem.
Donald Trump starting to position
himself as Jesus Christ, which again is
another crazy situation. This guy, in my
eyes, is starting to lose an absolute
plot. Whether you like him or you not,
it is what it is. Right? I don't really
care. I like policies. I don't like
specific people.
But it is getting wild. Now,
what is happening and this is what I
want to show you guys. Right? First
things first, my X account has been
suspended for some unknown reason. I'm
probably the most conservative person
that posts on X. Um so, I do apologize,
guys. What I'm going to have to do today
is I'm going to have to drop all my
charts inside my Empire community. You
guys, there's a link for that in the
bio. Right? So, you guys can jump onto
that for free. You can see all the posts
that I do put in there. Um
but the big one,
all right? I want to go straight into
Bitcoin. Now,
I did um
a little bit of a sneaky one today. I
was doing for my charts. I've already
done one live call today for an hour
with my community. I want to jump into
this. But I stole Nick's chart
today. I figured, you know what? I don't
need to rework this one. It is magic.
It's nice and clean. Let's just use
Nick's one for a specific moment. Right?
Because he's marked out the CME gap that
we've been monitoring for multiple since
basically um the Easter weekend uh when
we did get the CME gap. So, that's
67,000.
And we also have now a new CME gap at
73,000. Okay? So, this is what's
happened over the weekend with all the
movement that has happened in the
markets. Since we basically had a lot of
these announcements around
the Strait of Hormuz getting closed off
again, you know, blockade blockading
ships from going through. What it's gone
ahead and done
is it's caused this CME gap within the
market. All right? What that means is
basically price closed up here around
73,000 on Friday. And now it's currently
sitting at around $71,000,
which in turn creates this CME gap. Now,
you go back and look at the history.
Basically, let's just use some crazy
number. Um let's say 80 to 90% of the
CME gaps on Bitcoin have been closed.
All right?
So, what that means is I'm expecting
price to at least come back and revisit
this area of $73,000.
Now, the question is is that going to
happen within the next 48 hours? Is it
going to happen while the market is in
complete turmoil?
Probably not. But I want to show you
guys why there is still a slight a
possibility. All right? This is the
interesting part. Because you guys know
I've been targeting the fact of 67,000
for quite some time. And I've had this
sort of played out this entire period.
Now, I'm going to make this chart as
easy as for you guys to see as possible.
So, if you can if you don't can't see
anything, please let me know. You guys
should be able to see every single thing
on my screen right now. We are six
viewers away from doing a giveaway. Just
an FYI. We hit 100, we do a giveaway.
So, you guys got to share this out
there. You got to pump it out to your
friends. You got to pump it on X. You
got to pump it on Insta. You got to get
six more people in here for us to do a
giveaway. Just an FYI. Make sure you're
dropping like and commenting. Now,
getting into this.
This is what I see happening. This is
what I explained to you guys last week.
Right? There's nothing new.
I'm going to delete this. I'm going to
run you guys through exactly what I'm
seeing here.
I told you guys last week we're probably
going to get the breakout. We've got the
breakout. But the time to get the FOMO
is you don't FOMO once you get the
breakout.
You wait for the retest to confirm the
actual hold of the structure. All right?
This bear flag has been in play for
quite some time. Price is trending
sideways. Okay? We broke below on the
bear flag. It got picked up. You can see
the fat order zone sitting there. Right?
Price picked up from that point. This is
where we got the ceasefire announcement
between 68,000 all the way up to 73,000.
This is where people FOMO.
Right? This is where market makers trap
retail traders off FOMO.
I'm going to show you guys this on the
4-hour time frame in a second. But I
said last week, I said you don't get in
on the FOMO. You get in on the retest if
you missed the pump. All right? The
retesting which was taking place was
expected around $70,000.
That is what is currently happening.
Now, let me make one thing clear. All
right? If this was any given other given
scenario,
I would already be opening positions
right now. And I'm still tempted because
the charts are telling me, you know
what?
If we can hold here, then we should be
able to clean up and close out that CME
gap at 73,000
before price retraces and closes to the
gap at probably 67,000.
Okay? That's just based off on the data.
Three people off, guys. We're about to
do a $100 giveaway. 100 USDT. Let's go
for it. Let's pump it to 100.
Um now,
this is what I see happening. This exact
move. You can see here we've got the
retest taking effect. If this holds and
it is successful,
then I do suspect Bitcoin to then trend
upwards towards $75,000.
Now, the way I sort of see this playing
out, we've got a couple of scenarios
that need to take effect. But this is
where it gets rather interesting. All
right?
What we're currently seeing happen here,
and I'm going to break this down on the
4-hour for you guys as well. All right?
This is where some more data starts to
come into play. All right? So, you can
see here when we had the ceasefire
announcements, we got all the FOMO.
Right? We were overpurchased on the CCI.
We then had multiple bearish divergences
kick in. Then we have the large dump.
Stock standard practice. These things
happened.
Now, some of the early confirmations
that I've got at the moment is
we're actually trending in a in a
positive reaction on the EMA. So, that's
the 50 EMA and the 200 EMA. Right? Means
the the average price of Bitcoin is
rising.
But we've actually created a nice order
zone. So, you can see here, guys,
multiple order zones have been
presenting themselves. As they present,
price then reacts. Price pushes up. What
this is signaling is the fact of buying
pressure at these specific locations.
This is live data. Okay? You can see
live transactional data, live order
zone, live order zone, and we currently
have another one
sitting here at $70,800,
where price is trending sideways. Now,
take into consideration the US market
has not opened yet.
All the price action that has happened
from Asia
and London is virtually irrelevant. Just
an FYI.
All right. Oh, we hit 101. All right.
We're doing a giveaway. So, to be
eligible for the giveaway before we keep
going, make sure you drop a comment.
That's where I pull the name from. All
right? Where I post the winner is on my
X and on my Instagram. Problem is right
now,
if these guys have suspended my X
account for absolutely no reason
possible because I actually don't shill
anything. I literally just post
educational pieces on X as well as my
own personal YouTube and my own profile
and stuff like that. So, I don't know.
Elon's maybe not liking the fact that
I'm actually going down the educational
stuff as opposed to clickbait, but we'll
see how that transpires. Transpires. So,
make sure you have hit me up on
Instagram because that's where I will
post the winner for this giveaway. Just
an FYI.
But, as I was saying, with an order zone
that presents itself here, this is now
telling me that buying pressure is in
play. You can see here the buyers are
overtaking the sellers. So, I'm watching
this level. Again, I've got early
confirmations. I've got a few weeks to
the bottom of the range,
but
this is where it gets complicated. And
this is why I haven't opened positions
yet. And I was talking about this with
my Empire community today, is any other
given situation, I would be full sending
stuff right now. What I mean by that is
I'd be opening a couple of positions,
and I'm going to show you guys what
tokens they specifically are, the ones
that I'm watching, because I'm not
looking at everything. I'm not charting
10, 20 different tokens hoping for the
very best to happen. I'm looking for
high conviction trades right now. Okay?
High conviction trades, what that mean
is I have strong probability in them
specifically playing out. Not only
because of their USDT pairing of what
I'm looking at, but but also the BTC
altcoin as well. I'm going to show you
guys what I mean by that in a second.
But, the reason I am hesitant
about opening large-scale positions at
the moment is simply because of this.
Okay?
The US 500 futures market is nearly down
a full percentage point already.
Okay? This is a big deal. Whether or not
you want to accept it or not, it is a
big deal. We have multiple order zones
created into the top of the range on the
US 500 futures market, which means
essentially that there is selling
pressure building from the top of the
range down. Now, I think personally it's
quite mind-blowing in the fact that
we're about 3 and 1/2% off an all-time
high on the US 500. I think that's
absolutely wild.
But, I want to show you guys something
else where
this is where
honestly, I don't want this to happen
because it is a very big destruction on
the markets if this was to occur. All
right? So, take this seriously and
really give me your feedback on it. I'm
happy to hear your thoughts, but this
part here is quite critical and
something that you guys need to be aware
of. All right? I've shared this chart
multiple times on my streams. I've shown
you guys how I've been able to depict
when previous bull markets have taken
effect. All right? You can see that here
when you get a really deep sell-off on
the CCI
off this trend line, you can see on
multiple occasions that's what's led to
the next bull market situation.
Now, where we are currently is you can
see we are very, very far away
from this trend line.
Okay? Very far. Very, very, very, very
far away. All right? Now, yes, we're
overpurchased on the CCI and we came
back and we retested this level here,
the 113 fib, and we've had a reaction
off that point. Okay?
But, as you can see, this trend is very,
[clears throat] very, very far away.
It's about a 20% drop.
Okay?
Now,
there's been some very big talks about
black swan events.
You know, we're getting very much a
whole global economy shift at the
moment. I don't know if you guys have
seen this either today, but Spain and
China, right?
There've all been a lot of tensions,
obviously, as you guys would know, as
across Europe at the moment. As this
loads, let me just show you guys this.
But, what's happening at the moment is
you're seeing global powers starting to
link up with unlikely allies.
Right? Spain is now speaking with China
on the basis of opening up European
exports because Donald Trump is
threatening Spain because they didn't
like the way they reacted. And Europe
and and essentially na- the US or NATO
is it's in it's in fractions at the
moment, right? It is starting to pull
itself away. There is so much
uncertainty in the world right now that
something like this,
where it drops 20% all of a sudden,
would be a total destruction in the
global markets, but also, I don't know
about you guys. Let me know in the
comments.
I don't think it's unheard of.
I think this is possible.
Right? Look, there's going to be
multiple trades in amongst this, right?
We're going to be able to pick some
stuff out. You know, I'm going to trade
with the trends and so forth, and and
just play my trades as I usually would.
But, I'm conscious of this, and I'm
conscious if that occurs,
this is my next target for Bitcoin. And
this is why why I'm going through one
scenario to the other because
if we start to get something like that,
I want to show you guys the next
possibility of what I have here.
It's really simple.
I love Fibonacci. You can see my
Fibonacci ratios, right?
Right now, we've had a run-up from the
bottom of this level here to the top of
this range.
Now, a common target when you get a big
reversal formation is
to see something like this.
You get the run-up.
You get the pullback. This pullback
needs to break back below the trend
line.
It does something like this.
And hits total destruction level.
Okay?
So,
when you look at this in this grand
scheme of things,
you go, well, we've had a major
rejection. If we fail to hold the trend
like I'm hoping for tonight, and the
reason I say hoping because again, US
market hasn't opened yet. We haven't got
enough confirmation. We've only got that
one order zone on the 4-hour time frame
that's starting to take effect.
But, if this doesn't hold tonight, and
oil prices continue to spike, which they
are, they're 9% nearly today, which
again has been a detriment to the global
economy,
and then the US 500 again is going to
wipe off potentially a trillion dollars.
Who knows? We'll see how that sort of
transpires.
If that happens, we know Bitcoin is very
much a risk-on environment and loves
that. Okay? If this occurs, then
we break back down to 67,000. We come
back and we close that CME gap that
we're talking about here as opposed to
revisiting 73,000.
And then if this does not hold,
then you can see that yes, there's been
a lot of buying pressure in here, and
65,000, which is where I've marked out
these circles earlier, right? 65,000
is realistically the next point of
support. Okay? The next big point.
But, if that fails, a big common target
with any particular market move is the
1618 Fibonacci level. That would bring
Bitcoin back back below $60,000.
And again, a massive wipeout and
destruction across the markets. Hence
why I did label this buy BTC.
And when I mean buy, it's B Y E, not B U
Y, right? Just as an FYI.
So, we're going to have to wait, and
this is why I'm saying to you guys,
there is so much uncertainty out there
at the moment. Even me personally,
I'm not in any particular trade. I
closed out a trade on Saturday. I'm
going to show you guys exactly what that
was. I walked through it on my entire X,
even though they suspended me now, but I
did put it inside Empire. So, you guys,
if you want, there's a link I've
provided by CoinBureau. You guys get 14
days for free, and it's actually free to
join up overall, and you can see all the
stuff me and my team are posting in
there.
But, as you guys will see here,
the two biggest scenarios right now,
make it very, very simple for everyone.
We hold and we retest, and we push up to
75,000.
Or alternatively, right? I'm going to
remove the fibs just to make it very
simple for everyone to see, is the
retest fails. We come back to this
point, 69,000,
and then we crash land back into 65
after closing the CME gap at around
$67,000, which again is quite obvious
from this chart here.
So, I wish I could tell you guys right
now, hey,
full scale, [clears throat] I've opened
up longs. Full scale, I'm opening up
shorts.
But, I can't because of the uncertainty
that's in effect here on the US 500. And
because again, we're already down on the
futures market nearly a full percentage
point, that'll cause mayhem. You've got
oil that has already spiked up again
um
9%. So, you can see the gap that's taken
effect there. You can see we've
basically just
smashed straight through everything. Um
In an ideal world, I'd love this to
happen.
Right? Come back to 100. Give us the
retest. That will push, hopefully,
Bitcoin as well alongside with it as a
bit of a, you know, risk-off, sorry,
risk-on appetite starts to produce
itself. But, I want to show you guys the
charts and the trades that I'm looking
at, right? The conventional trades, the
trades that I'm specifically watching to
play out right now, despite everything
that is happening. Okay?
So, we've made our target. So, I
appreciate you guys. I'm going to pull
someone from the comments. I'm going to
do a giveaway. I'm going to post it up
on my social. So, if you haven't done so
already, make sure you've liked me on
follow me on Instagram cuz that's where
I put the winner. Like I said, the last
two people I put out there did not claim
the prize, which
blows my mind. But, I've been keeping an
eye out hoping hoping hoping no one
claimed the prize. So,
um that sucks. So, hopefully the next
person claims their prize.
But,
I'm going to show you guys
two uh sorry, three particular trades
that I'm watching right now. All right?
One being Pepe.
Okay? I love this little frog token.
I love it because I've had a lot of
success trading it, right? Just the
other day, I'll show you guys quickly
just so you guys know I'm not
bullshitting you by any means necessary.
You can see I made a trade on this
literally on Saturday night. Um I
depicted the whole trade as I was going
through it, and I cleaned up $979 US
realized profit. All right?
The reason I jumped into this trade here
was quite simple. I'm going to break
this down for you guys as to why I also
took profit on it, and I find people
struggle the most with taking profit.
They don't push the sell button.
Okay?
I'll show you guys this one here.
And then I'm going to show you guys what
I'm looking for again to trade this
token. All right?
I was looking at this breakout point.
Okay? You can see this here. You got a
nice falling wedge into the daily level
support. And I captured this full move,
this full breakout. All right? At this
point here, there was an order zone
sitting here on the 1-hour time frame
that was sitting across that point
there. At that point, I was up about
$500 US. I didn't close the position cuz
I let this trade play out overnight,
right? A lot of my trades I let them
play out overnight when they're high
conviction trades. Anyway, what happens
from there? Bitcoin's comes back down.
I'm up about 10% or $100 on this
particular trade. I said, "No, I'm
sticking to my conviction cuz this is
just possibly just a retest of the
breakout." And you can see here on the
CCI, it was also oversold.
So, from that point,
it rockets. And my big early indicator
as to close my position, I closed that
position. You can see at 385.
You can see my position there was
basically closed at three
384.30. So, nearly right at the peak of
the top. Right? But, the reason I closed
that position there, this is a learning
curve, right? So, if you want to take
some notes, this is a good time to take
some notes. Okay?
When I see things like the CCI get to
plus 300 or plus 200 on the 4-hour time
frame, in particular plus 300 on the
1-hour time thing time frame, I know for
myself that that is a big extended move,
and it's probably time to take profit.
And not hope for the very best that
you're going to squeeze that last
2% out of the market. Versus what could
have actually happened and did happen is
the market then tanked 10%. So, again
guys, the message in this trade is don't
be afraid to take profit. There's always
another trade around the corner. And the
fact of the matter is if I did not take
profit, I would have had my stop loss
hit or back at entry point anyway.
Now,
what am I looking at on Pepe right now?
I'm going to show you guys this because
this is where I think it gets a little
bit juicier.
I'm watching this particular level on
Pepe. You can see this here, and I'm
just going to I'm going to open this to
make sure you guys can see my prices and
my price action. Okay?
Right?
On Pepe at the moment,
I'm waiting to see if we get a hold here
or some sort of confirmation because at
the moment you can see candles love to
hold this area or reject. And right now
we're on the other side of the range.
And right now you can see the CCI is
coming back to that midpoint range where
momentum tends to reset. Okay? Again
guys, TA works. Right? I hate the people
that say TA doesn't work. It's usually
the ones that don't know how to use it
properly and get destroyed using it.
Right? TA alongside liquidity and
understanding where the market movements
are across the global markets is quite
important. But, I'm looking at this at
the moment cuz as you can see here now,
right?
Price is basically holding the bottom of
this range, but it hasn't given me any
confirmation. I always look for three to
four confirmations to enter a position.
Right now, I do not have them. But, I'm
watching this particular trade at the
moment because from a risk to reward
ratio, it's at a quite a nice position.
And right now, you can see
that overall, even within this range,
it's 3%. A full-scale breakout is 14%.
Now, if this does not hold on the US
market open,
be very specific with my words right
now. I'm watching for the US market
open. I'm not rushing into anything. I
want to see how the US futures market
reacts, how oil prices react. Okay? If
that does not hold up,
then my target will be back down towards
here at 325
for Pepe. Because there's no point me
longing into resistance or longing into
the breakout with any conviction. I'd
rather get in off the support level. And
that's what I'm happy to wait for. Okay?
But, you can see from a longer-term
perspective, from February 2026, Pepe is
now breaking out of the downward trend.
Okay? So, that's what I mean by this is
why I'm looking at this as a high
conviction play. And I want to marry
this up with Ethereum. So, I want to
show you guys Ethereum. All right?
If you're enjoying this and you're
learning something, I can see now we're
hanging around the 100 mark. I
appreciate you guys for sharing the
stream out. Like I said, I'm going to do
a giveaway. I'm going to give away 100
USDT. So, if you haven't done so
already, make sure you comment, right?
Drop your Drop your Drop your username
into the comment section. That's where I
pull the winner, and I'm going to post
it on my social. So, if you haven't done
so, follow me on Facebook, X once my
account gets up on X, and Instagram.
That's where I post the winner.
But, you can see here this is the next
big one.
All right? This is the one I'm watching.
And the reason I'm watching, so my
experience in trade, I've been in
trading for 8 years now, 9 years nearly.
The crypto market loves to move in
waves, right? Bitcoin moves first, then
you get the larger altcoins running. And
the moment you start to see Ethereum
run, it starts to put a bit of sentiment
around the altcoins. Okay? And Ethereum
in itself has not been doing too bad.
I've been trading Ethereum and been
watching it quite closely. Now, look at
this.
Okay?
I want to show you guys this. A lot of
people haven't posted this yet. So, pay
close attention.
We had a big large-scale breakout on
Ethereum. You can see this is the bottom
of the range. It's pushed. Now, it's hit
a specific level that I love to focus
on, the 707,
and then the 618 on the fib level. All
right? This is the ETH/BTC chart for
everyone's reference. This is not
Ethereum/USDT.
This is Ethereum/BTC because if this can
move in an upwards direction alongside
Bitcoin moving up, then this thing is
going to go bananas, right? I like to
trade tokens that are moving in the same
way. You want to see the USDT pair
moving in positive correlation or
positively to the BTC pairing as well.
This is now broken out. Let me break
this down for you, right? It is starting
to break out.
So, what I'm watching here, there's an
8% move on this particular chart. Now,
take note of this. Okay? This is a good
place if you want to get pen and paper.
This is a good spot. Right?
Look at the ETH/USDT pair as well. This
is what we've been monitoring. So, if
you guys recall last week, I said to you
guys,
I'm watching Ethereum cuz I'm watching
for the breakout and I'm watching for
the retest and then the move. What
happened on Ethereum?
That exact play happened. Okay? You get
the breakout. We got the retest. You got
the push, which was 8%.
I I I don't I don't make this up. The
chart told me it happened.
I went with the chart. The chart moved
in the direction in which I was
interested in tra- in trading. Okay?
Now,
Ethereum and Pepe
tend to move side by side.
If you didn't know that, you can go
back, you can look at it. Once Ethereum
gets moving,
Pepe gets moving. Okay? Now, I can't put
my hand on my heart and say that happens
100% of the time because I'd be lying to
you. And again, that would mean like
it's some sort of definitive answer. I
cannot give that to you. But, when I
watch Ethereum,
I watch Pepe.
Okay? Now, I'm watching this again at
the moment because you can see we're
back down to this order zone that is
sitting here
at 200 and 2,160
dollars. You can see I've got multiple
alerts stacked there already. Right?
I'm watching for those alerts to get hit
because I think I can snag a deeper
entry on this, especially if the US
market opens up
again negatively on the futures market,
it should give me a deeper entry if I
want to look for any long positions.
And we can break this down a little bit
further.
There's an one alert alert on Ethereum
going off. There's also the 200 EMA on
the 4-hour time frame sitting around
2,132
dollars to be exact. So, again team, I'm
monitoring Ethereum.
I'm monitoring it for the rejection back
down towards the 50 EMA all the way down
to this order zone, but I'm not in it
currently.
Because A, I'm not in a position to
short at a level of support.
And if I was, I wanted uh you would want
to short off the top of the range, not
short into support levels. I never short
into support. Okay?
So, I'm watching this at the moment. You
can see it here. It's where price has
bounced off historically. We do have
positive correlations on the EMAs, you
know, the golden cross of 50 and the 200
trending upwards. So, again, this here
would be my particular move on Ethereum,
but given the fact that we do hold up
here on the US 500 as well. So, again,
the next 24 to 48 hours are critical.
So, take note of that. So, Pepe,
Ethereum are two of my high conviction
plays at the moment that I'm watching
for.
I'm going to show you guys one now
that I think has personally fallen off
the radars for a lot of people.
And it's one that I measured up today
with my Empire community that I'm
sharing with every single one of you.
And I looked at this on the monthly. I
looked at this on the weekly. I looked
at this on the daily.
And there was multiple correlation
points on this. And then I'm going to
jump into the comments, see what you
guys are talking about.
And that way I can show you this as well
because again, we smashed out some river
trades last week. One trade that will
pay for someone's whole week's worth of
wage. Happy days. Now we've got Iran and
the whole US situation going absolutely
ballistic again. Ceasefire's probably
about to be broken, you know, these guys
are already
Lebanon's been bombed as well. That's
causing a [ __ ] show. This guy thinks
he's Jesus at this current rate. Losing
my marbles over how this is going down.
But
the coin that I'm watching for at the
moment
which I think has fallen off a lot of
people's radar. Now tell me if you've
been watching this, I'm all ears. Please
tell me. I'm curious, right? But
it is BNB.
So
Binance we know is one of the biggest
global exchanges, well, the biggest
crypto exchange in the world. All right?
Now
>> [clears throat]
>> the level
in which I'm watching for BNB is A, of
course, I was never going to find them
by BNB at $1,400. That would be
basically complete suicide. Nuts. Right?
The level I'm watching on BNB is one of
my fun critical levels. The 707, the fat
order zone that is sitting here, and of
course the 200 weekly EMA, which also
lines up with the monthly 50 EMA as
well. I'm going to show you guys this on
the monthly because
this here to me
looks juicy.
Right?
I've got multiple alerts stacked here
already at 546
558.
As a collective
I think we should be monitoring this
very, very closely.
All right?
I'm going to be monitoring this. I've
got multiple alerts. I'm not going to
find them. I want to get a deep wick
into this area and I want to load a bag
of BNB.
And I think personally from a risk
perspective
that there for me
is definitely a high value trade.
Right?
Yes, we can draw the trend line. We can
draw bring it a bit lower.
But what's happened here is BNB has been
following the 50 EMA on the monthly.
This is also the big order zone that is
sitting here. So this is transactional
data. It's valid, right? Buyers and
sellers are at a battling point at this
point. It's also the retracement point
from this large-scale breakout that's
taken effect, which is the 707. So I am
watching BNB quite closely. You can see
we've got the daily order zone there. I
want to see a spike below.
I want to grab the wick.
Then I want this to run straight back up
and give me basically a 10% lead on this
particular move. So if you're in BNB
already, let me know in the comments.
I've been watching this for a while.
Again, it's now getting to a point where
I've got to closely monitor it and I
don't think a lot of people are talking
about BNB. And again, team, one of the
big things I'm watching for is high
conviction trades.
This here for me fits that category and
it also fits the fact of what I want to
be watching. I'm going to take a photo
of this. I'm going to post the chart. Uh
I'll post it up. I can't post it on X at
the moment, so I've got to post
everything in Empire. That's why I
created my own social media platform
because I'm sick of everyone banning
crypto people for absolutely nothing.
Like we're posting valid content.
So I'm going to post this up on there.
Um and a couple of other ones that I am
looking at at the moment is RV.
So I don't know if you guys have checked
out RV anytime soon. I'm going to jump
in the comments shortly, right? But if
you haven't checked out RV, have a look
at this token at the moment. The reason
being is this thing has been in a mass
downtrend for quite some time. Starting
to get some bullish divergence and what
I'm waiting for to see on RV
is realistically the breakout here.
The this range is 40% on RV.
Okay? Again, we've got to be patient
because I want to get in around the $85
mark, right? So I want to get that wick
to the bottom of the range. I don't want
to enter in the middle here. I want to
get based upon the bottom here on RV.
You can see from a weekly time frame
this is where the midpoint of the order
zone is as well. All right? So I love to
target those areas because again, that's
where I see strong levels of support.
Okay? I don't like to buy in thin air
and hope for the very best. I want to
get in at around $85, right? I use data.
I use my TA. That gives me my entry,
okay? And I do not find do not rush. You
could not make me find me into any
market ever. Like my former days are
dead and dusted. I don't care.
Right?
That's what I'm watching for on RV. So
again, guys, I've given I've I've
presented the fact that Pepe is one of
my high conviction that I'm watching
for. ETH is the other one.
Um BNB is the next big one. RV is one
that I'm watching very closely as well.
And for those of you D gens that love to
trade ZEC
I've got my um my retracement target on
ZEC at the moment is around $300 as
well. That's what I'm watching for to
take place. I've already got alerts set
here as well because I'm not going to
find my by the top of the range as you
can see here at plus 300 on the CCI.
What did I do plus 300 last time? I took
profit. That's what other people have
done or valid traders. I want to see
this come back down, retest cuz you can
see now on this also
this is also broken the downtrend
had a large-scale breakout
and now the expectation would be a
retest back towards around the $300 mark
as well. So I've got a I've got a um
a chart on this that I'll post up later
on as well. So
I'm going to jump over to the comments
now. Give me one section session.
Um I want to make sure I cover off any
questions. Make sure you guys have also
dropped your comments in the chat
because that's where I'm going to pull
the winner from as well. Now, full
transparency, it does take about 24 to
48 hours for YouTube to render the
stream because I do present live and I
use a software called OBS. So by the
time it goes through, it then takes
about like I said, 24 48 hours, but I do
post the winner on my socials every
single time. Um what have we got here?
Let me just have a look. Solana, XRP,
people wanted to know.
Um
let me have a look. What else do we
have?
XRP and Solana. Everyone wants All
right, let me show you guys XRP and
Solana, all right? I'll show you guys
what we've got there and put it in the
comments. Did you guys want me to do a
$100 USDT straight off giveaway or two
$50 ones? All right? Completely up to
you. The ball's in your court. All
right? It's completely up to you guys.
Whatever you guys want. I don't mind.
All right? Friendly that way. Whatever
you guys want, we'll do. Now
I'll show you guys what I've got on XRP,
the wonderful retail token.
I'm a bit cautious on XRP at the moment.
Straight out, I'm very cautious on this
token because despite any sort of
reasonable market movements
it actually has not performed all that
well. Now this chart might look a little
bit scattered. Might be a little bit
going on, but keep it really simple for
you guys.
It's trending on the um
November 2024 support. It's also below
the 200 EMA. It's also below the 707
level, which is never a great sign
because ultimately what this opens up is
essentially a free fall of about 16%
back towards about a dollar 10.
Okay?
The only positive factor I can see here
is if price can get back above. Sorry,
let me just move this in.
The only positive factor I can see here
is if XRP jumps back above 136 and
actually holds with some conviction and
then actually closes above the 200
weekly EMA. But if you look to the left
here, again, this is why the data is so
important.
You can see that once price starts to
get trapped below this level
it really opens up the avenue of a
potential a large-scale drop and it's
happened historically on XRP. Okay? Now
where it is at the moment, I for me this
isn't a high conviction trade. All
right? This isn't something that I'm
seeing positive action on. It's not
something I'm seeing, you know, it's
we're going to see a reversal. They've
got I've got no validation. I've got no
confirmation of anything right now. And
even on the XRP BTC chart, you can see
now it's completely failing. It's back
below the the weekly support levels.
You're getting the um
the EMA starting to cross bearish as
well, getting very close to that point.
I personally do not have any
high-level conviction to open up any
positive longs on XRP as it currently
stands. It's not something I'm trading.
I'd rather get into Pepe or or
or ETH for the time being because the
chart looks cleaner.
Not so much I believe in the projects.
Like I don't care about the projects. I
care about what the chart's telling me.
That's what I'm looking at.
And the last one, Solana. I spoke about
this today uh with my team, but you can
see this on Solana at the moment. Uh we
had the failed breakout which happened
like last time. You can see that here.
We had a failed breakout again. You get
the rejection. Now ultimately it opens
up the gap again to head back towards
about the $78 mark. Simple breakout
failed.
Ultimately needs to it's retesting at
the moment, but again, if this does tank
the US market like we're expecting
then this would likely pull back towards
the $78 mark as well. So
pretty straightforward sort of stuff.
Don't really need to overcomplicate that
one. Um but again, team, I've gone for
45 minutes now. I am so happy to see
every single one of you on the call. We
smashed out through 100 again. I
appreciate you all. Please, if you're
enjoying this, share this with your
friends. Hit me up on the socials.
Again, I'll post the winners on there.
I'll get everyone's usernames as well.
And I appreciate all your support. You
know, I focus heavily on keeping an
unbiased reaction within the markets.
I'm very technical with the way I trade.
I'm not your typical influencer that's
going to shill a whole bunch of crap and
share random stuff. Whatever I share is
what I'm personally looking at, what I'm
personally doing. And I appreciate you
guys all for the support because it's
been a great couple of weeks and we're
really starting to ramp up on the
stream. So, thank you very much. I hope
you appreciate it and I'll catch you
guys on Wednesday. All the best and
smash it. See you later.