Bitcoin is starting to show its first
real cracks, signs that it's going to
reverse. I've been warning you guys that
this is going to be happening. We're
slowly seeing it unfold. There's still a
chance that we could actually push up a
little bit higher, but to be honest, a
pivot high moment seems like the most
likely outcome. How low could Bitcoin go
from here? And uh are we really going to
see that drop to 49K or actually
$38,555?
And why those numbers? All of that here.
and more on Coin Beer Trading. What's
up? My name is Aaron Disher from the
Better Traders. You're watching Coinb
Trading. Hit the subscribe button, like
the video. Let's get into it right away.
Now, I'm going to give you guys the
bullish scenario first. Um, I also want
to start with this elephant in the room.
Um, a lot of people on X have been
raving and super excited about Bitcoin
breaking above overhead resistance. Now,
you'll notice on my chart, it doesn't
appear like that. That's because I never
ever ever
use linear scale. I'm always using log
scale because linear looks like garbage
with crypto charts mainly because of
well charts like this. It just doesn't
really help me. It doesn't inform me. It
doesn't give me a good idea. It's not
too pretty. Whereas a logarithmic chart,
it's still insane. Rave is just a joke
right now. Anyway, um so that's the
first thing is that if you're using log
scale like I am, no. Bitcoin actually
hasn't pushed above overhead resistance
yet. Now, you can groan, you can gripe,
you can whail about this. It's just the
fact. Now, do I ever, listen carefully,
do I ever switch my charts from log to
linear? No. Never. I don't even look at
linear scale for anything. If you guys
watch my videos, you've been watching
for a long time, you know I don't use
linear for anything. It doesn't make
sense to me. So, with that in mind, no,
we have not seen the price of Bitcoin
come up to test overhead resistance.
But, you know what would be a really
good target if Bitcoin finally got a
magical push up higher? It would be most
likely today, immediately today at
$77,300.
Now, maybe Saturday 776K. Hey, do I hear
75 74? But that's the next logical
target. Now, the other thing to consider
is the TBO, which stands for the
trending breakout indicator. Why is this
relevant? Why am I bringing it up? Well,
four years ago in the previous bare
market, in the previous bottom year, we
saw the price of Bitcoin rally up from
below the cloud at 37K all the way up to
48K, just a little bit above, that's
right, the daily TBO cloud. So, if
Bitcoin were to actually have an insane
extra leg up higher, which isn't very
likely, but if it were to happen, the
top of the cloud is always going to be a
great level of resistance or a
termination a termination zone to watch.
The other thing to consider though is
that even back here in 2022, the
direction or the angle of the slow line
tells me which way the chart is going to
go. Just like right now, if we zip ahead
to where we are, the slow line, while it
is admittedly not as strong bearish as
it was back over here in March, it's
actually flattened out, meaning that the
angle isn't so vertical. Now, it's
slowly moving a little bit more
horizontal, I guess you could say.
But is it really flat? Nah, it's it's
still pointing down. Is it slowing down?
Yes. But is it like going up or flat?
No, not yet. So that's the other thing
that I keep looking at in terms of price
action. The fact that the slow line,
while it's not pointing down admittedly
as strongly as it was before back over
here in late March, it's still pointing
down. Putting a gun to my head, that's
down. I know it's slowing down, but it's
down. Okay. The other thing to consider
is that daily RSI, which I always use
RSI with a length of seven because it's
a lot more responsive for crypto charts.
Again, the default is RSI with a length
of 14, which might work well for stocks,
but for crypto, RSI 7 works really well.
We saw RSI go um overbought on Thursday,
yesterday at 70.76 and then earlier this
week on or rather Saturday, not earlier
this week but Saturday, April 11th at
73.37.
Before that we had 76.83. Before that we
had 82.07. Before that we had, you get
the idea. These are all higher levels,
but each high
is just a little bit lower, as in lower
highs.
The expected natural response for price
action after seeing weaker highs over
and over and over is to see RSI go a lot
lower. Now, we saw a tease of this back
with a low on the 29th of March where
BTC
went down to about here, 65K.
It invalidated our bare flag, which you
notice I haven't talked about anymore.
And just because something is
invalidated doesn't mean that the bare
flag wasn't a good call to begin with.
It just got invalidated, which is okay.
And I am not ever going to say, well,
because it was invalidated here, that
means we have to draw it out. We have to
move things around. No, it doesn't work
like that with bare flex. At least in my
opinion. No, no, no, no, no, no, no. So,
it was invalidated when the price went
above. Great. But that leaves us with um
another thing to be watching, which is
our support fan. Now, whether or not you
believe in support fans or not, it
doesn't really matter. Our support fan
is based off of an initial pivot low.
Okay? So, we have our low on the fee
February 6th low. We have a low here on
uh March 29th. What we do after that is
we draw successively
higher support levels based off of the
next successive pivot low over and over
until it just doesn't make sense
anymore. What will happen with this
inevitably as well is that support's
going to go way more vertical. And these
very very vertical support levels or
resistance levels if we were to invert
the chart are obviously going to be the
first ones to be broken. But the first
ones to break create the new trend, I
guess you could say. Let me show you
what I mean. So, going back over here,
February 6th, February 24th, we have
another low. We're just going to draw it
out cuz it's going to be a little bit
prettier. And then we have another
support low right there. So, see what
happens to price as soon as it pulls
back from here. If you really want to be
really annoying about it, I guess you
could do this, but it doesn't really
make that's like too vertical. Uh, for
the sake of an example, we'll just do
it. We finally have that big first
crash. All right, we see price
respecting this previous support fin
kind of sort of. But you can see how
price on this level right here, which is
much more convincing to me, at least in
my opinion. Seeing the price pierce but
struggling to break above, that's a
great sign. And then we see it breaking
lower, breaking lower until it pushes up
higher. Okay, but we're not focused on
those support levels. We're focused on
these support levels. So, the main level
to watch literally right now today is
$73,700.
If Bitcoin
wicks below this level, which is a
pretty strong possibility given the fact
that, if you didn't already notice,
Thursday's low at $73,39.
If we were to just take that and drop it
over, that would be below this first
support fan line, then it creates a
pretty good opportunity for BTC to crash
below this first level and at least come
down here to the second one. Now, what's
wild is if we think about time
and how long this is taking. If we break
below something like this,
by the time we get here to Monday the
20th, which isn't that far away, it's
only a couple days away, that means that
Bitcoin would be just above this little
pivot move here on the 12th of April.
And with the TBO, it would be very much
already hitting the fast line, if not
the bottom of the cloud.
Now, does this mean that this is the
next real big pivot move where we see
Bitcoin get down to those crazy levels
that I just shared with you? Well, to be
honest, I really already went over the
game plan a while ago. Uh on the 10th, a
week ago on Friday, I talked about the
fact that I was predicting Bitcoin
dominance would shoot up higher, which
it did. And once we saw Bitcoin
dominance top out, most likely dominance
would shift to others and alts, which
happened yesterday. So the next thing to
logically happen is for Bitcoin to roll
over. So I I really encourage you to
watch that video to get up to date on
that. But before you watch that, check
out the links down below in this
description on that video's description
to sign up and trade on Tubbit where you
can earn over 15,000 USDT. There are
also way more deals available on the
Coinbe website. If you go to the deals
button here, there are lots of tools,
resources, services, wallets, uh trading
bots, even educational courses like our
course 50 minutes of financial freedom
from the better traders where you get a
10% off discount.
So definitely check out the links down
below.
The thing that I'm paying attention to
that I made mention of on Tuesday this
week is fear and greed. Now, Fear and
Greed actually moved up. I wish they
would change the scale for this. It
doesn't look so great. On Tuesday, it
was up at 21. On Wednesday, 23. Wait, am
I right? Yep. 23. Oh my gosh, I can't
speak. On Wednesday, I was up 23. And
what's really weird is that it held the
same level two days in a row.
It could be nothing. It could be
something. I don't but it's very very
weird to see the fear and greed index
just kind of park and pause at 23. The
wild part about all this if you really
think about it looking at price action
which is feeling really good, right? Can
you admit a little bit that even though
me as a bear I can admit like wow like
the sentiment is really really high
right now which is strange because when
you look at the crypto fear and greed
index we're still at extreme fear which
is really really weird. Um, so there's a
massive disconnect in terms of the
comfort level of the market where
everyone is satisfied and happy right
now and we're at extreme fear. That
should be a massive massive red flag to
you. Uh, you don't even need support
resistance levels. You don't even need
RSI or to look at previous mark markets
or historical markets. That's a big
problem. the fact that people are very
content and happy with this move up,
which isn't really that big of a move.
Could it push up higher? It it always
could. There's always going to be a
chance. All right. But the reality is
that I think it makes more sense for
Bitcoin to fall lower given the fact
that we're very very similarly
positioned like we were back in the
middle of March. By the way, a month
ago, as in Monday, March 16th, is when
we saw this, well, first green candle
and then we saw on Tuesday, literally a
month ago, a pivot where we saw Bitcoin
drop about 14%. I still think that we
could see another move down 14% if not
lower. And that brings me to some much
lower targets.
The reason why I still think that
Bitcoin can go lower is because it has
in the past. But before it even gets
there, there's a lot of these levels
right here. These successive support
levels on the chart for BTC are the
first ones that got to get knocked out.
And we actually have another level right
here. Although it's very, very flimsy to
call this a level, but anyway. Actually,
I want to delete. I don't like it. So,
our first level to take out is right
here at $70,400. It's a 6% move. While
that might feel like a lot, and
especially if we get down here, like
that's 13%. Wait, didn't I just didn't I
just talk about that being a
possibility? Here's the thing. When we
start to get these bearish drops, like
back over here on the 17th of March, we
saw Bitcoin lose 11% over the span of 6
days. I know it says five, just trust
me, it's actually six candles. Okay,
that kind of a move is not ridiculous or
strange to see at all for BTC. In fact,
it even went lower than that. There's a
really good chance that Bitcoin could
drop 14%. And it doesn't even have to be
over six days. It could be over two
days. Um,
the other things to consider are the
artificial support levels, which Bitcoin
has admittedly been doing really well
with this historical level at 74,58,
which is from April. I'm still very
surprised and impressed with the fact
that BTC has closed above it and it's
still kind of dancing around this level.
That's wild to me.
But I still think that Bitcoin can go a
lot lower. One of the other reasons why
I think we can go lower is that Bitcoin
has historically, as in the last three
bare market years, 2022, 2018, 2014, the
bare markets have lasted at least 52
weeks, if not longer than 52 weeks. I
believe the 2022 bare market was 54
weeks. The 2018 one was 52 weeks. And
I'm pretty sure the 2014 market, the
bare market actually started, it just
took a lot. Actually, it was 2014 to
2015. So, it took over a year. Took
something like 60 weeks.
And we're only
sadly right now. You actually don't want
to know this. Trust me. But we aren't
there yet at all.
Right now, we are only on week Oh, come
on. I hate when that happens. You click
it and you think it's working. It's not
working. We're on week 28 right now out
of a 52- week bare market approximately.
So, out of this entire span of time,
we're still waiting for the market to be
done
about the beginning of October. And I
know it's a really easy argument to to
say, "No way that's happening.
Bitcoin's in a super cycle right now."
I've seen lots of people actually say,
"No, no." See, like this back over here
in 2021 when Bitcoin fell 50%, it shot
up even higher. People wouldn't be able
to handle that. People won't be able to
handle that kind of a a draw down
comeback. We're down 50%, just like last
time. We're going to go up even higher
this time to 250. Are you guys ready for
250? And everyone starts sounding like
Macho Man Randy Savage all of a sudden.
What I find the most interesting is that
I've been seeing so many accounts,
so many bull posting right here.
The bottoms in um 250k next 300,000 by
the end of 2027.
All this garbage. Now, are we at a
shortterm reversal? Yeah. Like we've
seen a good bounce. Admittedly, it's a
good bounce. But the problem is that
every single bare market sees a bounce,
multiple bounces, if that. If we go back
to 2022, we saw multiple decent midcycle
rallies. There are two backtoback ones
over here. The first one in January, the
next one in March, we saw kind of a r,
not really, I'm not going to say it's a
rally at all, but like right here after
we bottomed, we saw a rally of like 43%
which was really good. saw this one. It
moved up 23% and that was it. So, I
mean, it's not unusual to see Bitcoin
have these bounces, these little mini
rallies. The same thing happened back
over here as well. Um, actually all
throughout 2018, we had massive, massive
recoveries, but that's because volume uh
was way down, which means volatility can
be way higher uh with an immature
market. So,
is it weird that Bitcoin is bouncing
right now? No. And I'm going to tell you
because I was there. Every single one of
these pumps right here, people were
saying super cycles in. Bitcoin's going
to go to $40,000 next. We're
everything's going to go up so much
higher. It's never going to stop. Every
single one of these rejections, people
were like, "Nah, nah, nah. It's going to
go up so much higher." No one was ready
for this right here. No. Absolutely. I
can tell you right now,
this is one event that's burned into my
brain, into my memory. In November,
everything just absolutely crashed. If
we go back to fast forward 4 years, same
sentiment, same thinking. When we saw
the market starting to bounce, people
are starting to get really cocky,
especially here in in March. Then we see
all this contagion, all this collapse,
all these bankruptcies and stuff. Then
the market finally bottoms out. People
started to get really bullish here and
it crashes. Really bullish. I got
bullish here in September, October
thinking, "Okay, great. We're done.
That's it." And it even fell again.
It It matters, guys. The duration of the
market matters so much more than you
realize. We're still not there yet.
Now,
yes, we've seen some pretty incredible
events so far. Let me just go ahead and
delete these guys for a second. I I
still think that we're not there yet. I
still think we're in for more pain. I
still think that it's not just going to
be 60K, but I think the next pivot low
at 49K and then finally 3855, that seems
like a reasonable target for multiple
reasons. And I'll say it again because
why not? We take our high at 1262,000.
Sorry, 126,200.
If we go down here, that's 69K.
Sorry, 69K. Oh my gosh. 69
69%. Which is an improvement from 2022's
drop of 77% which is an improvement from
2022's drop, which was 84%. So 84, 77,
70. It's a good target. It matches with
this little pivot low. Maybe a little
bit lower cuz stops are going to get
triggered. So maybe around 37K. I I know
a lot of people are going to continue to
argue with me in the comment section and
it's fine. It's totally okay. I could be
1 million% wrong.
But I I've been doing this just a little
bit longer than most of you. And when
I'm looking at the sentiment right now,
I'm looking at fear and greed still at
extreme fear. But given the timeline and
the sentiment, everyone is super excited
right now. Everybody seems to be like,
"Woohoo! Here we go. We're going to go
back to 80K, 88K, 100K, 120K. Do I hear
a $250,000?"
Like
people getting played real hard right
now. Okay. I've already laid the game
plan. April, we have a rally and then
unfortunately May and June, historically
speaking, in a bare market, it goes low.
It's red. It's red. In 2022, it's red as
well. In 2018,
hopefully we bottom before then. This is
just brutal watching all this chop. The
important thing to keep in mind right
now is account preservation. I've seen
so many weird random charts pumping up
hundreds of percent right now. Do I feel
FOMO? Nope.
Because I'm again of the belief that
we're going to go lower. And if that's
the case, these charts that are popping
are going to dump right back down. Look,
I'm going to explain why I don't have
any sense of emotion or feeling like
there's no way like I'm going to miss
out. I need to buy right now. Look at
the chart of FF. Ladies and gentlemen of
the jury, I present to you FF
single day pump 150%
back over here a week ago and it's just
about to fully retrace all the way back
down.
And you think that these coins that are
pumping today right now are just going
to keep pushing up higher. They're never
going to have a pullback. These pumps
are super organic and news-driven,
quality driven. They're actually
contributing something to the ecosystem.
Right now, it's a game of cat and mouse.
And right now, it really feels like the
cat is away, and the mice are at play
pumping and dumping charts left, right,
and center.
Where's the cheese? I don't see any
cheese right now. I don't see any end. I
don't see any reward or goal. All I see
are random pump and dumps, which you
guys should also know. Well, look at the
history of bare markets. There will be
pump and dumps because
Bitcoin dominance is falling. And as
it's falling, then we're going to see
alts just flash left like all over the
place. It happened in 2018. It happened
a little bit in 2022. Not so much during
the year, but at the end or like from
summer on it did for sure. Understand
pump and dumps do not reflect demand. It
does not reflect quality. It does not
reflect
an actual viable product. And sometimes
a good project will literally get pumped
and dumped. It's just how it goes. They
can't say no to that.
You just have to be a little bit more
skeptical, I guess. So again, I think
that this is still a very strong chance
that Bitcoin rolls over from here. I
swear to God, my handle is not
incorrect. It does say moon and papa. I
know a lot of you don't believe me. You
think that I'm doom and papa. I get it.
But I've been telling you from November,
warning you about 2026, which is a
bottom year. And we're waiting for
Bitcoin to bottom in 2026. And once it
does, trust me, I'm going to go back to
being moon and puppet. But right now,
I'm doing everything in my
everything in my control to preserve my
portfolio to stack sats. Actually, I'm
staking to earn a passive yield because
that's been my plan all along. And then
once we get signs of a bottom, I'm going
to be placing my bids. I'm going to be
dcing. And I will let you guys know
exactly why and what I'm going to be
invested in. All that fun stuff. But you
have to stay subscribed. You have to
have notifications turned on. All that
good stuff. The important thing is not
to rush. Bare markets are not in a rush
to get over. All of us that are traders
are in a rush to get it over with. The
bare market can go a lot longer than all
of us have patience for. Just trust me.
Okay? You're going to want to watch the
video that I mentioned before about
Bitcoin dominance because that same
exact thing is playing out literally
right now. You need to know how it ends.
Watch this. Until the next time, you
know what to do. Stay awesome and stay
in the green. Peace.