We need to talk about the total ES
chart. The crypto total market cap
excluding stable coins just did
something yesterday that is extremely
exciting. Even though we might get a
short-term rally, I'm still expecting a
drop in the wider crypto market because
of this chart. We're going to get into
that and way more this video here on
Coinb Trading. What's up? My name is
Aaron Dishner from the Better Traders.
You're watching Coin Bureau Trading. Hit
the like button on this video, subscribe
if you haven't, and let's get into it
right away over here on Trading View.
The first thing to focus on in terms of
price action for Total ES is this level.
Now, this level of support established
on the 6th of February when we had our
massive dump and our recovery and then
we had our higher low here on the 24th
of February.
Several things have happened since it
was established on the 24th of February.
just a couple days later it was pierced.
It was tested a lot later in March and
then finally the the price which is
really a market cap but the price closed
below this level of support.
Since closing below that level of
support here on Friday, March 27th,
we've seen several tests and pierces of
this level, namely here on the 1st of
April, and then more recently Monday's
candle. [gasps]
The reality is that I still expect a
bearish outcome for this chart mainly
because it's not just a support level.
This is actually a bare flag.
It's textbook bare flag to be honest.
And the reason why I say that is because
a bare flag has successively higher lows
and higher highs until we get a break of
support. And what happens is that the
price falls down and it tests previously
lost support confirming it as
resistance. This happened once and now
twice.
Just to refresh your memory, this bare
flag concept is exactly I repeat exactly
how the last dump just or not just but
how it happened, how it unfolded. Okay,
so yes, we saw many tests and pierces to
the top side. But what happened over
here? We saw here on total ES once
support was established even though
basic basically it was here but that
would change the angle and ruins a bunch
of stuff like this.
[laughter]
[sighs and gasps]
No, [clears throat] let's keep this.
This is even this is even better.
Why am I laughing you ask? Because it
doesn't matter. It It's still a bare
flag. The price go insane.
The price broke below support, tested
it, pierced it many times, even rallied
up a lot higher here in January and
again in the middle of January, except
it failed to close back and hold inside
until finally it lost it. It lost the
plot. Now, let's just say that this is a
support level. Well, it's funny what
happens when you see a big drop of
support. It's a big break, comes back
up, and it dumps.
We're literally looking at this take
two. In terms of other indicators right
now, the trending breakout indicator,
the TBO, remains strong bearish. The
macro trend indicated by the slowest
moving average here, the TBO slow line,
which is at 2.45 trillion at the top, is
still pointing down. As long as this
line is pointing down, it's macro
bearish.
If we look at the RSI reading,
we recently saw it put in a slightly
higher high on Sunday the 5th at 56.11
compared to 55.99.
Again, a difference of what, like 12.12.
It's not a massive difference. The main
thing is that we were already overbought
here on the 16th of March. We broke
support, put in a low. We have a lower
high over here on the 25th of March. We
have a lower low on the 29th of March.
We got a technically a higher high on
the 5th of April. But I mean, it's
marginally higher. It doesn't really
make that much of a deal to me or a
difference,
which means I'm expecting RSI to go
lower. And the only way that RSI goes
lower is if the crypto total market cap
excluding stable coins drops lower. as
in down here to support at uh according
to the TBO 1.9 trillion.
Now, what will this do to the total
market cap? What will this do to
Bitcoin, Ethereum, Solana, everything
else? I'm going to get into that in a
second, but before I do, you guys,
there's never been a better time to be a
trader in crypto. I know that these
markets can be exhausting.
Don't worry, because if we keep the same
52- week bare market pattern from 2018,
2017 to 2018, then 2021 to 2022,
guys, it's okay. We only have 6 months
left. We're halfway done. Doesn't it
feel great? But I'm serious. We're going
to have so many great fake outs
this month. Probably going to see a
rally, short rally.
But I'm telling you that May and June
are going to be rough for BTC
statistically speaking.
But with that said, there will be there
will be opportunities for you to make
some good money trading. Why not start
trading now using Tubbit, which has a
crazy campaign where you can sign up and
earn to trade over 15,000 USDT. You
should also start considering
what um Slush Wallet coins you want to
start accumulating, whether it's Sooie,
whether it's Deep or Walrus.
I already made a video about this last
Friday. This is a great strategy to
start employing. You could even start
now where you're basically staking and
earning a yield on a single token pair.
So, if you feel like the bottoms in for
Suie, then now is a great time to sign
up for your free slush wallet. So, that
way you're not just buying and holding
Sooie Deep or Walrus, you're actually
staking it and you're earning a yield on
that. Plus, there are way more deals
available on the Coinbeer website. If
you go to deals, there are other
exchanges, other wallets, bots and bot
trading, crypto tools, as well as a 10%
off course, sorry, 10% off coupon for
our course at the better traders uh 15
[snorts] minutes to financial freedom.
Now going back to the charts, the main
thing that you have to know right now is
even though we might see a potential
rally for total ES, understand that the
weekly chart is the clearest bearish
chart that you could possibly look at
right now.
Yes, last week closed up green. Yes, we
saw a big pivot from TBI support here at
about 614 billion moving up
substantially substantially to 1.96
trillion. That is a huge move. And the
last time something like that happened
to be completely fair was back over
here.
I have to change the scale from 119
billion all the way up to 771 billion.
But do you notice what happened back
over here in July? Even though we did
see a nice 30% rally, it gave it all
away, struggled, and dumped even lower.
I actually think we're going to see
another leg down. And I'll tell you why.
For starters, we are below the weekly
TVO cloud. So, no matter how many times
this moves up higher, the reality is
that as long as total ES is below the
weekly cloud, this means that we are
strong bearish. This means that the
total crypto market cap already flashed
these warning signals which I shared
with you guys way back in October saying
danger danger like this is not a good
sign. I told you
TBO closed long. Not good. This is not
good. Very bad. And then we had our
cross down. Then we had our confirmed
open short right here on the 22nd of
December when most of you were thinking
that BTC and the total market was going
to be pumping a lot higher. Did we get a
rally? We did for 13%. But was this the
right open short signal? Absolutely it
was. Now something you have to see is we
have to zoom out to the previous bare
market. I want you to see how long it
took from the previous open short on the
25th of April until the open long
printed. It was 62
weeks
from this symbol back here in April 2022
until the market finally bottomed out
here in November, it was another 30
weeks.
So for all of you that are believing
even if we get a rally, which is going
to fool so many people right now, we are
only 15 weeks in. there is an extremely
high chance that we continue to go lower
instead of higher.
Not to mention the fact that draw down
for this bare market so far is subpar.
It actually doesn't cut it compared to
previous bare markets. If we measure
from 2017 December
Oh, I can get it. Come on. Come on.
There we go. down to December 2018. An
88% draw down measuring from here in
November 2021 to November 2022.
Again, that's a nice 52- week long bare
market. When was this? This is January
to December. Almost 52 weeks, but
basically it was 50 weeks. Here we have
a
52- week bare market.
So again, this is where I struggle with
a lot of people getting really excited.
Even if we get a rally, for starters, be
the total ES chart has only fallen 55%.
Well below the normal draw down for a
bare market. [clears throat] Also, we
are not in that range. Remember I said
like 50 weeks, 52 weeks. If we're taking
the top here, drawing it out to where we
currently are right now this week, we
are only on week 26, literally about
halfway there.
This is the part of the ride where
everyone's like tapping like the sides
of the car saying like, "I want to get
off now. I'm I'm done. I'm ready to get
off." No, no, no, no, no. Once the ride
stops, no amount of crying is going to
make the conductor stop the ride. This
is where the ride is finally going to
get interesting. We've already had a big
draw down. It makes way more sense for
the total ES chart which mimics the
total crypto market cap and also for BTC
to have a 52 week bare market ending
about the first week of October 2026
which still means we have 26 weeks left
and seeing draw down of and again if we
just go 7 8 78 we'll just say 68%.
That would mean moving down here to 1.26
trillion, which I actually think it's
going to be more, but it means that
we're not there yet. It means that the
market should still fall another
38%. I know it's really difficult to see
because these are overlapping. [sighs]
[clears throat]
What is this going to mean for Bitcoin
and Ethereum and everything else? Well,
it means more downside continuation. It
means a bigger drop for BTC. means a
bigger drop for Ethereum. A lot of
people still don't believe me. A lot of
people think, "Oh, the price right now
of Bitcoin is holding at the November
2021 high at 69K. We should be buying
here like crazy. It's not a bad idea to
start accumulating, but like going all
in, nah." And the reason why I say nah
is because if we do the same thing,
everyone was thinking, "Well, there's no
way in this bare market. I cannot tell
you." And actually, all the receipts are
online. And you can look at X, you can
look at YouTube videos. If you just go
back in time, no one thought that the
draw down from the November 2021 high
would ever go below the previous
all-time high in December of 2017.
What happened? Well, funny you ask. The
price definitely did. Initially, it
bounced back and then it went even
lower.
Don't think that just because Bitcoin is
bouncing right now off the previous
market top that it can't go lower. It
can definitely go lower. And I've been
saying this for a long time and I don't
mind repeating myself, but my targets
have been wide out in the open for a
long time. 60K is next. Then it's going
to be a swift kick down to 49K. will
probably be bottoming out worst case
scenario at 38,555.
Why do I say that? Because the draw down
from our October
2025 high down to 38,555
bucks is approximately 69%.
Well within the realm of it being a very
possible draw down considering we had
84% then 77% then looking at 69%. So
it's, you know, draw downs decreasing by
7% for each bare market. I think that
seems like a good target. 38K. So sub
40K
even though BTC is kind of sort of
holding for now. Trust me, it's it's
done this many times before back in
2022. And it's not just BTC, it's also
the total ES chart. A lot of other
charts kind of found their footing in
January 2022, even having a rally, only
to give it away. Now, I will admit the
main distinction between then and now,
was mass contagion. During this time, we
saw the collapse of Teral Luna. We saw
the bankruptcy of Celsius, BlockFi, and
FTX way over here, and countless other
fiascos like Three Arrows Capital. It
was bad.
This time around, we don't really have
any of that contagion. And for that, I'm
happy, but it doesn't mean we get a get
out of jail free card. If BTC goes
below, rather the market cap exceeds the
low from early February, guess what's
going to happen? Margin calls, DATs or
digital asset treasuries are going to
get their positions called. They're
going to try to raise funding to get
themselves out of the hole that they've
ducked themselves into. It's not going
to go well.
The dangerous thing about where we are
right now in the bare market, given the
fact that we're only 26 26 weeks in to a
potentially 52 week long bare market, is
complacency. I wish I had an animation
to go, [gasps] but I'm serious. In the
same way, in the same way that people
back in October, oh, sorry, let's back
it up. August and September and early
October before the crash and even after
the crash, everyone was so complacent
with the price up there, thinking, well,
it's going to go up higher. It just has
to. No one was paying attention to the
signs of growing weakness.
Now, we could say the same thing here
for the bullish case, except for the
problem is that everyone is complacent
and happy with the prices right now. You
don't understand the level of fear that
I've seen. I've been in these markets
since late 2017.
[clears throat]
We have not seen desperation yet. We
have not seen max fear, max FUD yet.
2018 November, oh man, that was a
bloodbat. Absolutely brutal. And it took
months for the market to recover.
Literally months. It did not recover
until April 2019.
Going back to the last bare market 20 21
November and it bottomed out in June
2022 except it kept chop consolidating
until December another 6 months.
I understand that I'm doom and papa. I'm
no longer What does it say? Moon and
papa. I'm not moon and papa. I know I'm
doom and papa. But you guys have to
understand I've been telling you this
for months. This is a bottom year. This
is a bare market year. There are
incredible opportunities. And if I'm
right and totally as is giving us a big
fat warning sign that we might see a
massive drop coming up soon, you should
be excited. If you really care about
crypto, if you really like crypto
projects, if you really like all these
amazing, especially crypto AIcentric
projects, wouldn't you want wouldn't you
want to buy them on the cheap?
It's not such a bad thing. You have to
understand that there is so much
massive, massive potential right now,
this year. You just don't realize it.
You don't recognize it yet.
Be careful.
Watch and pay attention. Be careful.
Step back away from your bias and look
at what a lot of the big talking heads
are saying about the market right now.
Everyone's excited thinking that, "Oh
yeah, we're done. We bottomed out.
Things are good. We're going to go up
higher."
Same thing happened back in the summer
of 2018 around July and August,
September, October. People were getting
really excited thinking that Bitcoin's
going to pump and it dumped.
After the June crash, oh, the bottom's
in. This is great. Nothing could go
wrong. Except it did. And it took 6
months.
Once we finally capitulate, which I
still believe is hopefully around the
corner, hopefully sooner than later, cuz
this is just painful chop. Once we
finally capitulate, that is the moment
where I'm going to start accumulating.
And I am so excited to pivot into that
phase. In the same way, if you guys go
back and watch my videos from 2025, what
did I tell you over and over and over in
2025? I told you take profits on the way
up. I said protect your profits with the
stop loss and if you get stopped out
just walk away with the money. Why?
Because it was a top year. 2025 is when
Bitcoin and the crypto market topped
out. Did it had an amazing parabolic
blowoff top? No. Does it matter? No.
Were you supposed to take profits? Yes.
Did a lot of you? I really hope so
because honestly every single video I
was reminding you take profits. Take
profits. Take profits. any sort any sort
of rally that happens, take profits and
just get stopped out in profit and walk
away. So, in the same way that I was the
squeaky wheel warning you guys again,
canary in the coal mine, I'm telling you
now, don't rush into anything. There's
no need. A bare market takes a long time
to unwind. And once we capitulate, then
it's going to be me repeating over and
over, accumulate, accumulate. This is
the time to accumulate. And accumulating
does not mean going all in with my
entire portfolio on one coin. It means
applying a DCA strategy. This is what we
teach at our courses to better traders
for good reason. Again, I've been doing
this
for just a little bit for just a little
bit uh you know almost 10 years now,
which is nuts. So, you have to
understand I am not new at this. I
understand market cycles. I'm not a noob
when it comes to trading crypto. There
are cycles. I don't care who says that
the four-year cycle is dead.
>> [sighs and gasps]
>> The time to accumulate is not here yet.
It will be. Trust me. I will be
screaming from the rooftops, accumulate.
All right. I might even get a new sign
behind me that says accumulation zone.
[laughter] Have it like off. And when
we're finally there, like, turn it on.
I'm not going to do that.
We're not there yet. We're not.
I want you to take a step back to look
at your feed. Look at all the talking
heads. You pay attention to, which is
fine, which is good. Pay attention to
what they're saying about the current
sentiment. Pay attention to what they
think about the current price of what
should be happening next. Very few
people are actually calling for lower
lows. Everyone started to shift their
thinking over the last couple of months
talking about these bare flags probably
because someone else has been talking
about them for a lot longer.
Jumping on the bus. It's a short bus, by
the way.
We are not yet at max pain, max fear.
We're not. Just trust me. Just take a
step back and look. Okay. I want you to
watch the video about the slush wallet
because this is a fantastic
complimentary accumulation strategy that
you got to employ, especially if you
love the Sooie ecosystem. All right,
check out this video. Until the next
time, you know what to do, stay awesome,
and stay in the green. Peace.