Hello team. So sorry we're six minutes
late. My OBS system just decided to
completely crash. Similar to what I
thinking is happening with Bitcoin soon.
But um besides besides the fact I do
apologize. We're 6 minutes late. I've
got to get into it. We've got to wait
one or two minutes for everyone to sort
of jump in. I do apologize. I don't know
what happened. The whole system just
decided to malfunction. Wasn't
connecting my stream. It was an absolute
disaster. So, I do apologize, but thank
you guys for the comments. Everyone was
getting quite excited. I've got you guys
open on my other screen here. So, thank
you very much for your patience. I got a
lot to share with you today. Um, I'm
also building an indicator for everyone
as well to sort of help them demonstrate
where you can pick up the the fake pumps
that are coming in as well because I've
been seeing a lot of this and a lot of
people would have got caught out
yesterday in that 76k push. Um, that was
actually when I opened up another short
position and then we had that instant
rejection. So, I want to show you guys
how to start to read a lot of that
information, a lot of that data. So, I'm
trying to build you guys an indicator
that picks up a lot of that information
for you and condenses it and makes it
really, really easy to see. So, I
haven't finished it yet. It is still
early days, but it is something I want
to bring to you all. So, stay tuned. As
soon as it is ready, I will publicize it
for everyone. Everyone will have access.
Not going to charge for it, nothing like
that. It's just a free thing that I want
to give away. It's the community for all
the support. So besides that, I want to
go through Bitcoin because it did make
the move that we were looking at off
that trend line that I said, you know,
we're probably going to have a hit
towards 75K. We got 75. Now,
realistically, there is still the order
zone uh sorry, the CME gap that is still
hasn't been filled at 67.5K,
which we went through on Monday as well.
So that is hence why I did open up a big
short bigger shorting position um at
that 76k region and I'm I'm t my target
is for that towards that 67k zone. So I
want to show you guys what that looks
like how it's all come together and of
course we're doing a giveaway today for
everyone that joined us on Monday. We
hit over a 100red viewers. So thank you
very much. That means we do a giveaway.
We're doing 250 USDT giveaways today.
So, I'm going to draw those out live,
excuse me, at the end of the stream. So,
thank you very much for everyone. Let's
get into it. So, before we do,
housekeeping. First things first is
everything I share on here is not
financial advice. Obviously, it's all
for educational purposes, giving you
guys some resources, some tools, some
educational learnings that I've also had
in my past to help you guys look at the
market as well. And the other big one
also is please smash the like button,
comment, share this out there with your
friends because again, every time we hit
over 100, if we hit over 100 again
today, we're going to do another 100
USDT giveaway. So, it's up to you guys.
Share this out far and wide. And let's
get into it. Comment in below because to
be eligible for the giveaways, you need
to comment and I post all the winners on
my socials, which you can see there in
the bottom left. So, let's get into 10.
I'm just going to move this over to my
other side and then um we'll continue to
smash on. Give me one moment. There's
always a lot happening on these streams.
I love it. Gets me excited.
So, first things first, I want to cover
off Bitcoin. So, you can see here guys,
I'm starting to build out this indicator
for you all to to find out when you're
getting these large scale pumps. Shows a
lot of the volume. also shows you when
volume's coming in and validates the
move versus the gray volume which
showcases that it's low volume moves as
well. And then I'm also pulling in spot
versus leverage data as well because one
of the big things we noticed and I want
to show you guys this. I had a friend
send this to me. One of my coaches
inside Empire shared this with me as we
were getting this runup the other day
and he's like Matt just an FYI you know
we're in a couple of trades. We talk we
do some trading together. is like spot
is actually selling into the leverage
position. So you can see leverage
popping up here while spot trading was
actually selling into the leverage
position. So something to be mindful of
there and that's why I wanted to cover a
lot of this off. It's why I thought you
know what maybe I can build you guys
something special where you can actually
pick up a lot of this and this is one of
the examples here where you're getting
these pushes but actually the volume's
quite low. You can see it in the gray
here. You get the X and then all of a
sudden boom price starts crashing. So,
one of the big things I'm big on is is
finding high conviction, high
probability moves. I mean, it doesn't
always come to plan. That's just the
nature of trading, right? But I want to
show you guys what I'm sort of putting
together. This is a little bit of a
quick overview. Like I said, it's still
very fresh, very early days. If you want
something like this and you're happy for
it, you know, I'll do some back testing
on it. We'll share it. We'll give it a
play around. Comment in the chat as
well. You know, again, guys, I feel this
stuff. I build it for you guys. I trade.
I'm I'm fine with my trading. It's more
so to give you guys some more resources
and tools. Now, in saying that, let's
get into the analysis piece.
So, the big one I want to show you guys
here is Bitcoin obviously, right?
Bitcoin at the moment, this is where
it's starting to get interesting. All
right, I want to show you guys. I want
to zoom in on this part. So, as you guys
are fully aware, the one thing that we
were watching for on Monday in
particular was this particular move here
off the base of the trend line up
towards the 75K mark. Now, if you guys
are following me on socials, my X is now
back alive. Uh, my X did die for a
moment, but lucky enough it is uh
reactivated, so you guys can hit me up
on there. But I put up a post on my
Empire account and on on X yesterday
talking about the fact, you'll see it
here, that the 1618 Fibonacci level was
hit and that's where we had the instant
reaction, the instant selloff, which
also presented another fresh order zone.
So, you can see there, that was my
position on uh Bitcoin last night. Now,
what I'm seeing happen is still
relatively um accurate in my opinion
because as this move took effect, and
this is on the daily time frame, you
guys should be able to see this. Now,
this liquidity week, you can see
highlighted here in yellow, actually
started to form. Now, I've had a lot of
people message me about what this
indicator is. Um guys, this is a paid
indicator. It's not cheap. Um it's why
I've showcased a lot of it to you guys.
I'll put it's in my Empire platform. You
guys can go and find it there if you
want to. Uh there's a link in the bio
for everyone. Um compliments of coin
bureau. You guys can get 14 days for
free in there. Plus, it's free to sign
up to get all this sort of stuff. But
this here is a paid indicator. So the
data I'm bringing to you, you guys don't
actually have access to it. It's not
something you can just go and whack on.
So just be an FYI for this. Right now,
we've got the liquidity wick. This
formed pretty much instantly on the
daily time frame the moment price hit
towards this point. Now, I'm going to
break this down for you guys because I
want to show you guys this on the 4 hour
time frame. Now, sorry, on the half an
hour time frame. But first things first,
I want to show you guys how I got to the
point of the 1618 fib level. Now, for
you guys that have been following me for
a while, you would know by now that the
1618 Fibonacci level, and I love trading
fibs, is something I watch religiously.
um it is something where market makers
love to push price towards and the
reason for that is it basically hits a
lot of stop- losses and it's an extended
move that takes effect within the
market. So you can see in this situation
here, right, the target would have been
75K.
And what happens in that sort of respect
is a lot of people put their stop losses
and their take profits, everything right
at that 75K mark, right? If you're
entered in here hoping for a short,
people start putting their stop losses
at at round numbers. Like that's typical
retail sort of situation. So what do the
market makers do? They pump it past just
up to the 1618, take everyone out,
reverse the market. So, I wanted to
bring this to your attention because
what I'm seeing now is very similar,
right? Very similar to what's happened
in the past. We've had the target of the
1618, right? Now, let's put this into
reference. Let's whack this into the
half an hour time frame because this is
the part I really want to show you guys.
Now, what's happened in this scenario is
you can see we've had a massive selloff
at 76K, which is the 1618 fib level.
Then we've had another sell off here at
74,600
as well. And now you can see price
trying to react and trying to bounce off
um this small level of support. If you
look to the left here now reality is
this is what the market is trying to
price in and this is my two cents on it.
You guys can tell me what you think in
the comments. You know, go nuts, right?
Like the stream, give me all the buzz.
give me all the all the as some people
commented on my last video, you know,
they don't like my thumbnails because
they felt a little bit too harsh. Um,
but I find it funny. It's all fun and
games. The one thing I'm looking at at
the moment is what's happened is
basically price has come up. It's taken
out all this liquidity
and it's got all the optimism that's
coming, right? I call optimism because
we have these large scale moves. People
get really excited, right? We've seen
it. BTC inflows on the ETFs have
skyrocketed over the last few days. Go
have a look at it, right? But what
happens from that? Then you get the
hopeium. Then you get the Bitcoin's
going back to 100K scenario. And it's no
difference from when Bitcoin was at 100K
and then all of a sudden Bitcoin's going
to 250K off no credible basis
whatsoever. Just people throwing random
crazy numbers out there because theium
gets real, right? Everyone gets really
excited. Now, people are getting excited
at the moment because we've also got the
war talk set to take place again on
Thursday. So, what that means is
essentially the the market is trying to
price in what they're expecting to be an
end of the war. Now, if that doesn't
take effect and the reality is we still
have that CME gap which is sitting below
here, right? You can see what the order
zone sitting here. That's where that
that other CME gap is. The one that we
were talking about on Monday which still
hasn't been filled. one that Nick was
talking about as well on the Coin Bureau
channel. Reality is if this doesn't pop
back up, get past this 1618 level, which
I personally don't think is going to
happen tonight, then I do expect a
further downturn within the market. And
the reality is with this is this
downturn isn't small. It's quite big in
the grand scheme of things. Let me just
zoom out on this, right? Let me make
this a little bit more smaller so we can
see this more clearer clear. But the
drop from this particular level, it's
about 8%. It's not small, right? So you
can see here we've had a good scale
move. We had the bounce off the order
zone and off the 4hour order zone that
we were tracking on this trend line. You
can see that happen here. So that for me
would be the first point in which
Bitcoin would have to break through. So
again, back down to that $70,000 mark.
But ultimately that CME gap at 67,000
still hasn't been filled. And we've had
a large scale push so far. But when you
zoom out, right, let's just zoom out of
everything at the moment. Let's limit
all the crazy noise, all the jargon, all
the crap that's on the charts, right?
Really just bring this down a little bit
smaller.
We're still in a bare flag. We still
have not taken out this level of
resistance, which is at $75,000,
which is the last time we also had a
major rejection. And also we've now
printed a liquidity wick above and you
can see we are also over purchase on the
CCI. So basically about to put in
bearish divergence as well on the daily
time frame. If I was a betting man and
sometimes I like I do like to have a
punt but on the charts I like to use the
data then my suggestion is and my
thought process is that we come back and
we come and tag that 67,000k mark before
punching up any further.
Now, if I had to go put my Hopium hat
on, whack the Hopium hat on, it would be
my next target would be 80,000. But the
reality for that is, and if I zoom in
here, the reality for that is quite
simple. I don't need a FOMO into
anything because what I'd be looking at
is the break above, the retest, and then
the push. Okay? I don't expect this
price just to skyrocket straight to
$80,000 and I got to run in with all the
hopeium known to known to mankind. I
look at it from a structured
perspective. We got a breakout, retest,
then punch it up towards 80. Where we
are currently, the market isn't telling
me that. What the market is telling me
at the moment is we've attempted to
break out. We've failed and now we've
got the liquidity wick. We've got
bearish divergence forming. We get some
order zones stacking to the top side
here. You can see here starting to form
on the half an hour time frame, right?
And price is essentially struggling to
make its way back towards the $75,000
mark. And in reality as well, if you
look at the S&P, this thing is heavily
heavily overextended. I mean, I put up a
post about this last night. I can't
believe this is 1.3% a little bit less
now towards breaking an all-time high in
the current environment. um quite wild
but again up against one of the biggest
order zones on the weekly time frame as
well. So again I the Bitcoin loves to
move alongside the S&P. It's why we've
seen the same sort of style of move
happen on Bitcoin. Um but I am
predicting in my eyes right now I'm
expecting a bit of a bit of a drop on
Bitcoin before any further price action.
So that is my two cents on Bitcoin. Um I
want to go into the altcoins before
anything else. So guys, if you've got
any questions, whack them in the chat.
Um, I'm going to have a look at the chat
in a couple of minutes. We've got the
giveaway to do as well. You can see
this. This is prepped and ready. Nick
and myself spinning around. So, we've
got all the usernames plugged in here.
So, if you were on Monday, you are in
this one. So, team, if we hit over 100
today, what I'm going to do is I'm going
to actually build this out to go
everyone that comments on the video as
well. So, if you are watching and you
missed it, you can go back and you can
comment. But if you haven't done so
already, share the screen stream, like
it, comment, get it out there for
everyone because every time we hit over
100, we're going to start doing some
giveaways. So, this will be the giveaway
from the weekend. Uh, sorry, on Monday.
Now, let's jump into this. I want to
cover with you guys a couple of my high
conviction trades. On Monday, I spoke to
you guys about Pepe. I spoke to you guys
about Ethereum, um, and a couple others.
Now, the high conviction trades in which
I was watching have played out. So, if
you were on Monday, you were taking your
note. We were watching what was
happening. Every single one of them
played out and Ethereum in particular
absolutely pumped. And it's why I said
to you guys, I'm not focused on
everything and anything. I'm focused on
high conviction movements, right? What
happened with with Ethereum? Bang.
Again, it put in that 9%. You can see
this is on Monday. I'm not bullshitting
to you. You can go and look at the
stream. I said this is one of the plays
I'm looking for. Bang. You had Ethereum
punch up straight towards the target. It
hit the target, rejected, has come back
under again. It's why I love to take
profits, not just hope and hold. So,
it's very obvious, very easy to see this
happened. You got the retest. Boom.
Punch straight up. So, a good move on
Ethereum. Now, am I going to open up a
long here on Ethereum? No, I'm not. I'm
not going to run along into resistance.
If I'm thinking Bitcoin is going to fall
reality, I'm also looking at Ethereum
starting to put in some bearish
divergence as well on a daily time
frame. Wouldn't be surprised if this as
well rolls over alongside Bitcoin. Okay,
so very simple like that. We can break
this down for our time frame. You can
see this here as the moment could be the
early form of the lower high versus the
higher high and the early stage signal
of a change in market structure. So that
is something I'm also watching on
Ethereum. Again, 50 EMA is sitting
below. The orders only sitting below
here, but right now I can't run a long
position on that one. So, that one
there, I'm just going to watch for the
time being. That was a good move on
Monday. That was something I liked on
Monday. Same sort of thing with Pepe. I
want to show you guys here again. Ethan,
Pepe like to move in sync with one
another. What happened? We had on
Monday, boom, big fat green candle on eh
on Pepe as well. You can see it put in
at a 10% candle, came back down. Now
it's holding the support level. This is
a more of an interesting one that I'm
watching. I'm not in this right now. The
reason I'm not in this right now is
because I do think Bitcoin may roll
over. But if it doesn't, then again,
this opens up the gap on Pepe for
another 9 to 10% move as well. But
again, I haven't got confirmation on
this one just yet. So, I'm still waiting
on the sidelines. I'll post my charts. I
keep people give a rolling update on
what positions I am in but I do whack
them all on my socials on X Instagram. I
just put up stories and I put everything
in the Empire platform as well which you
guys can check out. You can see this is
where we sort of post a lot of our
content. So you guys can see all of that
on your own terms. But the next few I
want to have a look at again is hype
because again hype has been positioned
itself really really well and I've been
monitoring this. So, I wanted to have a
look at the target still. This target is
still in place. So, if you are in Hype
token, I mean, I've got an alert set
around $47. I'm going to set another one
there just in case. It's the big fat
order zone that is sitting there and
it's been the overall target for hype as
well. So, that's pushing along quite
nicely, which is good. Not really much
you can do in this current scheme. If
you missed out on hype, you've got to
sort of wait for it because I mean, as
it stands, it's had a really good move.
It's probably got another 8%, but it's
in the middle of the range. So, the
riskto-reward trade on that one is a
little bit off. The other one that I was
watching on Monday, I said to you guys
on Monday, I didn't really have much on
XRP, right? I'm very honest, right? I'm
not going to [ __ ] you guys. So, as
it stands on XRP the other day on
Monday, it was actually sitting at this
low at the base of this order zone. And
I was really cautious on this one. I
said, you know what, we're trending
below. Haven't really got much
conviction in that particular trade. But
as from Monday, we've actually started
to form this order zone. So it's
starting to get a bit of protection to
the downside, which is good. So what I'm
watching for for XRP for for one of our
favorite retail tokens
is realistically we've had the breakback
above. You can see that here. And we've
actually had the retest. So if this can
hold and optimistically Bitcoin doesn't
roll over, then it will open up a gap
for about 8% move. And now this move
here has been taking effect since since
the start of February. We've been
trending within this channel. So again,
nothing new, but I'm looking at the
probability of what could potentially
happen. And in this case, I mean, you've
got an 8% gap here. The one thing I'd be
watching for is simply a break retest of
the 50 EMA, then a push. So you want to
get above that 50 EMA to really get the
conviction going in the trade. But I
don't mind the risk appetite off this
particular movement because if you're
looking at something here, this is the
way I'd be personally positioning myself
is a run to the top of the range and
obviously a stop loss just below the
order zone, which gives me about a two
risk-to-reward ratio. Not great. I
usually want to get about a three. Um,
but again, still not a bad position on
that one. But what I would suggest for a
lot of people if you aren't doing it at
the moment is check the BTC pairings.
XRP BTC. You can see it's been falling
off a cliff. But look at the difference
here. And this is where you get the more
high conviction trades. XRP I mean sorry
Ethereum going in the exact opposite
direction. As I showed you guys on
Monday, this was getting its breakout.
So, what do you think fueled the USDT
price action which went above basically
everything else pushed really well? It's
because the ETH BTC pairing is gaining
value. That means it's gaining value
against Bitcoin. So, it's moving at a
faster pace.
So guys, thank you. I'm going to get
into what I want to get into now is I
want to have a look at the comments. I
want to see if you guys want me to have
a look at anything in particular. And
then what I want to do is I want to go
through the giveaway for you all and um
we'll sort of wrap it up there. But
still got a little bit more to go
through and a few charts that I do want
to cover. So let me just check the
comments here.
Um where are we? Where are we? Kanga,
greetings from Ghana. Welcome, welcome,
welcome team. So guys, if you haven't if
you want me to have a look at anything
particular, run it in, put it in the
chat. I'll have a look at for you at it
for you all shortly. Um, but in the
meantime, I'll have a look at a couple
of other charts since you guys hadn't
put anything in there yet. I'll have a
look at a couple other ones that I was
watching to see what they're doing
because I haven't checked on them in the
last couple of days. So, I'll do it
while I'm on the call with you all. Um,
BNB, if you guys haven't noticed this
one, I spoke about this on Monday.
Again, I don't like to sort of go
through a million one charts, but B&B, I
am watching. I'm hoping if Bitcoin does
roll over here, and look, I don't want
to be that person, but fingers crossed I
do. Um, I want to get the the bag on B&B
at around $555.
It's the monthly order zone. It's the
weekly order zone. It's the 200 EMA.
It's a complete sell-off point. Likely
give us the bullish divergence as well.
For me, that's a good value position.
So, I am watching B&B very closely. You
can see the order zone there on the
daily, but I do want the deep, deep
retracement around that $550 mark. So,
I'll take another snapshot of this for
everyone. I'll whack this one up. um on
the socials and in Empire and so forth
for everyone. But I do really really
like this one. So I'm I'm watching this
one really closely. The other one I want
to have another look at was Ave. I spoke
to you guys about this one on Monday as
well. Ave is doing really really well at
the moment after a massive massive
selloff. Um I'm looking for this early
early part of the breakout if it does
happen. It hasn't happened just yet, but
it's starting to make its way.
And from Monday, this has also had about
a 15% push. So, it's doing quite well. I
was still expecting this to pull back
slightly. It hasn't just yet. So, I'm
just monitoring. I'm not in it right
now. But, Ave in itself is bouncing off
this large scale weekly order zone. And
like I said as well on Monday, it's got
about a 40% push from the bottom to the
top. So, I've got alerts stacked at
around that $90 mark because if it can
get in off that $90 mark, it does open a
big segue. It is a large order zone and
I'm expecting that level of support to
hold and you can see we're getting the
bounce off the ave BTC pairing as well
which again has been holding up since
April 2024.
So not a bad sign there and some bullish
divergence as well there on the weekly
time frame. You can see that there. So
there's some strong analysis going out
there at the moment. Um I'm just very
conscious of the pump that we've had on
Bitcoin. I'm very very cautious of that.
Other people are still trying to scream
out, you know, 80k, 80k, but I'm not
convinced just there yet on Bitcoin. I'm
really not convinced. But I do like the
movement on some of the alts as it
stands. It's going to be interesting to
see how the US market opens today with
the US 500 futures haven't really moved
all that much. And funnily enough, I
want to show you guys this.
The level that they're bouncing up
against at the moment is the 1618
Fibonacci level. So, it's going to be a
bit of a battle. Um, it's going to be
really interesting to see how this
transpires tonight. Uh, we've had a
really, really big 3-week push on the US
500. So, or the S&P. Really interested
to see if we can get above this 618 area
because that'll be huge. That'll put
like a new all-time high on that. Um,
then if that starts to occur, different
story. I'll start to get a little bit
more little bit more hopeium into
Bitcoin, but not right now.
Um, all right. So, you guys, B&B, yep,
gone through that one. ICP, let's have a
look at that. I don't think I've charted
up ICP in a very, very long time.
Wow. Yep. Haven't charted this in a
very, very long time. This thing is very
down.
See, I don't I don't really trade any of
these coins anymore. I stick to the high
probability trades. I stick to the the
larger time frame trades. I stick to,
you know, your big your bigger tokens
cuz I mean, look at this.
I sure as [ __ ] would not have wanted to
buy this.
Does this ever end?
Oh my god. All right, I'm I'm not even
going to bother. Um, let's bring this
back down. Let's have a look at this on
the smaller time frame as it stands.
Um, let me just draw this up. Let me
clean this up again. I haven't charted
this in a very long time. Remove all the
drawings on this one. Let's have a look
at this on the weekly first.
Very simple. We're going to mark at the
mid-range of the order zone. You can see
that there. It gives me a very very easy
easy level to manage. And I can look at
this in its own little formation here
because there's literally no historical
data on that front. So, I've just got to
use what we've got here.
So, as it stands at the moment for this
one, I mean, you're in the middle of the
range. Yes, you've got the breakout. You
probably got a bit of a a bull flag
forming there, which is good early signs
as well. So, maybe I'll have a look at
this on the 4hour time frame as well.
You've got order zones stacked above.
So, it's going to have a bit to a bit of
a resistance to break out of here.
Let's have a look at something for a
moment.
So, we've also got here. It's currently
bouncing off the the 50 Fibonacci level.
So, let me mark out what that support
there looks like. Whether or not I'
prefer that one or whether or not I
prefer prefer the 618.
You can see our price candles get
trapped within that area. So,
I preference my preference with this
would be personally I'd be waiting for a
deeper drop. I'm going to set an alert
here around $234. I don't really like
entering off the 38 or the 50. I like
getting the deeper entries because then
you can have a deeper stop loss. Um,
we'll see how this one plays out. I'll
take a snapshot of this anyway and I'll
sort of run up what I'm thinking.
That's sort of how I would be predicting
that because you've got just got
multiple order zones now that are
resistance levels and they formed above.
So I'll take a snapshot of this
download. All right, what else have we
got? Always around the 15th of the month
strategy is buying big and price reacts.
See, I don't I disagree. I actually
disagree with that last comment. I don't
know if you guys have noticed, but now
when Micro Strategy buys, it doesn't
have the same effect anymore. Go back
and look at it. Like historically when
they used to come out and be like I've
brought millions and millions dollars
worth of Bitcoin. It used to pump but
not so much anymore. I don't really see
that. Now I just see like a general, you
know, oh cool they've purchased. Thank
you very much. But nothing else. Um all
right team. What I want to do is I want
to get into the giveaway and let's punch
this out. This is the exciting part. So
before we do the giveaway, I just want
to say a special thank you to everyone
that has been jumping on these streams
and sharing it. Wednesday is always a
day we have a lot less followers um and
jumping on. So if you can punch it out
on Wednesday for me because if we can
hit over a hundred people on a Wednesday
as well um we again we do some
giveaways. So Monday we had about 115
113 people on which was awesome. I want
to try and crack 200. If we crack 200
I'll do a 200 USDT giveaway. I mean it's
just more fun. Um but I do want to say
thank you for everyone and thank you for
everyone that started following me on
the socials. It's been really much
appreciated. Helps boost the algo. helps
get the message out there that, you
know, crypto education is a massive
piece. Learning how to trade is a
massive piece versus just buying and
hoping and, you know, following people
that are just shilling stuff. So, thank
you very much for that. And for the
winners that I will pull from the wheels
today, you will be posted on my socials.
So, make sure you are following because
you have seven days to claim it. Okay?
So, make sure you are following on the
socials. So, without saying that, my
socials are down the bottom. You should
be able to see them all down there. Hit
me up on X, hit me up on Instagram, and
there is some special promos in the
description for you all as well for some
exchanges that give some bonuses away
and for Empire where you guys can get
some more data, information, offers, and
a whole bunch of cool stuff going on.
So, thank you to everyone. Let's spin
the wheel. Remember, we're doing 250
USDT giveaways. So, if your name is in
here, happy days. Let's spin it.
All right, here we go. So, here we go.
Here we go. Who do we have today?
We have
Daniel Ludon. All right. Congrats,
Daniel. Let me save your name so we
don't lose it. Happy days. Um, so what
we'll do now is we will remove remove
Daniel from there because we don't want
to double up on the winners. But good
luck. We have one more chance. Good luck
everyone.
Here we go.
Marcus G6S,
if you guys are on here, hit me up. Make
sure you send me a message because that
is the only way you guys are going to be
able to claim your giveaway, of course.
And for everyone else, thank you very
much for joining. I will see you guys on
um Monday. I'm also going to do some
more live streaming as much as possible
for you all. I want to get people
trading. I want to get the excitement
flowing. So, um I might hit up the boys
coin bureau, see if we can do some live
trading sessions as well versus just a
market analysis and do some stuff on the
smaller time frames. Usually in these
sessions, I'll try and condense as much
into this as possible so you guys can go
away for the week. You know, you've got
a whole bunch of stuff in your arsenal
ready to go. We've predicted all the
moves on Bitcoin at the moment. And now,
like I said, just to sort of wrap things
up, I am predicting a move to go more
towards the downside versus the upside.
I want to see that CME gap close at 67K.
The S&P 500 is right up against the top
of the order zone as well. Alpha 1618
Fibonacci level. I'm expecting a
rejection to take there or basically a
fake out to a dump. And the big news
around the Iran war is going to have a
really big effect because the market is
trying to position itself for that to
end. So if it doesn't end and there is
no essentially a nuclear deal, which is
the biggest impact that that is going to
have, then I expect a massive selloff
personally. Right? So guys, I'll leave
you with that. Thank you very much. I'll
see you guys on Monday for a massive
session. Let's pump 100 people in on
Monday into the live call. And you know
what? If we get a 100 on Monday, I'll do
the live pull. I'll spin the wheel live
on Monday for everyone that's there. So,
thank you very much everyone.