What's up, guys? It's Jordan here from
CoinBureau. If you're new to the
channel, subscribe and be sure to stay
tuned until the end of the video to get
all of the important information.
Continuing on in my more beginner
trading tutorials on this playlist,
we're going to be looking today at trend
lines. Many traders do use these wrong
and it costs them money. In the next few
minutes, you're going to learn how to
draw trend lines like a pro and use them
to actually trade. Please also feel free
to join my personal trading community
and trade along with us in my Discord
server. That link is in the description
and as you can see by the P&L share
room, our crew is absolutely killing it.
There is also a trading setups room here
where the traders who are trading a lot
are constantly dropping really, really
interesting setups and helping all the
traders along the way. Trend lines
really are one of the most basic
technical analysis principles, but
really something that does get used
badly with bad habits that are created
early. If you can use trend lines
properly, they actually allow for some
pretty incredible sniper entries. So,
let's talk about now what is a trend
line? Very simply, a trend line connects
higher lows in an uptrend and lower
highs in a downtrend. They help identify
direction, support and resistance, and
momentum. Here we can see a strong
downward sloping trend line giving us
very nice short entries until that trend
does get broken and then we get the
beautiful long trade. Important to
understand, especially at first, is that
upward sloping trend lines are drawn
below the trend connecting your higher
lows. And the opposite in a downward
sloping trend line, you're drawing your
line at your lower highs. You can choose
whether you like to draw these in at the
wicks for extreme trend lines or at the
candle bodies, but make sure you are
finding your trend lines on the most
visible touch points. Let's now talk
about how to draw these trend lines
correctly. And this is where the most
value is. Here are some rules. Number
one, minimum two touch points, but
really you want three plus touch points
to have a stronger trend line. Don't
force the line. Make sure you are
actually seeing multiple touch points on
the charts. Choose whether you are using
bodies or wicks and stay consistent with
that choice. And always feel free to
adjust the trend line slightly to get
your best angle and most touch points.
Some common mistakes here are forcing
the lines to fit your own bias, ignoring
the market structure, drawing through
random points, and this does take time,
but really just play around on the
charts and very soon your mind will
start identifying where to put in these
trend lines very easily. Remember, our
brains are pattern recognition machines
and they automatically find these kinds
of consistencies for us. We just need to
learn to look in the right way. Let's
now talk about the major ways in which
trend lines work in terms of crypto
trading. And these form the three major
strategies that trend line traders use.
Number one, they create support and
resistance on your charts and very often
price does bounce on these lines as
support or resistance. They also offer
us breakout opportunities where price
does fall below those levels. And then
most importantly for conservative sniper
traders, they allow retest entries on
support and resistance flips. Let's walk
through now a few very quick and simple
practical examples. Number one is the
bounce trade. Here we identified the
trend line with at least three touch
points. And here was a very volatile
candle and try not to trade during times
of extreme volatility. But here we can
see a very nice opportunity for a bounce
trade. Remember to always draw in your
trade and set your limits with a risk to
reward ratio of at least one to three.
Also, always be sure to try and find
confluence with your other indicators.
My chosen indicator for this is the
market cipher. And here we can see a
very nice green dot trigger wave coming
in for us at the support of the trend
line bounce. This is also a decent
example of that support line being
flipped into resistance and giving us a
nice retest trade. Always draw in the
trade with your limits clearly defined
as well as your targets and your risk to
reward ratio and make sure you are using
a nice entry signal within your given
trading plan. The major thing to be
aware of here are fake outs. Make sure
that you are getting the correct entry
signal on the retest of the support and
resistance flip in the correct
direction, otherwise you could get
wrecked on a fake out trying to catch a
breakout without a proper signal coming
in. If you need to learn to use market
cipher, I will drop that link in the
description. Some pro tips from me here
are to make sure you are combining these
trend lines with support and resistance
zones, moving averages, candle stick
patterns, using higher time frames for
stronger trend lines, and keeping in
mind that the more touches means the
more reliable trend line. Common
mistakes here are over drawing trend
lines where you don't see enough touch
points, trading every touch blindly
without confirmations from other
indicators, ignoring the overall trend,
and not waiting for enough confluence on
your confirmations. If you found this
useful, like and subscribe and please
let me know any questions you have in
the comments.