It's pretty wild to see the Bitcoin or
crypto fear and greed index at 21
considering that the last time I got out
this high was basically back over here
on March 5th where we saw a pull back
and also over here on the 17th where we
also saw a pullback at a pivot high.
Now, when we actually look at the chart
for BTC, I mean, we just saw a 5% move,
5% plus move on Monday because of news,
just like we saw a big five, sorry, 6.3%
move on Wednesday, March 4th, before it
made a pivot high to a low, and then we
see a big push up to a pivot high on the
17th of March. Both of those levels
corresponding to overbought conditions
and fear and greed going, "Hey, hey, is
anybody is anybody paying attention
here?" Now, I want to show you more in
regards to price action, how it
responded in the past, as well as other
indicators that are very clear that this
is a strong case for a pivot high here
on Coinb Trading. What's up? My name is
Aaron Disher from the Better Traders.
You're watching Coinbau Trading. Hit the
subscribe button, like this video, and
let's get into it right away.
The first indicator that we can use for
this is actually RSI. RSI has been
fantastic because it tells us when the
price is overbought or oversold. Easy
peasy, right? So, I use RSI with a
length of seven. So, that way RSI is
much more responsive. At RSI with a
length of 14, it's not as crazy or as
whippy, I guess you could say. Um, so
that's why I think it's better uh to use
something faster. So on the 4th we saw
RSI get really close to being
overbought. It was at what 69.75
and then it rolled over. It actually
pivoted and fell about 11%. Over here we
saw RSI on Monday the 16th of March at
76.83
and then we saw RSI drop down another
what 10%. Well shortterm and it also
fell down a lot lower like 15%.
One of the bigger reasons why I think
that this is a pivot high moment for
BTC. Aside from the news uh about Iran
and all that stuff
is also RSI. Um if we just focus on
price action in RSI, we we recently seen
a big move on RSI on the 16th of March
about a month ago. Now when this
happened, we had a huge push up to what
74,000 basically 75K. Actually, on the
17th, we moved up to 76K.
Monday, we moved up to 74,900.
So, just slightly lower than that.
Bitcoin could still push up a little bit
higher, but the the bigger problem right
now is the fact that we have lower highs
on RSI.
Um, and the fact that we had a really
nice big green candle of 5.2%, but RSI
didn't even manage to go overbought
above 70. That should be concerning and
again it could push up higher but that
should be something you should be
worried about if you're both. The other
thing to consider as well is onbalance
volume. Now all these are free
indicators. Um I also will be sharing a
paid one in a second but I want to start
with the free stuff first. Now if we
look at onbalance volume here, the
reality is that onbalance volume has
been very very reliable to show us these
pivot high moments where we get
overbought conditions. Whether it's when
the blue line, which is onbalance
volume, goes above the white line or
really high above the white line like it
did on the 16th and then it had a
pullback. This time it hasn't pushed up
as much, but it's still above the white
line which has flattened out quite a
bit. This is still a pretty convincing
pivot high moment. The last time this
happened, by the way, was way back over
here in like December. We saw two spikes
above the moving average. And for
onbalance volume, I use a 21 SMA for
those that are curious. And here again
on the 5th of January, big spike in
onbalance volume and price and a
pullback. big spike in onbalance volume
here on the 14th of January at 98K
and that's where we fell from.
Now, let's fast forward. We have a
fairly decent spike. Not as big
admittedly as what we saw on the 16th,
but that's still
indicative of a overbought moment. Now,
volume as well has spiked, but not as
much as it did back over here. Now,
we're not going to see that much
happening. We didn't see that big of a
volume spike over here on the 16th of
March. We did see a decent one here on
the 4th of March.
Uh but the 16th of March didn't really
have amazing volume. Kind of like what
we saw on Monday. Now, in terms of paid
indicators, the TBO, which is the
trending breakout indicator, there's a
couple of things to pay attention to.
For starters, it printed an open long.
That green triangle right there tells us
it's basically bullish confirmation of
an uptrend. Now, how could I say that
we're going to have a pivot high moment
where we're getting an open long on the
daily time frame? Well, I can say that
because if we go back in time, we
literally saw this same thing happened
back over in January. Literally, when
Bitcoin pushed all the way up to 98,000K
or wait 98,000
up to 98K, that was the moment where I
had a pivot high. The thing about TBO
open long and open short is that these
are going to be late. But more
importantly, the slow line, which is the
slowest of the four moving averages that
comprise of the TBO, if it's pointing
down and we get an open long, that open
long is going against the trend and
there's a real big disconnect there,
meaning that the macro trend should be
trusted over the open long. that we will
see a really great reversal, a good
bullish move soon, but I don't think
that it's here yet.
Now, it's not just on Bitcoin either.
Other charts are showing signs of
weakness, and it's really, really,
really interesting. I want to share
Ethereum next with you, but before I do,
I need you to go to the description down
below. Check out the links that we have
for different exchanges like Tubbit,
where you can sign up and trade to earn
over 15,000 USDT and rewards using the
link that's provided. There also way
more deals for exchanges, for wallets,
for crypto trading bots and tools here
on the Coin Bureau website. Also,
there's a 10% off discount to our course
15 minutes of financial freedom from the
better traders.
Now, going back over here to the crypto
fear and greed index, showing it over
time, we can also see a couple of
moments here where this has been really
helpful to give us a good sense of how
overbought we might be. Now, this isn't
the only thing that should really be
driving the the pivot high
belief right now. Again, it's RSI. It's
on balance volume volume kind of sort of
as a TBO. Yes. Um it's also this as
well. And the weird thing is that we can
also use this crypto fear and greed
index in parallel with what's happening
with Ethereum which is even clearer to
me.
Ethereum had some pretty strong
overbought moves. Namely, here on the
16th of March, we saw a crazy reversal
from the 9th to 16th of 23%. And finally
on the 16th, it closed up 8% on the day.
Now, when this happened, check out all
the other indicators. RSI went super
overbought at 84.03.
That's a big warning sign. Look at on
balance volume. Massive spike. Um, in
terms of volume, there was a huge spike
of volume as well. Most likely this
spike was fueled by of course bullish
sentiment, yes, but also short squeezes.
But that marked a pivot high moment. And
guess what? If we look at the same
metrics over here with the current
price, what do we have? We have RSI that
is just slightly overbought on Monday,
but only at 70.83,
lower than the high we saw on Saturday,
the 11th, lower, much lower than March
16th's high as well.
We also have very bullishly ascending
onbounce volume. This is the one case
for higher highs for Ethereum to be
honest. We saw a good spike in volume.
But the TBO is clear here. The price is
struggling at pricebased resistance.
Yes. But also this red dotted line which
is TBO resistance is also really clear
about Ethereum hitting a top target.
If this is a pivot high moment, what we
should be expecting to see next is not
only a rejection
per se, but an opportunity to buy lower.
So, I want to provide both outcomes for
this video. I know a lot of you are
really, really impatiently waiting for
the bottom for BTC. And I keep getting
people asking about, well, what about
your bare flag? Well, like I said over
here, when the price pushed up on
Tuesday, the 7th of April, it
invalidated the bare flag. Bare flag
went bye-bye. That's done. But it
doesn't mean that our support level or
support fan here hasn't been
invalidated. This is still super valid.
In fact, it was threatened on Monday's
open. So, now we're looking at something
like this, something give or take. The
reality right now of a very fast
short-term overbought move is some sort
of a corrective move back down, which
gives us a couple of targets and things
to watch. Now, first off, the the number
one level that we need to look for in
terms of a pullback is always the TBO
fast line, which today is at $7,818.
That's the first target right there,
which from the current price would be a
drop of about 4.7%.
What will happen first off once the
price of BTC goes down that low is it's
going to break this first support fan
level. Not the end of the world. It's a
very weak level that most traders aren't
really paying attention to admittedly.
But once that level breaks, then there's
a greater chance or likelihood that we
start to break more and more and more.
The other thing to consider as well is
our date.
Right now, as of the filming of this
video, it's April 14th. We're about
halfway through May. And if you've ever
heard the adage, uh, sell and may walk
away, we're getting really close to a
moment where,
well, think of it this way. If you were
a market maker and you wanted to really
manipulate the market, what would you
want to do? Would you want to just dump
the price or would you want to pump it
and have everyone feel really, really
good pushing the price up too high, too
hard, too fast, only to reverse, only to
pivot? So that way everything starts to
fall lower. Bitcoin could still move up
higher. But there's one more thing to
consider and that would be our previous
artificial supports back over here on
April 7th. We had a really nice pivot
low moment right there when we finally
had the end of all the tariff FUD fears
when BTC dropped from over $100,000 down
to 74K down 32%.
This level of support was taken out real
fast in the beginning of February and
now it's created a couple of things. For
one, we have a resistance that's
respected here on the 4th. It pierced it
on the 16th and 17th, but inevitably it
lost it. And what's really interesting
is that the price of BTC closed just
below that level, $74,58.
So, if Bitcoin
actually closes and holds above $74,58,
I'll tell you this, the next stop is
going to be up there, the slow line, or
basically $80,600.
I don't expect that to happen. Uh what
I'm expecting to have happen next is the
market gets excited, euphoric, over
levers into higher highs as things are
going crazy and we get rugged and we see
everything fall a lot lower as in down
to those targets that I've talked about
over and over. 60K is an easy first
target, then 49, then 3855.
I know a lot of people still don't agree
with me on my bare market thesis, and
that's totally fine. And what I can also
tell you with 100% confidence is that
over here on this Wednesday, January
14th move where we saw TBO open long and
it reversed against us. It's not the
first time that this has happened
either. If we go back a year, we saw
this same thing happened in a fake rally
in late March that led up to the top of
the cloud here about 10 11% up higher
and then Bitcoin kind of rolled over
here in April. And as soon as we hit
May, guess what happened? Bitcoin mega
dumped 30% first and then it mega dumped
again in June where we finally bottomed
out after bottoming out and we bounced.
Guess what? TBO opened long here on a
move in August and it still rolled over.
TBO opened long over here the 29th of
October and the price rolled over.
Inevitably, this is going to be correct
like it was back over here in January.
But the reason why this one worked is
because the time of the bare market had
been fulfilled. From it topping out here
in November to bottoming out in
November, it had already done its
year-long bare market. It was done.
So, the reason why this open long that's
recently opened yesterday isn't really
giving me confirmation feelgoods right
now um is just because we're going to
see more of these print and seeing it
print on a big pump like this. it makes
more sense to see BTC
maybe move up a little bit higher, but
honestly, we're at a pivot high moment
where I think we're going to be going
back down and lower because we haven't
really fulfilled the bare market
duration from our our top here on
October 6th at 126
199. We are only 190 days in, which is
great. We're more than halfway done with
this bare market in terms of it being a
true 52- week bare market. But
I I still think that we're not there
yet. If we look at 2021's sorry 2022's
bare market, it's about 50 52 weeks 54
weeks. If you look at 2018's bare
market, it's about 52 54 weeks. If you
look at 2014's bare market, even longer.
So for us to only have what 27 weeks
under our belt to say the bare market's
done just feels a little bit too early.
Now, does Bitcoin have to stick to the
four-year cycle? No. But has it been
reliable up until now? Yeah, it has. So,
how am I trading this right now? Well,
basically, I'm looking for short
positions across the board. That makes
the most sense on a big overbought
short-term move. Even though things are
feeling good right now, I'm still
skeptical. I'm going to be watching to
see if Bitcoin can actually close above
that level, that April 7th, 2025 pivot
low level, like 74,500 or so. But the
main thing to watch right now is if it
can hold above that level, then it has
to push up a lot higher to 80,600,
something like that. But the to the top
of the TBO cloud and the last time that
happened, it rolled over. I'm not
discounting the fact that we could see a
rally this month in April. In fact, I've
been expecting it, especially since last
week looking at the data. But the data
also very clearly tells us that May and
June should be red for Bitcoin and for
crypto. That's why I still believe that
we're not done yet. After we bottom out,
May and June, maybe then we're going to
get a nice reversal rally again in July
after a drop. if it plays out the way it
has in the last two bare markets, which
is pretty good evidence to be honest.
But I know I know some of you don't want
to believe and it's okay.
The fun thing is that you don't have to
believe. You just have to watch, wait,
and see what's going to happen. And I'm
personally pivoting myself to be ready
for another pullback here. Let me know
what you think about this down in the
comments. And I need you to watch this
video next to give you an idea of how I
think Bitcoin dominance is going to be
reacting from here on out. Until the
next time you have to do, stay awesome
and stay in the green. Peace.