What's up, guys? It's Jordan here from
CoinBureau. If you're new to the
channel, subscribe and be sure to stay
tuned until the end of the video to get
all of the important information.
I have been getting a lot of requests
for more beginner style trading
tutorials here. So, if you are wanting
to learn how to break down the charts
using technical analysis, this video is
one of the best places to start. And
today, I'm going to show you how to very
easily identify support and resistance
on your charts. This is absolutely
essential to crypto trading, and really
a lot of traders lose money because they
don't understand this concept properly.
It really is quite simple as long as you
know the basics and you don't create bad
habits. In this video, you're going to
learn how to identify and draw in
support and resistance like a pro and
use it to find better entries and exit
points for your trades. If you are
trading along with us, use the Bybit
link in the description for some
benefits. That is my preferred exchange.
Please also feel to join my personal
trading community and trade along with
us in my Discord server. That link is in
the description. And as you can see by
the P&L share room, our crew is
absolutely killing it. There is also a
trading setups room here where the
traders who are trading a lot are
constantly dropping really, really
interesting setups and helping all the
traders along the way. So, let's take it
slow and discuss a little bit about what
is support and resistance. Support is
simply a level where buyers step in.
And resistance is a level where sellers
step in. Think of support as a floor and
resistance as a ceiling in a room. In
this video, we're going to keep it
simple and we're going to talk about
horizontal support and resistance lines
as this is really the best place to
start. Once you learn this concept,
you'll be finding levels all over your
charts where price bounces on support
and gets rejected from resistance.
Something to keep in mind here is that
the more touch points that your support
gets, the higher significance it has.
And also bear in mind that when a strong
resistance level is broken, it will flip
into acting as support and vice versa
for support flipping into resistance.
This is what we call a support and
resistance flip. Let's move into now a
step-by-step on how to draw these lines
in properly on your charts. Number one
is to remember to always zoom out and
use higher time frames. If you are
starting out on this, I would recommend
zooming out to the weekly time frame.
This is a great place to start and it
does take practice, but very quickly
you'll be seeing these lines all over
the charts because our brains are
pattern recognition machines. When
starting out in drawing support and
resistance, try to mark out areas on the
charts that have similar levels of
support. These are levels that look like
obvious highs and lows. And try to focus
on areas with multiple reactions. You
can then go draw in your horizontal
support and resistance line. And even
better is to start early with trying to
understand these support and resistance
levels as zones. This is where it does
start to get slightly more complicated,
but it is very useful and effective in
terms of finding nice entries and exits
to be able to understand these levels as
zones. And moving forward in time on
this chart, we can see just how
important that zone was as it allowed
for some beautiful sniper entry longs on
recent price action. Don't force the
lines, but try to find the lines that
are giving you the most touch points.
The most useful indicator here to help
you find these major support and
resistance zones is the fixed range
volume profile. There are full tutorials
on this on my personal trading channel,
so check them out. It's absolutely
amazing how the high volume nodes of
this volume profile can give you
beautiful levels and zones of extreme
significance. Many of the traders in my
community know that the fixed range
volume profile is one of my absolute
favorite drawing tools. And it really
does help to find these levels in a
smart way using volume based on previous
price action. Some common mistakes that
beginners make here are drawing too many
lines, ignoring the higher time frames,
treating levels as exact prices instead
and trading every touch without waiting
for confirmation from other indicators
for confluence. So, let's have a look
now at a few simple strategies using
support and resistance. Number one is
the bounce trade. So, identifying a nice
support and resistance line and then
waiting for price action to move towards
these lines for a nice bounce. Remember
to always draw in your trades and
identify your risk to reward ratio as
well as using your other indicators for
confluence such as this daily bullish
divergence on the RSI, which came in at
the exact bounce point on this example.
The next strategy example here is a
breakout trade. This is a little more
risky and does require being patient for
a retest. But as we can see here, this
zone was acting as very heavy resistance
and once price broke out from that heavy
resistance, it offered a very nice
trading opportunity. Here's another
example of a breakout trade that did
actually give you the retest, which I
would recommend using as a more
conservative trader. Here we can see
price bouncing on major support, then
breaking through, and then coming back
to retest that broken support as
resistance, and that is where the nice
trade came in. Remember to use your
other indicators for entry signals at
these retests like your RSI, your SMC
order blocks, or of course your Market
Cipher. Remember to always try and add
as much confluence as you can to each
entry with at least three to five
indicators giving you the same
directional signal. You can combine
these support and resistance levels with
trend lines, moving averages,
candlestick patterns, volume, or any
other indicators that you enjoy using in
your trading plan. Let's have a look at
a practical example of a bounce trade
and how you would go about executing
this. I'll be using my favorite
indicator for an entry signal, which is
the Market Cipher. Here we can see our
support trend line, price moving towards
that trend line. We draw in our long
trade identifying our risk to reward
with at least a one to three. And in
this example, we can see a beautiful
rifle pattern, which is one of the best
patterns that you can get on Market
Cipher. And there we see a beautiful
trade with very little drawdown,
smashing one take profit after another,
and actually going on to give us a
pretty crazy return of a risk to reward
ratio of about one to nine and a half.
Very important is to take gradual
profits along the way, especially when
you do get opposing signs on your
indicators. To recap in a quick summary,
support equals a buying zone, resistance
equals a selling zone. Use zones instead
of just lines and wait for
confirmations. If you found this
helpful, like and subscribe, and let me
know, do you prefer breakout or bounce
trades using these lines?