What's up, guys? It's Jordan here from
CoinBureau, and in today's video, I'm
going to be showing you how to use the
trailing stop to make sure that you are
locking in the maximum possible gains
that you can on your trades. This really
is one of my all-time favorite features
to use in trading when it comes to stop
loss, and one of my favorite things
about the Bybit platform, although it
can be found on some other exchanges. It
can help you to manage your risk and
lock in higher gains through using a
little bit of automation. And very
often, people think that using this is
actually more complex than it is, and
today I'm going to break it down so you
can all start using it. Knowing how to
use the trailing stop is a great asset
to any crypto trader and was a
game-changer for me when I found out how
to use it. We're going to be having a
look at what is a trailing stop, how it
can be used for higher gains and higher
win rate, and of course, how it works
and how to activate it using all of the
different parameters. If you are trading
along with us, use the Bybit link in the
description to set up an account, and I
will be demonstrating the trailing stop
today on Bybit. Please feel free to also
join my Discord trading community. The
link is in the description, and as you
can see from the P&L share group, the
crew is absolutely killing it. Okay, so
first things first, what is a trailing
stop? As the name suggests, it is a stop
loss that will trail automatically
behind the price at your given distance.
So, you select the distance behind the
price that you want the trailing stop to
follow, but and it will automatically
trail behind that price every time the
price moves further in the direction of
your trade. So, let's look at this
simple example now of Bitcoin as it is
at the current value area high of its
range. This is using the fixed range
volume profile. This means that
technically now we are looking for
signals on our other indicators for
confluence for a short trade on Bitcoin
somewhere in this zone. For the sake of
this teaching, let's say that we are
getting a confluence signal from our
other indicators telling us to go short
at the current moment. This could be RSI
and stochastic RSI in overbought at the
same time on this time frame. This could
be an SMC order block or a market cipher
red dot trigger wave or bearish
divergence or any other indicator that
you use for confluence on your trades.
If the short position is looking like
this with our stop loss above the
previous swing high wick, of course,
when we enter the trade, whether it's on
limit or market, we want to enter with a
stop loss so that there is no moment
that we are unprotected. I always
recommend here on Bybit to make sure
that when you are entering your trade,
you enter with a stop loss level. The
take profits are less important. You can
always go put them in at a later time,
but I would recommend opening your trade
with an initial stop loss in case you
lose internet connectivity, and you
should never be getting liquidated. So,
once you are in your trade, you can go
ahead and set your take profit limit
orders. You can do this in a number of
different ways depending on what you
prefer. One of the best ways, in my
opinion, is to use the fib retracement
tool. There is a tutorial on this on my
personal trading channel, so check it
out, and this allows us to find very
nice high probability take profit levels
to set our limit orders for our gradual
take profits. Now is when it gets
interesting when we start to understand
how to use the trailing stop, and there
are three major different ways of doing
this. The first way is to set your
trailing stop at the open of your trade
at the level of your stop loss. So, if
you do this, you open the trade here
with your stop loss here, and you also
set your trailing stop at that same
distance. Then, as you go into profit,
your trailing stop will trail behind
that price at the same distance, and
remember, it only moves in the positive
direction of the trade. So, if price
moves down this much, your stop loss
will also move down that much, and then
if price reverses and goes up, it will
hit your trailing stop. And this is the
main idea behind the trailing stop. It
is especially useful for scalpers and
trend following, but it really can be
used on all styles of trading. The
second major way to use the trailing
stop is to drop it in manually when you
want to remove all risk and when you
have taken a decent amount of profit off
the trade. So, say this trade has gone
to hit your TP1, TP2, and TP3, you can
now go drop in quite a tight trailing
stop so that your stop loss will trail
any further price movement as long as it
is in the direction of your trade, and
as soon as there is a pullback, you will
lock in that amount by closing the trade
at your trailing stop. This allows for
very high profit-taking efficiency, and
as I say, is just amazing for trend
following. As if there is a very big
impulse move, your trailing stop will
follow it, and once that move stops, you
will lock in those gains. The third most
popular way to use this, and actually my
favorite way of using it, is to use the
activation price function in the
trailing stop. This will allow you to
choose a price at which you want to
activate the trailing stop, and at that
activation price, how large you would
like your distance to be between price
and between the trailing stop. This for
me is an absolute ultimate tool when it
comes to risk management, as in essence,
you can automate moving your stop loss
to a break even after your first take
profit, and then letting that stop loss
trail price from then on. This ensures a
risk-free trade at your first take
profit without you having to be on the
charts at that moment to move your stop
loss to break even, and as the trade
goes in your favor, it also allows you
to lock in a stop that trails the price.
What I will usually do here is I will
take a one-to-one risk-to-reward ratio
from my stop loss,
find that price, and at that price, I
will set the activation price for my
trailing stop to be placed above break
even with a little bit of buffer for
fees. Then, in the trade, when price
hits that level, the trailing stop will
activate and appear, and of course, if
price retraces, it will close the trade
in a profit, and if price continues
further, the trailing stop will follow
along with it. So, this is helping you
to manage your risk better in two major
ways. It's allowing you to lock in
higher gains as the trade moves in your
favor for if or when the trend turns
around. It's also allowing you to
automate placing your stop loss into
profit, which can have a significant
effect on your win rate. All right, so
let's have a look now at how to actually
use the trailing stop on Bybit and which
parameters you need to understand in
order to execute it. For the sake of the
demonstration, I'm just going to open a
paper trade here on Fatcoin. Remember to
always open your trade with a stop loss
in place. Here you can see my trade
entry and my stop loss, and you can
always drag your stop loss around as you
need to. All right, so now we are in the
trade. Come to your trailing stop right
here in the open positions section and
click add. The main thing to understand
here first is that you can set it by
distance or by rate. By distance is the
amount of actual price between price and
where you want your trailing stop to
follow. It seems complicated, but it's
really not. You just subtract the price
at the distance of your trailing stop or
where you would like it to be from the
current price, and you're left with the
price difference. Try to look at the
candles on the lower time frames and see
how big the volatility is within the
trend to find your ultimate distance for
your trailing stop so that you are
trailing behind the trend as it moves
up, but if there is a major retracement,
the trailing stop will lock in the gains
for you. The other way, and the way
which I think is the easiest, is to just
measure the distance that you would like
in percentage between price and your
trailing stop. So, if we come back to
our trade here, we simply measure how
far we would like our trailing stop to
be placed, you can always drag this
around afterwards. So, let's start with
a 2%. We then go and add the trailing
stop in at a rate of 2% and click
confirm. As you can see, this has placed
a trailing stop for us here, and this is
really where it does get fun. This
trailing stop will trail automatically
behind your price. As you can see here,
this is the trailing stop, and it is
following now automatically
as the price drops according to the
distance at which I've dropped it into
the chart. It will keep following at
this distance to any new maximum that
the price reaches on that trend. Then,
when the trend retraces by the distance
that I've chosen, the trailing stop will
get hit and lock in the gains. Then, as
I was explaining, another really big
brain way to use this is by using the
activation price. This is the price at
which your trailing stop will activate.
You don't have to use this feature, but
it can be very useful for automating
when you bring your stop loss to break
even if you do want this to be a
trailing stop. You might even choose to
do this after your second or third take
profits, which really helps you lock in
the maximum amount of gains you are
pulling out of a trade in any
eventuality. I usually do this at my
first take profit. Especially for
scalpers, you might want to do this at
your first take profit you are taking
all risk off the table and then
following with your take profit behind
the trend that you are scalping. This is
very simple to use. You choose the
activation price at which you would like
the trailing stop to be implemented as
well as the distance behind that price.
I really hope this has been useful in
shedding some light on the trailing
stop. It's really not as complicated as
you might think. It's so easy to use,
and it is so useful. Please let me know
any questions that you have in the
comments. As always, try to backtest
this using paper trades or demo first in
case you make any mistakes, and always
play from a position of power and
strength.