All right, we are live, fam. So, thank
you very much for jumping on. This is a
big session because as I've labeled it,
Bitcoin could die tomorrow. But, let's
be realistic about this, right? Is
Bitcoin going to die tomorrow?
Potentially not, but there is some
massive news that's going on in the
market at the moment, and we have to do
a big big deep dive into this. So,
giving everyone a minute or so to jump
in. As you guys know, it does take a
little while for the stream to get
pushed out to everyone. So,
I just want to make sure everyone gets a
chance to jump in before we jump deep
into what is currently happening in this
environment. So,
>> [clears throat]
>> we have a lot to cover. It is wild. The
last 36-48 hours going absolutely nuts.
And I don't just mean this from a
charting perspective. I mean this from a
global economy perspective. And this is
why I've labeled this video in the
thumbnail, Bitcoin dies tomorrow because
Mr. Donald Trump is doing some crazy
stuff that is potentially going to throw
the market into complete disarray. And I
think we need a deep dive into this. It
is very very important that we get into
all of this tonight and smash it all
out. Um Bitcoin is currently on a move.
It's up around 69,500.
It did peg $70,000 for a split moment.
Um but, it has not held up there
whatsoever. And the Friday market close
did occur at around $66,000
as well
last Thursday uh for the US market. So,
all of what's happening at the moment, I
do take with a grain of salt. As we both
as we both know, fake move Mondays is a
massive thing. We saw this happen last
week. It happened again this week. And
I've got to break this all down for
everyone. So,
if you just jump in, make sure you like,
make sure you subscribed, make sure you
follow me on X and Instagram. That's
where I drop a lot of my chart updates
after this
after this call. And if you are enjoying
this, make sure you share this stream
out with everyone cuz as we know, we
want to get over 100 viewers on this
stream co-currently. So, we want to have
them constantly on uh so we can start
pumping out some giveaways to you guys.
So, we already did a 200 USDT giveaway
um a couple weeks back. I want to do
another one very soon. So, let's get
those numbers pumping so we can make
those giveaways a regular occurrence.
So,
team, thank you for jumping on. I can
see all the comments are coming through.
Welcome, Kanga Matt. Hey, it is great to
have you all on. Um as you guys know, if
you see me turning into my side, it's
because I have all the comments there. I
love to see what you guys uh going
through. Bro, I'm counting on you for
the truth.
Guys, if there's one thing
that I can put my hand on my heart with
is I'm not your typical crypto
influencer that's going to shill you a
whole bunch of crap. Um I'm not going to
put out there, you know, "Oh my god,
Bitcoin's going to 250k when we haven't
even got past 70 yet, or we're going
down to 20 when we haven't even dropped
past 60." We keep things methodical. We
look at these with with data, right? We
go through we break it down section
section by section and if I think there
is nothing there, I'm going to tell you
there is nothing there. If I think
there's a lot of market uncertainty, I'm
going to tell you there's a lot of
market uncertainty. But, when you get
these messages of 80k next and you
haven't even broken like a major
resistance of 75, you've got to take a
lot of this with a grain of salt because
a lot of movements happen in amongs
amongst all of that. So, that's what's
kept me in the game for long enough. I'm
also want to announce I'm going to do a
special call.
Now, I'm going to see if I can do a
collaboration call on this one. But,
I've worked out how to get access in
this completely separate topic, how to
access the SpaceX IPO, which is
absolutely huge. So, I'm already exposed
to that and I want to show you guys how
to do that one as well.
Um I'll work out how I'm going to do
that, but it will be this week. So, make
sure again you are following my socials.
That's where I'm going to put out the
information on how you can actually do
this. And I'll walk you guys through it.
It is a big one. I've already purchased
a bunch of um we'll say exposure to the
SpaceX IPO cuz you can't buy it straight
away. But, before we jump into anything
like that, like I said, I'm going to do
that later in the week. So, make sure
you're following my socials.
But, let's jump into Bitcoin. So, let me
share screen with you all shortly. Make
sure you guys are seeing it.
And I really want to deep dive into how
we approach this moving forward because
as the headline represents, Bitcoin
could potentially die tomorrow. And
there is some merit in that, but no, I
do not think Bitcoin is going to $0.
That would be ridiculous to say. Now,
team, if you guys have not noticed quite
recently, um this is one of the biggest
outliers of what I'm watching in the
current environment. And something that
I think is absolutely nuts, to say the
least. Right? This came out just the
other day.
And you can see this here. Mr. Donald
Trump is putting out some weird and
wonderful tweets at the moment. Wild
tweet uh tweets, like crazy stuff,
right? I've never seen a president do
anything like this in my entire life. I
think it's absolutely ridiculous. But,
you can see it here. "Tuesday will be
power plant day and bridge day all
wrapped into one in Iran. There'll be
nothing like it. Open the effin
straight, you crazy bastards, or you'll
be living in hell. Just watch." Praise
be to like this This is unheard of.
I think putting tweets out like this is
dangerous. I think it is unheard of. I
think personally it makes you look like
an absolute imbecile, and it starts to
turn a lot of the world on you. Let's be
real. Now, guys, tell me what you think
in the comments for this because I think
this is absolutely nuts. And it's why I
did name the the the topic of the the
overall call, right? Bitcoin could die
or Bitcoin dies tomorrow. And the the
title of the call is a trap, right? I
want to show you guys why I think what
is currently happening is a trap because
as it currently stands, they're also
talking about the potential of a
proposed 45- day 45-day ceasefire,
right? Now, you can see here US and Iran
consider 45-day ceasefire deal while
pursuing
uh war. This to me, again, I take this
with a massive grain of salt. The reason
I've got to show you guys this first
because it makes all the sense in what
I'm seeing on the charts. So, you've got
to put two and two together. You can't
just look at one in silo. You've got to
measure it all together. How does it
actually make sense? So,
when you take this into consideration,
if the US at the moment is considering
and Iran consider 45-day ceasefire, why
is there such crazy wild threats? Why
are we seeing planes being shot down
just a couple days ago? Why are we
seeing the Iran come out and say, "Hey,
we're not in no negotiations. We don't
even know where this is coming from."
It is wild at the moment. There is that
much uncertainty between this situation
that it's now starting to reflect on the
charts as it has historically. But, I
want to show you guys where it is at the
moment because what this is going to say
and what is going to occur is if we
don't have any sort of a relief in this
current environment,
it is going to start to lead to immense
amounts of inflation, which is going to
continue to put pressure on the economy.
And again, we know Bitcoin doesn't like
that. So, I want to show you guys what
I'm seeing on the charts and how we can
mirror this news up with what is
actually happening in the market. And
we're going to run with it. Bitcoin
could potentially die tomorrow,
especially if this crazy person starts
doing [ __ ] like this. It is going to
throw things absolutely wild. I don't
want to see this happen. The reason I
don't want to see this happen is you
start bombing power plants, that starts
putting people into all sorts of serious
and bad situations, hospitals, the whole
works. It's not something you want to
see. It's not funny. It is quite
disturbing, to say the least, and not
something I thought I would see in my
lifetime from um someone of that status.
But, again, guys, I don't really want to
give my view on all this. I just want to
give you guys the facts, the data of
what's actually happening. And I'll be
be very intrigued if this does occur. If
this does occur,
whole different situation on the market.
I personally don't think a ceasefire is
going to occur. I think we're more along
the lines of seeing a ground invasion,
which is going to then potentially play
out exactly what I'm seeing on Bitcoin.
So, we're up to 79 viewers. Thank you
very much, team. If you haven't done so
already, make sure you drop comments in
there. Make sure you uh liking the
stream, sharing it with your friends.
Again, we hit over 100, we'll do a 100
USDT giveaway at today. As soon as we
hit it over 100 as well, I'll drop it in
the comments. I'll do the little spinny
wheel like I did last time. I'll send it
out. So, the way you get access to the
giveaway is to make sure that you have
commented cuz what I do is I pull the
username out from there, and then I post
it on my socials so you guys can see
exactly who has been chosen.
Um and I also do the the draw live. So,
I'll do it on Wednesday if we hit over
100. But, let's break this down now. So,
Bitcoin, we are up here on the weekly
time frame at the moment. Um
Uh there is a lot of There is always a
lot of scams and IPOs. I'll go through
the comments in a second. But, let's
jump into Bitcoin. So, the big one on
Bitcoin at the moment, right? And this
is one of the things that I met I
measured up to an absolute T from this
entire move. So, I was always watching
this big bear flag take effect, which
played out. Um
you can ask my community all that sort
of stuff. I've got multiple historical
charts on that. Now, where we're
currently faced with, I want to show you
guys this. I'm going to zoom into this
very closely so you guys can see this
because
a lot of people aren't talking about
this. Now,
if you haven't noticed, we're starting
to form another big bear flag. You can
see that here. Now, my trend line here
might not look as accurate as on the on
the weekly, but I want to show you guys
this on the daily time frame and where
it is currently. So, you can see here
there is 69,647.
So,
I'm a bit advocate for Fibonacci based
trends. I love fibs. A lot of my trading
is based around Fibonacci. So, I want to
show you guys what could be potentially
happening here and what I'm seeing play
out right now.
So,
what you can see here, I'm going to rip
this into the daily time frame for a
moment, right? You can see this is where
I've just drawn that line to show you
guys the 618 fib level and it also the
69,647
dollar mark. Now, I did have an alert
just go off a moment ago around 70,000
dollars.
I was looking at potential short at that
level. Um full transparency, I didn't
get a chance to place my order. I was on
another live call with my community just
chatting and going through similar stuff
um but in a lot more detail. And looking
at this as it stands, you can see two
things happening here. A, yes, we've had
buyers step in, which is good early
signs. You can see here buying pressure,
that big green bar. So, big fat order
zones are presenting themselves here on
the daily time frame.
But the problem we're starting to face
is the fact that price is actually
starting to break below the trend line.
And you can see we've got multiple
touches on this trend line that have
acted as a resistance and acted as a
level of support. Now, this is where it
gets a little bit scary for me and why
Bitcoin for myself and where I'm where
I'm looking at this plus me what's
what's going on in the war situation is
we're actually struggling to get back
above this level. And this level being
69,647.
Now,
in a fantastic environment and a long
environment as what I would love to see
is a breakout and a retest and a push
back towards targeting the 75k range.
Now, that in itself would be a fantastic
scenario, right? Hands up if you love to
see 75k Bitcoin. Me personally, would
love to see it. Why? It gives everyone a
nice little relief rally. The altcoins
will run alongside with it. Ethereum
will pump. It'll be happy days and
everything will be sweet.
Now, the situation we're faced with is
that is an 8% move. That is fantastic.
However, as price currently stands,
right? And as you can see now,
the
weekly close
for the US market was actually down
here.
This is where we start to doll back.
>> [clears throat and snorts]
>> We start to look at facts and figures
versus hype and all the rest of the crap
that comes along with it. Because the
reality of what happens is and I spoke
about this last week,
right? Is a lot of the times you get
what's called the fake move Mondays,
right? Price rallies only to then come
back and revisit the area in which the
US market closed on the previous week.
And that's exactly what we saw take
effect last week as well. Now,
history doesn't always repeat itself,
but it often rhymes. And you can go
back, do yourself an idea or do yourself
a bit of a research. Go back. Oh, we hit
100. Happy days, team. We're doing a
giveaway. Make sure you've commented in
the chat. If you haven't done so, you
won't be available for the giveaway. So,
again, if you guys want, I can leave it
up to you. We can either do uh 100 USDT
or we can do 50 250 USDT giveaways. Let
you guys what write in there. I'll pick
the majority, whatever you guys want to
do. Um we can do 250 dollar ones or we
can do one 100 USDT. The user gets
picked from the comments. So, if you
haven't done so, make sure you whack a
comment in there and I'll extract you
guys all later on.
But getting back on topic, go back do
yourself a favor. Go back and look at
the weekly close on the Friday and then
when price moves to on the Monday, and
you'll see majority of the time price
eventually comes back to where
the market closed on Friday. Now, the
situation [clears throat]
that we're faced with at the moment,
this is where I really want to break
this down for you all and really dig
deep into here. So, you can see what's
happening here, right?
On Friday last week or Thursday because
again, it was a it was a holiday on
Friday, markets were closed. Price
closed around 66,700
dollars. But where is price currently?
It's currently around 69,500
dollars.
So, what do we think is going to happen
in this situation? Well,
this is exactly what I think is going to
happen. We rallied,
we reject, and in all honesty, if we do
not hold here at 66,600,
66,700,
we'll just leave it at that.
And candles start to close below, see
this midpoint range of the order zone.
If candles start closing below that
level, again,
then my target will be 63,000 all the
way down to 62, 61.
And the scary fact of the matter is is
if
this takes effect,
okay? And we've already seen Fed Powell
come out and talk about inflation and
they're scared. They are genuinely
scared about inflation at the moment. Um
and I'm seeing it in like from my
background on markets in Australia, I
don't live in Australia at the moment,
right? But I'm seeing this across the
board. Governments are very scared of
inflation at the moment and what they're
already interested in doing is they're
interested in putting interest rates up
to combat it. It's up to me personally,
I think it's counterintuitive. The cost
of living is going up through the roof.
People are getting stung on fuel cost,
cost of living overall. Then you're
telling them you want to put interest
rates. There is very big scares
at the moment for a global recession if
this war continues and oil prices
continue to pump, right? Now, this is
how I see this all playing out. If that
does occur,
we don't get any of this,
we get a lot of this,
and Bitcoin fails here at that retest,
then my target of what I've always seen
and had forecasted
for this entire move,
which is from here, the target is the
one Fibonacci ratio. So, you guys,
whoever does trade based upon fib
levels,
there's a big situation here where
when you get these big moves on bear
flags using trend based fib, the target
is typically the one. Now, it doesn't
mean it goes in a straight full flat
fashion. It does go through levels. It
just stands the way markets operate.
They go up and down.
As it stands, the target is still
sitting around 52,000 dollars.
So,
we're starting to break this bear flag.
We're starting to put in lower lows in
comparison to where price was
historically.
Price is currently struggling to get
back above and this is essentially the
fake move Monday situation taking
effect.
I don't think we go straight deep down
drop. That's not what I'm saying. I'm
saying we're going to come back. I do
believe we come back, we retest 66,626.
From there, we come back. If that does
fail, 61,000 definitely on the cards for
me.
And if that breaks and all hell
absolutely breaks loose, again,
below this channel, we break below,
this is how I see it foresee this entire
move taking effect.
Now, it's not something I want to see,
team. It's I'm not I'm not saying I want
this to happen. Again, I would rather
the market go up to make it easier for
everyone, right? I am
again, I'm a trader. I just look for
opportunities. I'm not here to bag hold
or anything like that. But that is what
I'm currently seeing on Bitcoin at the
moment to take effect before anything
else. I don't see how people are saying
80,000 is next. That puts in a higher
high. It's got to break three different
resistance levels before that even
occurs. There is a lot to happen before
then and with the current tensions on
the rise, I don't see it happening. I
don't know how people are saying it.
Um
the only
small indicator
that I wanted to bring to everyone's
attention, you can see this is the
weekly time frame, right? Um again,
price is holding the support around
65,000. We've been monitoring that
channel for a very, very long time. Um
still great like, you know,
fantastic. Bitcoin is still holding
above that point. That's why I'm saying
it doesn't free It's not going to be a
free fall. Again, closes below those
order zones and then trickle on effect,
but you can see the next big, big order
zone for Bitcoin
is lines up perfectly with my one
Fibonacci ratio, right? At 52,000
dollars. This is the big mother of order
zones. 36 million transactions of
Bitcoin are sitting historically taken
effect at this level.
These levels of these big order zones
typically act acts like price magnets
essentially.
Um and you can see where they've all
taken effect on the weekly time frame.
Historically, the one at um 126,000,
the one at 94,000, and the next big one
is at 52,000 as it stands. So, what I'll
do is I'll take a snapshot of this. I'll
whack it on my X after the call. So, if
you guys want it, you can grab a hold of
this. Um we're at 109. Happy days.
Team, well done.
We haven't seen any comments around the
giveaway. I'm going to do a giveaway.
It's going to be 100 USDT. So, the fact
of the matter is whether or not you guys
want 100 USDT directly sent or you want
two 50 USDT
giveaways. So, write in the comments
which one you guys want. If not, I'll
make an executive decision and just go
with the 100. But if you guys want me to
do two 50 dollar ones, then whack it in
there. Whack it in the comments and I'll
take it from there. And again, guys, you
have to be eligible only if you have
commented. So, if you haven't done so
yet, make sure you comment on the video.
Um last time I did do a giveaway, people
like, "Why didn't you do the comments on
the on the um
the recording?"
Look, I'm happy to do it on the
recording, but I'll do it for the next
one. I love that we've got to celebrate
the fact that we're over 100 today, and
I'm going to give it for all of you that
have supported the stream um and have
jumped on today, you're going to be
eligible for the giveaway. Again, just
make sure you have dropped a comment,
that's how you will get access. Now,
I want to show you guys something
>> [clears throat]
>> alongside this.
Just have some water, one second.
I want to show you guys how I break down
this further. Now,
there's only one real thing that I'm
looking at that's giving me a bit of
optimism.
Now, I'm always I'm always going to show
you guys two sides of the coin. I'm not
going to give you one biased remark.
I've given you my strong point of view.
It's quite obvious what I see foresee
happening. To really wrap things up, I
think we come back and
revisit the daily close, which was on
Friday for the US market, which again
sat around $66,700.
We can clarify that. Now,
the biggest optimistic piece for me in
which I'm looking at is the weekly time
frame on Bitcoin and the weekly time
frame on USDT dominance. But, it's very
basic. It's only one confirmation, it's
nothing more.
I've got nothing else supporting it.
Make that very clear. Nothing else is
supporting this for me personally,
right? The only thing that I foresee
here
is this.
We've got rising momentum. What that
means is is if you look up here,
historically when we had drops
at this point
and at this point, these were much
deeper. You can see the momentum and the
selling pressure was in -300 on the CCI.
It was at -160.
And as it currently stands, it's still
rising. So, now we're at about -100,
which means essentially selling pressure
at the current point in time
has started to fade.
So, it's good early indicator,
but it's not enough for me to go, you
know, the bottom's in or 52k is off the
cards right now. We've just been
hovering below and around 65,000 and
essentially 70,000. Nothing else has
really given us confirmation. So, that
is why I'm taking this part here with a
grain of salt.
And why I'm still thinking I'm more
bearish as opposed to longs, right?
It's just because the data's telling me
that, and I'm not going to choose
otherwise. I'll take scalp positions,
don't get me wrong. I've been scalping
the last uh week with my community. We
jump on live. We had a couple of scalp
sessions. You know, we scalp Bitcoin, we
scalp ETH on a long. You know, happy
days and a couple of other ones.
The other one that I wanted to show you
guys is not so much the US 500 right
now,
>> [clears throat]
>> but I wanted to show you guys
USDT dominance. So, this is a negative
correlation. This works opposite to
Bitcoin. This rises, Bitcoin drops. This
drops, Bitcoin pumps, right? Very simple
fact.
Now, you look at this how it currently
stands.
Big fat order zone at the top of the
range here.
Okay? This is historically marked the
top of the bear market.
Historically. Okay? Make that very
clear.
Back in 2023, 2022, 20 and when uh 2022
May, when this has dropped down, we've
then had these relief rallies, this is
when we had big major pushes on Bitcoin.
As it currently stands, we're back at
that level.
And again, the only one optimistic piece
I'm looking taking from this is you can
see that momentum is currently starting
to fade on this on the on the um USDT
dominance part. You can see that we've
had multiple peaks, right? Similar to
what we had on Bitcoin. And then the
current one hasn't actually spiked all
that much and has actually started to
die off.
Again, one other early indicator I can't
use this as a confirmation. It is just
one piece of the puzzle,
right? Some people be looking at this as
a potential double top, but again,
there's no confirmation in that just
yet. It's very small, right? There's
nothing there.
The daily time frame, as you can see,
amongst this level, it is still rising.
You can see the 50 EMA here, the blue
line is the 50 EMA.
It is now bouncing off a level of
support
and going to be very interesting to see
where this lands over the next 24-48
hours. And if this again gives us the
movement on what I'm predicting to take
effect on Bitcoin to revisit the daily
close on Friday. But, you can see here,
there's now a channel that has started
to form. I've make a made a mention of
this last time, right? This time here,
drop below and then again, regain that
channel. So, we're back at that level
once again. So, the question remains,
right? I want to make this very clear.
>> [clears throat and cough]
>> I'm still bearish in the grand scheme of
things
because I've had no confirmation. And if
anything, to me, I look at things and
things are just getting worse, right?
This here does not signify anything
remotely
good at all. Um this is very early days,
but then you have the conflicting
message of Iran saying, "Hey, there's no
ceasefire."
Oil prices are still spiking,
right? We've had a 1% move down today,
nothing major. Um again, futures market.
But, again, um last week,
massive market push,
right? Massive push on oil prices again,
up 13%. So, I don't know about you guys,
but you've seen on the on the boards,
you've seen it on the on the on the
prices of of service stations at the
moment.
Fuel is still high, which means
inflation is going to rise. There is
predictions of 20% increases in food
across the board at the moment. 20%
increases in energy. It everything is
going up dramatically, and that there
won't create this risk on appetite
people are looking for to get Bitcoin to
pump the way they want it to. Now, to
really tie a lot of this in, this is the
part that I was watching for. I'm going
to go through the comments shortly, but
this is the part I was watching for last
week, which you guys know I've been
quite vocal about. This is my chart that
I use for the US 500, and again, has
allowed me to understand bull market
scenarios.
Okay? I'll just zoom out on this for a
moment just so if you're new to this
channel and you haven't seen this, you
can have a quick glimpse of it where it
represents the bull markets that have
taken effect at the same time when the
CCI has been completely over oversold,
sorry. Now,
as it stands and you guys are fully
aware, this was my biggest play and my
biggest focus. All right? It was this
drop here, which came back down to the
113 fib level. Again, another critical
fib level that I'm always watching and
paying attention to, which has now
bounced off. All right? We've re-tackled
and regained the range back above the 50
EMA. Again, very early signs because
what that does is it opens up a range of
6.8%.
Okay? But, we're hanging below the 200
EMA. So, again, I'm taking this with a
grain of salt because
the fundamentals at the moment
aren't supporting the charts.
For me, that's a problem.
Usually, I love to reference the charts
and I use them as my early indicators,
and I have confidence in my charting
abilities, and quite it works well,
typically.
But, I Like I said to my community today
is
I'm not in the market at the moment
to hold positions for a long period of
time.
Okay? I'm not trading daily and 4-hour
time frames in the hope that I can hold
these trades for multiple days and get
the very best out of them.
When I'm trading the market at the
moment, it is very much smaller time
frame trades. I'll give you guys a very
simple example, right? I was trading
Ethereum.
I've been measuring this move on
Ethereum for quite some time. You can
see the rising channel on Ethereum. You
got higher lows, higher lows, higher
lows, higher lows, higher lows. Big fat
order zone representing the fact that
buying pressure is still in effect.
But, I'll break this down for you guys,
all right?
Guys, thank you very much for the for
your support on the stream. I'm going to
break this down very shortly for you
all. Show you guys a couple other ones,
then we'll wrap it up. But, I've got a
few important things I want to get
through before anything else. And again,
thank you very much for the support.
We've got the $100 giveaway banked in.
I'm going to go through the comments in
a section in a second. But, Ethereum is
one of the ones I wanted to show you
all.
All right? Now, this is where people are
going to get caught.
Because look at this.
All right?
This is good early signs again.
Higher lows, higher lows, higher lows,
higher lows.
Ethereum building its case for potential
breakout.
You look at it from the flip side,
order zone, big fat order zone,
resistance, resistance. And what
happened here?
Significantly over-purchased
fake move scenario.
All right?
Now, I took a trade on Ethereum. This is
why I wanted to jump into this because
I was scalp trading Ethereum with with a
couple of my team. And again, got an
entry here and took profit around here.
All right? Quick 10-20% move, again,
10x. Don't need to go dramatic. Lock in
profits, move on to the next one. All
right? This here then took effect last
night on a Sunday evening with no basis
whatsoever. Again, fake moves.
I'm not interested, right? I don't trade
Sunday nights.
But, as it stands, you can see it
completely over-purchased, momentum is
coming off.
What I see potentially happening here is
very simple.
This rejects, comes back, and retests
this level.
Alternatively, my play for Ethereum, so
you guys are aware my play for ethereum
is two scenarios. We come back and we
retest.
Right? Because we've already had the big
fake move out. Or the other option is we
get the breakout.
And then we get the retest. And again,
price will be at the current position in
where it is currently. But I'm not going
to long into resistance. I'm not going
to take a long position into resistance
hoping that it breaks out. Keep it very
simple. I long off support. I short off
resistance and I don't hope hope for
breakouts. It's very much that easy to
understand. All right?
And again, the team, whilst I share a
lot of this for you all, just remember a
lot of it's it's all education. I'm not
giving you guys financial advice here.
I'm teaching you guys the way I look at
things. You guys take it away, use it as
you please. But my basis is giving you
guys the education so then you guys can
and do this sort of stuff on your own
terms. Um but again, it's easier said
than done and it does go a long way when
you start to learn this stuff
again for yourself, right? It makes it a
hell of a lot easier. For ethereum in
itself,
looking at a reasonably good move. It's
9% to the top of the range.
Or 25% to the next 200 EMA, which would
be the longer-term target. But as I was
explaining to my team, this would be my
first take profit. This would be my
second take profit, but only if we get
the breakout. Until a lot of that
happens, I'm simply looking for the
small timeframe trades, scalping
1-hours, closing them on the 4-hours,
locking in profits and moving on to the
next best thing. So,
thank you for that one. Now, team, I did
want to have a look at two other charts
just quickly
and then I'm going to jump into the
comments to see what you guys are
working through and just to make sure we
addressed any questions as well. Thank
you for jumping on. It has been a
fantastic session.
Um Solana, again, one of the big ones
that I am watching for, guys. Daily
timeframe. This coin in itself has not
done well.
Right? It is not doing well whatsoever
at the moment, but it is still holding
this big fat order zone that we has been
valid for quite some time and I have
been monitoring
again, these entire streams.
Has had ample opportunity since February
to take it to the top of the range. And
the top of the range there is 20% move.
So again, plenty of opportunity in this
one with Solana. But again, it's just
bubbling away at the bottom.
It continuously hits selling pressure
and again, another big order zone has
formed.
And no real basis at the moment for a
great trade whatsoever.
So,
again, team, the message in in sort of
what I'm giving you guys today
and [clears throat] I'm very transparent
about this is there is a lot of
uncertainty at the moment, right?
Despite the fact that a lot of early
moves on late Sunday and Monday, a lot
of those moves end up being invalid,
right? They end up being invalid because
the US doesn't want to leave what's
called a CME gap at the bottom of those
ranges. And they're in whether you like
it or not, they dictate a lot of the
market. Asia doesn't dictate the market.
London doesn't dictate the market. They
basically move throughout the session,
but the US will ultimately come in and
swing the market in whichever way they
deem fit.
And as it currently stands,
the US 500 again,
very early days of a bounce, but very
early days of also potential change in
downwards market structure. You've got
potential of high inflation coming in,
especially if this war continues, it's
only going to get worse before it gets
better. A lot of the effect of what's
currently happening doesn't really hit
the markets properly until a couple of
months in. So, just pay take that note
into consideration. That especially
happens with interest rates as well.
Now,
team, I'm just going to have a quick
look at the comments section here before
we dive into anything else. See what's
happening. I do appreciate you guys
being on the stream. It's been
fantastic. So, thank you very, very
much. I always want to see what we've
got in the comments section before
anything else. Looks like we've got a
base for one person saying 50/50,
another person saying 100 USD would be
lovely.
50/50 looks to be the the go, but
according to everyone, there's a lot
more comments around doing the 50 USD
take giveaway. So, I'll do two of those.
So, if you haven't done so already, make
make sure you smash the comments. Again,
that is where I pull the winner from.
So, I grab all the usernames. I then go
ahead put it on a spinning wheel. I
choose at random whoever wins. I'll post
the winner on my X and on my Instagram.
So, if you haven't done so already, make
sure you follow me on X. Make sure you
follow me on Instagram. You can see them
there bottom in the bottom left corner
there.
That's where I will post a lot of my
alerts, lifestyle stuff, all that sort
of things that come with it. And let me
just have a read through, see if we've
got any specific comments. For Is
anyone's got any questions? This is a
perfect time to write them in there
because this is where I will address the
questions for you all as well. And like
I said, team, I'm also going to pull a
notice on my socials to run through the
SpaceX IPO. I'll be putting that up
um over the next couple of days. Whether
or not I do that tomorrow or Wednesday,
I'll let you guys know, but I'm thinking
that is going to be a big one and I'll
show you guys how I've got exposure to
that and how basically anyone can do
this
with ease. It's so simple. Just no one
thinks about it. Um what have we got
here? What's your current Bitcoin mood?
I'm looking at this. What have we got?
Calm calmly holding spot.
Hedging for a drop. Watching from the
sidelines. Looking for the breakout. 24
votes. Guys, don't forget whack your
vote in there. I'm really interested to
see.
For me personally,
I'm still more bearish than anything
else. I at least think we're going to
come back, revisit that $66,500
mark where the US market closed last um
Friday. Uh sorry, last Thursday cuz
Friday was a public holiday.
Brett Thompson, I have faith in you
charting Kangamath. Guys, I will say
charting is my specialty. It's what I
absolutely love. Um trading levels, 1%
pump on your favorite coin.
>> [laughter]
>> I love the comments, guys. I do
appreciate it. So, team, what I will do
is I'll wrap it up there. We've been
going for 35 minutes. If you haven't
done so already, again, like me on the
socials. I'm going to go live again on
Wednesday. I'm going to put it in a
bonus session as well in a month that to
talk about the SpaceX IPO if you are
interested in that as well. I think it's
a big one. It's said to be probably one
of the biggest evaluations and IPOs in
history. They're estimating $2 trillion,
which is huge in itself. And similar to
what we put as the thumbnail today, I do
not hope Bitcoin dies tomorrow.
Could it be a possibility? It could be a
possibility any day.
Um but again, team, I think what is
happening today is a trap. I think we
are going to come back down, revisit
that $66,500 on Bitcoin. If we lose that
level, I do foresee 62, 61,000 and if
that drops, my major target of what I've
been watching for this entire time,
which is 52,000 and the big weekly order
zone, the bearish flag
on the be on the cards, especially if
Mr. Donald Trump does what he says he
wants to do, which I hope he doesn't.
So, team, thank you very much. I'll
catch you guys for the next stream on
Wednesday and have an absolute ripper
week and good luck on the markets. Speak
to you all shortly.