All right, we're live Coin Bureau fans.
We've got a big session scheduled for us
today. This one here is all about the
ceasefire and the market pumping. So,
everyone's seen this ceasefire news.
Markets are pumping at the moment and
the question right now is should you
actually be buying Bitcoin here? That is
the common thing I woke up to in my
inbox today. So,
I'll be honest. This doesn't move
This move doesn't look clean to me at
this current point, right? I'm looking
at things. I'm questioning everything
and I'm going, is this actually
legitimate or not? Or is this whole
thing completely fake?
So, team, give us a moment. We're going
to let everyone jump into the into the
stream like we usually do. We've got to
give it a couple of minutes for people
to jump in and then we'll dive straight
into everything. I've got a jam-packed
session for you all because
this move that's currently taking place,
I watched it all happen live last night
and it's completely wild how fast things
change from potentially the whole
civilization being wiped out, which were
the comments, which were absolutely
ridiculous,
to
the Prime Minister of Pakistan reaching
out to Iran and the US to all of a
sudden put a 2-week ceasefire in place
and now ships are flowing through like
nothing has even happened. It is
absolutely
wild.
So, let's give everyone 30 seconds. I've
got a lot to cover. I've got Bitcoin
charts. I've got altcoin charts. I've
got price points that I'm watching for.
Absolutely everything ready to go for
every single one of you. So, this is the
big stream. It's an exciting stream and
so much has happened after Bitcoin has
thrown in 5% leg after that news came
out just late last night. So,
without uh further ado, I do want to
jump into everything. Everyone is
starting to come in and for what I also
wanted to make a mention of
is on Monday, we hit 116
viewers at once, live. Absolutely huge.
At the moment, we've got 34 viewers live
and this will gradually build, but this
only built because of you guys and the
big one here is we're doing the giveaway
today. So, we're giving away 100 USDT
for everyone that joins on live on
Monday.
I've got the spinning wheel ready to go.
We're going to do that at the end of the
stream. So, if you were here on Monday,
make sure you stay on till the end. You
will see if you've won
um 100 USDT, but what we did do is we
split it into two $50 USDT giveaways.
So, that is what we we will be giving
away at the end of the stream and if we
hit another 100 viewers live today, we
will do another 100 USDT giveaway on
Monday. So, that is completely up to you
guys. If you haven't done so already,
make sure you like the stream. Make sure
you're commenting. Make sure you're
sharing this out on socials and with
your friends because that is how we get
into the giveaway section of having 100
people live. Every time we have 100
people live, telling you now, I'm going
to pump out a giveaway and today we've
got one giveaway from Monday and
hopefully we can get another one for
next week if we hit over 100 viewers
today. So, everyone is starting to jump
in. So, I want to get straight into
things. I'm going to share my screen
with you all. Give me one moment. I'm
just going to move one or two screens
around
and then we can get into I've got the
comments open on my right-hand side. Be
mindful, team. We haven't got a
moderator today. She had to She was on
holidays, which is awesome. Good on her.
And um
I'll be monitoring all sections of
everything. So,
you guys should be able to see my screen
now. That should be coming up for
everyone and I guys can see I am on the
Bitcoin chart on the weekly timeframe,
which is what we have been monitoring
this entire period. I'm going to show
you this in a little while. I'm going to
dive a little bit deeper into this, but
before we get into any of this piece,
this is where it gets rather
interesting, right? The moment I woke up
this morning, I knew what happened last
night. I said to myself, has Have we
actually had a ceasefire?
Because we've seen this happen a number
of times. We've had ceasefire,
ceasefire, ceasefire and actually
nothing has happened, right? No
ceasefire has actually taken place. So,
I'm going to bring you guys into this
and how this is flowing into the charts
because it's what we did on Monday and
it's what the predictions are starting
to look for as well and how we're seeing
things play out. So,
team, two comments in here at the
moment. If you want to be part of the
giveaways, you've got to put yourself in
the comment section. Make sure you're
liking the stream. Make sure you're
sharing it out live with everyone as
well. So, first big one here was the
ceasefire was shattered in a matter of
hours. So, this to me is a big red flag.
Um it is an early red flag. I can
understand when these sort of things are
going on. You don't want everything just
stops instantly. You've got to have that
flow-on effect, but this here was not a
great early sign by any means possible.
And the other big one is that there is
still missiles being flown into other
countries such as Lebanon, which was
meant to be part of the ceasefire. So,
to me at the moment, it's telling me
Israel is sort of complying with some of
the ceasefire, not all of it and I think
this is starting to look really, really
interesting when the US and Iran are
both claiming victory as well. Me
personally,
if it is the case, so be it. But the
reason I wanted to touch on this first
is because how this is going to affect
the markets. That is the biggest piece
of the puzzle right now. Is how is this
going to affect the markets and as this
Is this current move that we just saw
on
Tuesday, yesterday,
fake?
Let that sink in for a second because
as it stands, what was happening was we
had a breakdown of the bear flag
initially. Then we had the little
candle. You can see this one here that
then held back within the trend and has
now pushed up. Last night, we had
essentially a reversal of 4 1/2 thousand
dollars on Bitcoin. A roughly 6% candle
took effect. Now, the candle itself
between the open and the close was about
4 1/2% to 5%.
Quite a reasonable push. Now, that all
happened as soon as the ceasefire was
announced and rumors started spiraling.
So, it is a very, very good early stage
of crypto and for the global markets.
Now, one thing that people aren't taking
note of at the moment, which I think is
critically important to validate whether
or not this move is going to hold up is
what's happening on the US 500, the
futures market at the moment. I'm going
to show you guys that in a little while.
Now,
people saying new tariffs. Look, I have
seen already that has taken effect. I
saw an article just 2 seconds ago
talking about the fact that if the US
supplies Iran with weapons, it's going
to be a 50% tariff and in my head I'm
going, why in any means necessary would
you supply your enemy essentially with
weapons, especially when they've had
sanctions on in the past? It's a very
interesting time.
But before we dive into that, I want to
focus on Bitcoin. This one here is
really the big factor at the moment.
Now, let me break this down for you guys
from an educational standpoint and the
reason I say that is everything that I
share on this channel is educational
purposes only and everything I'm sharing
with you guys is from my own personal
experiences, my own learnings, my own
sharing so that you guys can see exactly
how I'm interpreting the charts and what
I am doing on the charts as well.
Now, the way I look at this and I put a
post up in my community earlier on, my
Empire Crypto Trading Community. There's
a link in the bio for this as well. If
you guys want to jump in on there and
stay more in tune with what I'm actually
doing and how I'm assessing the market
as well, make sure you click that link
below. I've done a deal with Coin
Bureau. They've actually given away 14
days free for everyone as well. So, you
can click that link and get access
directly there.
But
when I look for these measured moves,
this is the first fundamental factor,
right? You can see here that from the
Fibonacci level that we've had the
retracement, which was 3 1/2%
from that point then we've then had
essentially
you can see here a 6 1/2% push. Now,
when I look for particular targets for
these pushes, again, you guys know that
follow me regularly, I'm big on
Fibonacci ratios.
I look for pushes towards the 1.618 fib
level. Take note of that, team. If you
didn't know this already, write it down
because 1.618 ratio on the Fibonacci
levels is common target for big,
large-scale moves like we had and you
can see that this also matched up with
right at the top of the order zone,
which we've then seen price action
stall, which was around 72 thousand
dollars.
Now,
the big factor here and the way that I
look for these big movements in the
crypto market and Bitcoin in particular
is I look at the momentum that has come
in, right? The volume, the momentum of
the push itself. And on this most recent
push that we had, you can see that the
momentum The momentum was quite low It
was a lot lower than what we had
previously. Now, if you guys weren't
aware of this and you weren't awake, you
wouldn't know this.
But this entire move
took effect
during the market close.
So, take that into consideration for a
moment, right?
On
yesterday, Tuesday, when we had this
move within the market, the US market
was actually closed.
So, in theory,
the US market actually closed around
this level here,
around 69 thousand dollars.
And previous to that on Thursday last
week, the US closed the market at around
here, $66,000.
So, essentially, there is a gap in the
market between this entire level that
still needs, in my opinion, to be
revisited.
So, that is why I'm still a big believer
of the fact that this current move here
is still somewhat of a fake move. Now,
let me walk you through all of this.
All right? I'm going to take you guys
through this in a lot of details, so
make sure you're paying attention. If
you've got questions, whack them in the
comments.
Um and if you haven't done so already,
guys, make sure you like the stream. We
had a massive stream on Monday. We're
doing the giveaway today. You can see
here we've got the wheel of names and
all the
um
usernames ready to go. I'll be spinning
this at the end of the stream to see who
picks up 50 USDT each. We're doing this
for two people. So, if you haven't done
so already, make sure you like the
stream. Make sure you share. Make sure
you comment because that has how you get
eligibility for this as well.
Now,
what I want to see happen here, and what
I'm thinking is going to happen given
tonight's action, is
as this as it currently stands, we're
trending sideways.
All right? We're trending sideways from
this current move that took effect.
All right? And the way I look at this is
at the moment the market had that move
outside the US time zone last night. And
Asia and London don't typically dictate
which way the market is going to move.
So,
I'm expecting a lot of volatility to
come in
really soon. And the reason I say very
soon is because you can see within an
hour and 16 minutes the US market is set
to open.
But I'm going to show you guys how I've
sort of connected the dots here. And why
I think this move is still somewhat
fake. All right?
As it stands,
and I'm going to minimize this so we can
zoom out here and have a bit more of a
bigger look. All right? The order zone
in which we're playing around with at
the moment is sitting at roughly
$72,000.
So, in theory,
price needs to break above this point,
retest the 1618, and that will then give
Bitcoin the opportunity to run towards
$75,000,
which lines up with the rest of this
channel. Now, Bitcoin actually hasn't
done that just yet. And Bitcoin in
itself front run the news. All right?
What I mean by that, the moment the news
dropped, the moment Bitcoin was already
moving, which was also the moment in
which the US market had already opened.
So, am I expecting another massive push
on Bitcoin tonight?
Personally, no.
Not right now. And the reason I say that
is I typically look at the rotational
element of how these things operate.
Usually, you get the US 500 move first,
Bitcoin follows, or vice versa. And in
this case, I'm looking at the fact that
Bitcoin has potentially front run the US
500 or the SPX, right?
>> [clears throat]
>> That essentially did not move yesterday
because of the market being closed.
So, in theory, I'm considering a
pullback on Bitcoin than what I am more
so.
>> [clears throat]
>> Excuse me, guys. Um as an actual push.
And you can see this here. You can look
at this on the daily time frame as well.
All right? I think this makes it very
clear to see what is currently taking
effect, even if I remove the Fibonacci
ratios, right? What we've essentially
had is we've had price action trend
sideways
within this bear flag.
Essentially, retest the bottom of the
low that you can see take effect here,
and has now essentially pushed back up,
which is a great early sign. But what
typically happens when this occurs is
price then comes back and retests the
bottom of the range before moving
through to the remainder of the channel.
With, obviously, 75,000 being the first
connected point or the first point of
resistance in which I'll be targeting
for this move. But you can see I've
already got an alert set at 69,664
because I do believe the market will
head back towards that area at some
given point this week. All right?
>> [clears throat]
>> Let me make that thing clear that part
there clear.
It doesn't mean necessarily that
instantly tonight the market is going to
tank. But I do believe, in my heart of
hearts, the market will come back and
retest this current point.
And if not, come and retest the bottom
of the range here that actually sits at
around 66,800,
which was left open from essentially
last week last Thursday.
When the markets closed. Now,
in saying all of this, right? I want to
connect you with what is happening on
the US 500 cuz this is the big point
that a lot of people haven't noticed
yet, right? The US 500,
the futures market in particular, is
already up 2.6% for the day.
That is off the base of the news that is
currently taking effect, which is
absolutely
huge. Right, guys? I need a This is a
large number for the US 500 to move 2
and 1/2% before market open. It is big.
That means people are buying up stocks
right now. They're buying up futures
market stocks, right?
So, take note of that. But typically,
when I see this happen, I'm a very big
advocate from the fact that the crypto
market would then follow suit and and
move along with it.
But last night, we already had Bitcoin
push 6%
whilst the US market was closed.
So, am I right to assume that Bitcoin
should again push another 6% because
this is already pushed 2 and 1/2%? In
this current situation, no. In this
current situation, I'm playing a little
bit more cautiously because
look, call me a little bit more, I don't
know, what do you say? If you want to
call it ignorant, if you want to call it
um
cautious, however you want to put it,
I'm still not overly convinced about
this. Yes, we've had a lot of news come
out.
Yes, we've had Iran actually come out
and, you know, put out statements, etc.,
etc.
But I'm very cautious over the next 2
weeks on how this plays out because
within 2 weeks, negotiations still need
to take place. Within 2 weeks,
there is still a lot that needs to be
discussed
to make this complete deal come to
fruition. That is for me is very, very
important.
Hence why I'm still taking this and a
lot of the movement of what's happened
with a grain of salt. Still early days.
Still good signs. We're back above the
top of the range. You can see that here.
You can see it here. But I do still
think we still get a pullback. We're not
going instant bull mode right now and
everything is running straight to the
top of the range, right? I don't believe
that is happening. I don't believe we're
going straight to 80K. I think we're
going to take one step at a time. Again,
retest 69, take out 75, then give us the
80K pump, which is also lines up with
the trend line of this bear flag as
well.
You guys know from Monday, my deep
target, if everything was going to
happen, and it did happen last night, my
deep target was 52,000. I've been very,
very cool about that one. We're up to 73
viewers. Thank you very much, team. This
is huge. Again, again, if we crack 100,
we do another $100 USDT giveaway. So, if
you haven't done so already, make sure
you like. Make sure you smash in the
comments because I pulled all these
names for the giveaway from the live
comments section. So, if you haven't
done so already, make sure you whack a
comment in there because that is how you
get eligibility for the giveaway that I
will do at the end of this session. Just
wanted to give another quick shout-out
to that one. Now,
as we go through this, guys, I now want
to jump into a couple of altcoins cuz
there is a couple of altcoins that are
on my radar that are again bouncing off
those big critical levels that we have
been watching. I mean, Pepe last night
jumped about 13% off the back of the
news that is happening on Bitcoin. But I
typically do see ETH front running a lot
of the move, and I want to see if that
breakout that we're looking at on Monday
is now coming to fruition. So, we've got
to break that one down as well.
So, first one's first is I want to cover
Ethereum.
As you guys were aware on Friday, as I
was Oh, sorry, on Monday, as I was
talking about Ethereum, let me zoom in
on this one for you all to show you guys
how this played out since Monday. On
Monday, we were talking about the fact
of a potential breakout. And I said to
the guys, you know, we've already
oversold. We're already overpurchased,
sorry. We're already overpurchased.
We're already moving. And we're at the
top of the resistance. Whenever at top
of resistance and we're overpurchased, I
then get very cautious of the potential
breakout. And essentially, I want to
wait for price to come back, reload the
rocket, essentially, and for the
momentum to then reset. That is exactly
what happened.
Exactly to a T, I walked every single
person on the stream through that exact
play.
No word of a lie, you can go back and
you can watch it. This is why
understanding the flow of these charts
is very, very important. I also went
through this on my live call with Empire
and posted it in our community as well.
I posted the chat and the chart in
there, and we had a chat about this as
it was playing out. So, again, guys,
there's a link in the bio if you guys
want to check that out. There's 14 days
free from there from the Coin Bureau
team as well. And there's also a bunch
of other links if you're looking for
exchanges that you want to trade on as
well. The any money we make for those
exchanges goes towards the giveaways
anyway. So, feel free to jump on and
check those out.
But,
you can see here
on Ethereum at the moment, this is what
I'm watching. This is the exact play
that I went through on Monday. Is we
come back, we reset the momentum. You
can see that here. We get the breakout,
which has happened.
Now, I want the confirmation of the
retest. So, then I can run this entire
move. All right? So, you can see here on
the daily time frame right now, we've
already had the breakout on the 4-hour
time frame, which was the first big
piece of the puzzle.
But the 4-hour time frame isn't going to
give me the big definitive answer. I
want to wait I want to see this now. If
you didn't get the breakout off this
level, which you missed, if you missed
out on Monday's call, you may have
missed this one, right? But if you
didn't get the breakout off this point,
I'm not going to FOMO in here 250 200
$2,256, sorry. I want to wait for price
to come back.
I'm going to set an alert here at 2,157,
wait for that target to hit,
and then I'll show you this.
I want to look for this as the next
trade opportunity.
Okay? It's an 8 and 1/2% move.
It gives me a stop loss of about 2.42%.
It gives me a risk to reward ratio of
about 3 and 1/2, which to me is a solid
trade.
All right? You've got the EMAs that are
starting to cross bullish, which means
the average price of Ethereum is also
going up as well, which is another good
early sign. You're starting to get the
flips on momentum indicators as well,
and I want to catch the bull pullback
after what has been a reactionary move
across the board.
Does that make sense for everyone? If
you haven't done so already,
please let me know in the comments.
Hopefully this is helping you guys.
Again, what I've been watching on
Ethereum this entire time is this
ascended triangle essentially, which is
starting to form. We had the fake
breakout, which is standard, and now
we're sitting at where we are currently,
and I want to get the retest. Now, I'm
going to take a snapshot of this.
I'm going to take a photo. You can see
that here. I'm going to post it on the
side Empire. I'll post it on my X as
well for everyone that's following. And
if you haven't done so already, make
sure you follow me on X and Instagram.
You can see the links below in the bio,
because that is where I will be posting
the winners of the wheel at the end of
the day as well. So,
jumping on to what else I want to have a
look at is I wanted to have a look as
well at USDT dominance. The reason I
want to have a look at USDT dominance is
for the fact of the matter is we have a
very early days of breaking towards the
bottom of this support zone, right? Now,
this is quite a large range, and you
guys can see this. USDT dominance I've
always been a big one that follows this
because it's a direct correlation of
Bitcoin. I eat Bitcoin goes up, this
goes down.
This goes up, Bitcoin comes down along
with it. Now,
>> [clears throat]
>> as you can see here,
this can now potentially be also
supporting the fact of what we see
potentially happening on Bitcoin, I eat
the pullback.
I want to zoom into this section here.
You guys have seen the whole scenario
here. I want to show you guys a specific
area and really just focus on this
point.
As it stands at the moment,
you can see that we've actually started
to put in bullish divergence. So, if you
guys aren't aware of what bullish
divergence is, it is one of my most
fun, best, biggest indicators that I
look for in crypto and in financial
markets in general, right?
At [clears throat] the moment, you can
see this is bullish divergence. The
reason this is bullish divergence,
>> [cough and clears throat]
>> sorry guys, I'm still a bit sick.
But the fact of the matter is you can
see here we're putting in a higher low
off the basis of what was a lower low,
whereas price in this point, USDT
dominance, is putting in a lower low and
then another low. So, what this is
actually telling me
in the current scheme of things
is the fact that
buying sorry, selling pressure or
conversions to USDT at this current
point are actually starting to slow
down.
Sorry, actually starting to increase.
Sorry, got a bit of a switch there.
Because yes, we had a major conversion
here where USDT was then converted into,
you know, altcoins and Bitcoin and so
forth. But as it stands at the moment,
it's much lower in comparison to what
happened historically. So, in theory,
what I expect to happen
at this current point, just to make you
guys fully aware, you can see the big
order zone, the big fat order zone here,
$3 trillion essentially, 3 trillion
transactions,
right? Is last time off this level,
we had a nice big rally, nice big push.
Now, we've had some really good positive
market news, so I don't expect us to do
this one big green candle back to the
top of the range and wipe out all the
gains on Bitcoin.
It's not my expectation.
My expectation in this current scheme of
things and how way I've seen this play
out time and time and time again. Again,
this comes with experience, comes with
learning, comes with understanding how
to read to the charts is
as you start to get the 50
and the 200 EMA come down, eventually
they'll cross, which will cause what's
called a death cross.
Okay? What typically happens from that
point is you typically get
candles coming up to react to that
cross, that death cross that occurs in
the EMAs, and as well come back and
retest. You can see here the break of
structure.
So, in theory,
if this is the pull up
roughly 2%, let's just round off to 2%
to come and retest this range,
the EMAs come down alongside with it,
where does that position Bitcoin?
Let's go back to Bitcoin for a moment.
Make sure you're following along, we've
got a lot to cover. Told you guys had to
dive deep into this cuz it is critically
important. I hate seeing people get
caught out.
If we see a 2% drop on Bitcoin,
where does that lead us to?
>> [clears throat and cough]
>> Roughly back
and we can drag it up slightly back to
the other break of structure there,
roughly back to 70,000, but I would
almost guarantee in my eyes, can't
guarantee anything for obvious reasons.
There's no financial advice here.
Nothing's a guarantee in this
environment and in this this world of
cryptocurrency, of course.
But
my expectation is a drop back down to
$69,600,
which very much lines up with the fact
of what we are seeing on the USDT
dominance chart as well, which will see
this pullback up also. And then if that
is the case,
then happy days, because you know why?
That basically just confirms the fact
that market structure is now in a
downtrend for USDT dominance and will
help push us to that $80,000 Bitcoin
once again.
So again, guys, you've got to go through
and put the whole story together so you
don't get caught up in the BS that is
happening, all the headlines and all the
news, etc., etc., etc. Think about it
from a methodical standpoint. As someone
wrote in the comments section
on my last video, we're looking at here
and playing 4D chess. All retail traders
are playing 2D,
right? We're interpreting what we think
is going to happen
versus reacting to the news headlines.
We want to be ahead of the curve. We
want to be understanding where this is
at.
So, let's dive now into some altcoins.
That is what I want to cover for you
all, because I think we're going to have
some plays on the altcoins, but it's
about getting the right entry positions,
and that's what I want to set some
alerts for right now.
And then we're going to go through the
wheel and do the giveaways. So, guys,
before we jump into that, do appreciate
you all on here. Again, for you guys to
be eligible for the next giveaway, and
if we hit 15 more concurrent viewers at
this current point, we will be eligible
for another 100 USDT giveaway. So, if
you haven't done so already, share this
with your mates, share it with your
friends, get 15 more people in here,
smash them comments in there. All you
need to do is place one comment in the
comment section, and you're eligible for
the giveaway as well. I love giving away
cash, it's always fun. And if I can give
someone 100 USDT or 50 USDT, whatever it
is, and you guys can turn that into a
few hundred bucks, that's even better.
And it's a basically a few dinners paid
for me, paid for you guys on me.
Now, big one I wanted to show you guys
is Solana.
As you guys saw
on
Monday, I was talking about Solana,
and I spoke about the fact that where
price is currently, which was up around
here,
I expected price to come back and at
least retest the bottom of the zone, but
we also needed to come back and retest
this trend line. So, we drew this trend
We drew this trend line on Monday.
As an FYI for everyone, if you weren't
there on Monday, we drew this trend line
on Monday.
No word of a lie. I can't lie because
it's recorded.
And as I said, I expect price to come
back towards this trend line, and you
can see that is where we currently are
at, right this right at this point. But
the big thing what you're looking at on
Solana at the moment is the fact of the
matter is we've got an order zone that
presented itself here.
We've now got another order zone created
itself here. You can see the large
liquidity grab, that candlestick
highlighted in yellow, right?
Now, you go over to this next section.
As it stands at the moment,
price has also reacted off the same
order zone and is actually now holding
below the trend line.
So, if I'm thinking Bitcoin is going to
drop, I'm thinking the US 500 is already
moving alongside with it.
But I think USDT dominance is going to
throw a left up. Well,
I'm not going to FOMO
and try and buy the breakout,
right? I don't want to buy the breakout.
As I said on Monday, I'm not buying into
resistance for longs. Buying into
resistance just ends up in a bad
situation. It's where a lot of people
get caught buying the top, selling the
bottom, then they call crypto a scam,
and they got absolutely destroyed
because they've tried to send it on 50X
outside the resistance zone.
If you've been there, back in the
comments, cuz I can guarantee a few of
us have been there, especially in the
early days trading, they're like, "It's
going, it's going, it's going." Boom,
50x straight into resistance.
But, the way I'm looking at this at the
current point, guys, is
right now, if I've seen this full push,
where do I think it's going to pull back
towards? I'm going to show you guys how
I measure this. It's quite simple.
Fibonacci from the bottom
to the top of the range.
Now, if I'm a betting man,
which sometimes I am, I look at where is
the next best Fibonacci ratio that lines
up with the next clean level of support
and resistance, as well as EMAs, and
where I think price will essentially
line up with.
In this scenario,
the 50 EMA is definitely on my cards.
So, what I'm going to be doing is I'm
going to set an alert here at $82.80.
If I look back at that,
you guys have seen I did not even look
at anything on the left, but look at
this.
Price reacts off this level.
Price reacts off this level. Price
reacts off this level. Price reacts off
this level. Keep going.
Price reacts off this level. Price
reacts off this level. Candles get
closed below this level, and then you
end up getting demolished.
So,
in this current situation, we do not
want price to close below the 50 EMA or
$82.80 because then it opens up
essentially for a drop back down towards
$78.
So,
in theory, my play is essentially this,
retest this,
then give us the move off there, and
I'll happily take an order if all
conditions are set right for something
along the lines of this.
All right. A long tool.
Everything plays out according to play,
I'll put a stop loss below here,
and you can see back to the top of the
order zone is a 5% move. Might not seem
like much, but it's a 3.3 risk reward
ratio. Again, I only need to win
essentially four trades out of 10 to
stay profitable. And if this then breaks
out completely,
it opens up this massive gap, which
gives me a close to an eight risk reward
ratio trade.
Again,
we [clears throat] ain't here
trading like retail traders.
I'm not here playing hopium games.
I'm taking this from a methodical
standpoint and thinking about the theory
behind how I think this will play out.
If this does not play out, then so be
it. I've missed one trade.
Big [ __ ] There is so many trades on a
day-to-day basis that you can trade
that are currently available. All right?
So, someone has put up in the comments,
"Can you have a look at LINK?" LINK was
on my radar, so I'm going to go through
that as well, team. Again, I can't
believe there isn't that many comments.
I'm giving away cash, and you guys
aren't even eligible. There's 80
viewers, and we haven't even got 80
comments. So,
the credit goes to you guys. Whoever's
in the comment section, and if we hit
100, you guys are going to be the ones
that are eligible, that are going to be
at a good ratio to win something. You
can see it here. Last time we had over
113 people in the stream, 116 people,
and only this many, I don't know how
many exactly it is. Let's say say 20 or
so,
in for the giveaway. So,
I'll leave it up to you guys. You want
to be in, whack it in the comments,
smash the likes, share the stream out,
and we'll get this thing pumping. Now, I
want to show you guys LINK. So, let me
jump over to LINK.
LINK, very similar scenario. As you guys
know, I've been monitoring LINK from the
weekly bottom here. All right? That was
off $8.43
to be exact, which is the bottom of
where LINK historically broke out in
2022.
As it stands at the moment, the range on
LINK between this level that I've been
monitoring is about 20%.
All right? Now, as it stands in the
current scheme of things, let me drop
this into the 4-hour for you guys
because this is where LINK is
essentially trading sideways.
And you can see here, very similar to
what we've had on Solana. We've now got
bearish divergence in effect here,
right? And we're pumping straight into
an order zone. Now,
me being a trader,
I personally don't like trading middle
of the ranges. And what I mean by that,
if I look at this to show you all, to
make it very simple,
right?
Right now, you're dead center in the
middle of the range.
So, from an opportunity standpoint, if I
was to place a trade,
if I place, let's say hypothetically, a
long position
right here,
I'm instantly into resistance, which is
the big fat order zone. If you guys
don't have this on there, I I do have it
available on my platform. This
indicator, again, it is a paid
indicator. It's not my one personally.
It's It is off a third party, but I do
have a strategy and things built around
this. But, if you look at this, right?
You're basically stuck.
I don't see this as a valid trade right
now
because I'm running into resistance for
a long, and from a short, it'll probably
get picked up around this $9 level. So,
for LINK at the moment, I think there's
better opportunities out there on other
tokens.
Um I'd rather let this one play out, see
where it lands on the daily time frame,
see if we can at least get a retest of
what I typically see happen, and I'll
show you guys here.
You can see the breakout point. But,
typically, you get a retest of at least
the bottom of the order zone where it's
broken out from. So, in theory,
if I draw this out, so you guys can see
this,
I'd be expecting at least price to come
back towards the $9 mark. So, I'm going
to set an alert here at $9.02,
right? And let's just have a look at
something here. I want to see what that
lines up with from a Fibonacci ratio
because that's always the big kicker. I
want to see this one first.
Sets off the 1.27.
But, if I look at this
from an overall movement standpoint,
>> [clears throat and cough]
>> like clockwork, it's also the 50
Fibonacci level as well. So,
I'm going to set my alert there. You can
see $8.99 and 902, it's already set. And
I'll wait to see if this plays out as we
expect, and I'll monitor this one as
well. I'll place this chart again within
the community.
Um
And I'll also place it on my X. If you
guys aren't following along already,
make sure you're doing so as well. And
I'll take a snapshot of this. I never
want to be someone that's FOMOing in
charts. I never want to be FOMOing
taking trades.
Um I'm just checking the comments now,
guys. Want to see if you guys have any
specific question. If you've got a
specific question, whack it in there
now, and then I'm going to run the
wheel.
Always love your TA. No, I appreciate
it, guys. Thank you very much. We try
and keep things very, very structured.
HYPE, I'll show you guys HYPE. I've
already got that done.
Um I'll show you guys Zcash as well
because Zcash I had the levels marked
out, and that has also bounced as well.
So, showing you guys first ones first,
HYPE, let me see. I've got it here
somewhere.
Where is it? Where is it? Where is it?
Here we go.
So,
as I was saying to you guys, we like to
play 4D chess.
I've had this marked out for the last
week and a half, 2 weeks. Um you guys
can go back, have a look at the call. Um
have a look at the stream. I have been
documenting this one, and I've been
posting updates again within my Empire
community. You guys can get 14 days
free. The link's in the comments,
compliments of Coin Bureau, of course.
Um
you can see here, right? Breakout of the
long-term downtrend. Each Fibonacci
level has then acted as a staircase to
heaven. We first marked this out at
around $28 was the first point. We get
the breakout. We get the retest. The
next attempted breakout will be at this
point at around $41. You need to get
back above this order zone, or else it's
going to continue to act as a level of
resistance.
Then, look for the retest, and my target
has been $47 for this for quite some
time, and the extended target for this
is around the $60 mark. So, very easy.
Very Don't really much more needed to be
done with HYPE. Everything's been marked
out, and it's been playing along as it
should. So, it's been doing quite well,
to be completely fair.
And Zcash, I do have Zcash here. Let me
just find it.
There we are.
>> [clears throat]
>> Z E C, so
this is a fun one.
When people were buying here, I was
like, "You've got to be nuts." You think
I saw posts about this thing going like
$10,000, just ridiculous stuff, right?
But,
I was always very much confident that
we'd get a pull back to around 235 buck
mark.
Um the reason for that is quite simple,
right? If you look to the left of this
chart, this is the breakout zone and the
resistance point, which was never really
properly retested. So, this has had a
real large-scale breakout now. I'll zoom
into this in a moment.
Um I'll remove a bit of this as well,
just so we can clean it up, so you guys
can see it. But, as it stands at the
moment, I wanted to sort of I want to
run my fibs. I want to see how this is
sort of playing out right now. Give me
one moment. I want to see how this move.
What it's bounced off as current scheme
of things.
I think we still get a little bit of
adjustment on this. Let me just zoom out
on this one.
Play around with that with a little bit
more detail. There we go.
Tidy this up.
We'll look at the fib levels here.
Measure these out.
If I just a bit of a breakdown just
below the 707 level, and now we're
getting the pump out of this range as
well. So, if I'm looking at this on
Zcash,
right?
Am I going to go in and FOMO buy
the top of the range that's currently
in play?
Probably not. I don't want to buy the
middle of the range here. Why? Because
again, this thing moves fast, it moves
volatile. It swings crazy.
But, I'm looking at this.
Nice double bottom. You get the
breakout.
I then look for the retest. So, what I'm
going to do in this scenario, I'm going
to set a little back here around $302.
And I'm just going to wait for Zcash to
come back towards that point. I'm not I
don't own any Zcash or anything like
that, guys. Just as an FYI, I don't own
crypto bags in general. I like to trade
them. I'll heavily trade the [ __ ] out of
them, to be completely honest. Um but
I'm not really big on bag holding. I
like to just trade things get in, get
out, make money. So, that's completely
over purchased at the moment. Um
So, it would not surprise me if we see a
pullback on this one very soon as well.
But I'll take a snapshot of this. Um
I'll take a little screen grab of that.
Also, just to make a mention keep our
eyes on this one as well. Now, we're
come to the point in the stream
that I appreciate every single one of
you guys jumping on.
We're going to do the giveaway.
So, this is your last chance to try and
get this next stream out to 100 people.
If not, we're going to have to wait till
Monday. But,
we have the spinning wheel here, team.
So, we're giving away 250 USDT giveaway.
So, if you see
your
um your username here,
like it in the comments. I want to know
that you're still watching because if
you're on here live, it'll be even more
fun. Um this part's exciting. And team,
if you haven't done so already, please
like me on socials. I do post the
winners up there. I do post all my
updates. I have got you guys some really
good giveaways as well. You can see in
the description of the video. There's 14
days free for our Empire community,
which has been complimented Coin Bureau.
Plus, off the back, there is some links
to some exchanges that will do some
really good promo offers for you. I
think there's one with ToolBit at the
moment about There's another
one with Bitget and so forth. But just
make sure those exchanges work for you
and within your region.
Again, shout out to those guys for the
for supporting the channel. But, let's
do the giveaway. This not refresh. This
list is from Monday.
Team, this is what I'm saying. This list
is from Monday.
So, what I'll do is, right?
I'll make a deal with you all.
Everyone that's on this channel, I'll
make a deal with you all.
If you weren't here on Monday, what I'm
going to do is I'm going to give you
guys the last opportunity
to get put on the wheel for the today's
one, for today's session on Wednesday.
All right? This is the deal.
Typically, we have to hit 100 viewers to
be eligible and to get the giveaway
going. All right? What I will do
is I will do another 100 USDT giveaway
next week.
Okay?
But this is the criteria.
And the onus is on you guys for this
one. A, you have to comment
right now. You have to drop a comment.
So, there's 70 people on here. There
should be at least 70 usernames that get
pumped into this.
And I'll make it very easy for you guys.
My last video on Coin Bureau
on
Monday has gone over 2,000 views.
If you guys can get this video to 3,000
views, which is only a thousand more,
which isn't dramatic, it's not hard.
That means you guys have to share it on
socials, pump it out there, etc. I will
do another 100 USDT giveaway. And
everyone that is in the comments section
right now and everyone that watches this
stream back on the recording and is in
the comments section and post comments
on the recording, on the main video, I
will also include you guys to make it
widespread and give everyone ample
opportunity. All right? And we'll do 250
USDT giveaway. So, it's all up to you
guys. I want to be fair. You know I'm
friendly. I love what I do. I love
giving back to you guys. And we're
starting to pump some good numbers. So,
rewards are out there, especially for
everyone. We can see me and Nick
spinning here in the wheel. So, guys,
I'm going to send this now. Let's click
it to spin. Good luck to everyone.
Fingers crossed.
First one off the rank. Here we go.
It is
C C Andra. C Andra [laughter] 828. So,
congratulations. I'm going to just grab
that one.
I'm going to just put it down here on um
my other screen so it doesn't get lost.
Give me 1 second. I'm just going to
whack that in here.
So, it doesn't get lost. And now, we're
going to pump one more. So,
congratulations. Here we go. We'll
remove that one cuz you can't get double
wins. That's not fair.
Good luck to everyone. Fingers crossed.
Let's go. Let's go.
Oh.
Black Cat Z 014. Congratulations. That's
another win.
So, guys, congrats to everyone that did
win. That's 50 USDT. What you need to do
is you need to send me a message on
Instagram.
Send me a recording so I can see that
you are actually the owner of this
username on your YouTube channel, right?
It's not hard. Screenshot, video. Very
easy. Send it to me. Send me a wallet
address. And bang, I'll pump 50 USDT
straight into there within a matter of
seconds. So,
team, thank you for jumping on. We've
smashed out 47 minutes. It's been an
awesome stream for you all. Thank you
very much. Have a fantastic week. I'm
going to keep dropping um charts on my
socials and in the Empire community. And
thank you very much to the Coin Bureau
team. This has been an awesome stream.
And thank you very much Thank you very
much to every single one of you. Have a
fantastic weekend. And good luck in this
crazy market. I absolutely love it. See
you guys. Bye.