AI has made coding a lot worse. Just fix
it loop. Now, I'm sure you guys have
been in this and this again is
self-inflicted. It's easy to say, "Oh,
yeah. Just don't do that. Go manually
fix the code yourself." But what I'm
talking about here is when the AI makes
a mistake, you tell it to fix the
mistake. It doesn't fix it. And you just
keep going back and forth. Starts at 10
minutes and then 20 and then 30 and then
hour, then 2 hours where you're just
trying to fix bugs all day. And your
prompts are literally just fix this.
Here's the error message. Here's what
went wrong. Let's try this solution.
Let's fix this. Where if you had just
coded it correctly the first time, which
maybe took you 10 minutes of manual
work, you never would have been in this
situation.