AI has made coding a lot worse. Now
look, everybody talks about technical
debt, but AI introduces this new kind of
debt where you have thousands of lines,
maybe hundreds thousands of files that
nobody on your team truly really
understands. Now, I created a fully AI
coded app, three of us coding this app,
and we were all just like in cursor and
Claude code whipping up all this stuff,
and we got something out really quickly,
and it was cool, and it was working. But
then we actually got to a point where
we're like, "Okay, maybe we're going to
sell this. Okay, maybe we're going to
release it to more users." And when we
started going through and actually
trying to do some real on this, none of
us had any clue how this thing was
actually built. Like we knew the general
stack and some of the languages, but
like the whole architecture was just
blind. We just had all of this massive
amount of like AI unknown debt, where we
didn't even know how bad it was. And
what we ended up doing was literally
just refactoring and rebuilding the
entire thing.