Perplexity just released their new
computer feature, and honestly, this is
the best AI tool that I've used in 2026
this far. Now, in this video, I want to
break down what it is, explain how it
compares to something like OpenClaw, and
why I'm personally switching to it right
now for certain tasks compared to
OpenClaw. Let's get into it. Okay, so
you can see the computer is running on
my machine right now. All I did is just
go to the website and then I just gave
it a prompt. Now, the important thing
here is that this computer from
Perplexity can effectively do everything
that Open Caw can do, except it doesn't
require any configuration on your end.
You just make sure you have the Max
plan, which yes, is $200 per month, but
I do believe that they're bringing it to
the pro plan soon, and you can start
using it. It has skills, it can go to
the web, it can write code, it can do
all of the things that you would want an
AI agent to do, except you don't have to
manually configure it or worry about the
security. So, I'll go through a bunch of
demos here so you can see what this is
capable of. But I really do want to
explain what it is and how it compares
to OpenClaw because I know a lot of you
watching this channel have watched my
OpenClaw videos and you've seen that
even me as an experienced developer can
take hours to configure the instance
properly. And while it's super powerful,
it's definitely not beginnerfriendly and
it eats a massive amount of time and can
also be configured incorrectly and lead
to a bunch of security issues. So, this
effectively fixes all of that, but there
are some pros and cons. Let's get into
it. Okay, so there's kind of two
approaches that I want to talk about in
this video. First is OpenClaw. Second is
the Perplexity computer. Now, you can
see that with OpenClaw, you effectively
have full local control, which means you
configure everything. You set it up
exactly how you want, and it makes it
extremely powerful because you can
effectively do anything, right? It's
infinitely configurable. That also means
you own everything and you own the
complexity and the responsibility of
setting up an instance like that.
Whereas with Perplexity computer, it's
cloudnative, so it just runs on
Perplexity's infrastructure. There is
actually zero setup. You literally just
sign up, you pay the 200 bucks per
month, and then you can start using it.
And then it has model agnostic
orchestration, which means that it
automatically routes to different models
based on what needs to be used. You
don't pay for API keys. You just pay for
credits for the computer. And this means
that you don't need to fine-tune your
cost, where I know some people are
literally spending $200 per day using
OpenCloud, right? And then in general,
you just describe what you want and you
get the result. You might need to
connect your Google Drive or something,
but that's about it. And just to give
you kind of an analogy here, the
computer is like hiring a general
contractor. You just describe what you
want the finished product to be, in this
case, the kitchen, and then they pick
the plumber, the electrician, you know,
the tile guy, whatever, and spin up a
bunch of sub aents to accomplish the
task without you really needing to do
anything. So, let's talk about what the
computer actually is. Now, if you
remember Perplexity a few years ago,
they were really just doing search with
AI. They then released the Comet
browser, the Comet Assistant, and now
they have the computer feature, which is
really the most capable one that they've
had to date. Now, effectively what this
allows you to do is have model agnostic
orchestration, like I said, parallel sub
aents just like you would have inside of
something like claw code if you were
triggering them yourself. Self-healing
problem solving, and then an isolated
compute environment, which I think is
the important part here, where when you
use this computer, it's essentially
using a virtual private server that's
already configured where you can't
configure it incorrectly because you
don't have the ability to configure it
and Perplexity has set it up for you.
Now, the model orchestration is super
interesting because that means that
you're able to access all of the
Frontier models and even the new ones
when they come out without you having to
actually select them and set all of them
up. So, if you want to use Grock, if you
want to use Gemini, in fact, you don't
even have to pick. It will just
automatically route it to all of the
different models based on what the task
requires rather than you having to
configure that yourself. And you may
have seen that recently I had an hourong
video explaining to you how to configure
this to save money. In this case, it's
already done. So, what I want to do now
is show you exactly how this works so
you can see what I mean. And by the way,
this presentation that I'm going through
here was actually generated with
Perplexity Computer. And the entire
script that you're hearing was also
generated with Perplexity Computer.
Anyways, let me go over and show you
what's possible. All right, so I'm in
the app now and I do want to remind you
that in order to use this feature, you
do need the Max plan. And I believe it's
going to be available for the enterprise
plans if it's not already as well as the
Pro plans later. But for now, you do
need that $200 per month subscription,
which will give you 10,000 credits by
default for the computer. And then I
believe that you can get some bonus
credits when you sign up. In my case, I
was able to actually partner with
Perplexity for this video, and they gave
me a bunch of additional credits. So, I
haven't had any issues running into
limits. And to be honest, it hasn't used
as many credits as I would have expected
it to. Regardless, I'm going to start
running you through a few demos. So,
what I'm going to do is just switch over
to the computer tab here where you can
see a bunch of different tasks. I had
another account where I was messing
around with this. I just made a fresh
one for this video. And what I'm going
to do is just give it a prompt and let's
see what it does. Okay. So, I'm just
going to go here. I'm going to paste in
a prompt where I'm asking this to
research the top five AI agent tools
right now. So, OpenClaw, man, Claude,
Co-work, Perplex, the etc. And then give
me one of your choice. Give me the
pricing, positioning, key strengths,
weaknesses. And then I wanted to put it
into an interactive report as a web
application. So, we could actually send
this to, for example, like an executive
team. So let's go ahead and press enter
here and see the result that we get. All
right, so this is the resulting web page
that it created. You can see it gave us
a bunch of information. It created a
full comparison report and we can
actually see all of the files that were
generated up here in this kind of little
window here as well as the usage of the
computer during this particular task and
how long it worked for. In this case, it
was 8 minutes 25 seconds. And if we
scroll down, let's have a look at this
by just making it full screen. Okay, so
you can see this is actually deployed to
like a full website, I guess. Uh and
from here let's start scrolling through
and see what we got. So we get a
comparison for developers, knowledge
workers, power users, makes sense.
Engineering teams, all okay head-to-head
analysis where we can kind of click
through and you know toggle these
various things and see this cool kind of
like skill graph of what each is good
at. Overall pricing breakdown in terms
of how much it costs uh and kind of nice
tables. And overall this is quite good.
I mean, I'm pretty impressed that's able
to whip this up in literally 8 minutes
without me having to do anything. And
it's even given me this kind of light
and dark mode, uh, which I didn't even
ask for. Now, just to draw a comparison
here to Open Claw, obviously, I could do
this as well with OpenClaw and create a
website like this. But when I've done
that in the past, it requires, first of
all, that I'm going to set up all of the
different routing for the models. So, we
could use like Gemini for research, you
know, Opus for planning, all of that
kind of stuff. It also requires that I
have everything preconfigured and that I
have a coding task, I have a git task, I
have or sorry skill, I have all these
other skills already added. And then in
terms of actually running and viewing
the site, it's a lot more difficult to
have open claw automatically deploy this
and put in a format where I could
actually instantly share it with someone
because if you uh configure the instance
properly, usually you're shutting down
all external traffic, meaning you can
only run it through something like tail
scale, right? or you're going to expose
a site publicly, which you probably
don't want to do directly on the virtual
private server that's hosting your
OpenClaw instance. So, at minimum, just
being able to have the site deployed
instantly so I can actually start using
it right away is a massive benefit. And
again, like I said, I can do this in
OpenClaw, but it's just going to take me
a lot longer to set up. And for any
beginners, I don't know if that's
actually even going to be possible for
you get a result like this unless you
really know what you're doing in terms
of the config, setup, deployment, all of
that kind of stuff. Okay, so I've got
another prompt here. research Nvidia,
Microsoft Anthropic, pull the latest
news, do the analyst sentiment, and then
give me any financial developments and
build a comprehensive dashboard that I
can actually use. Let's see what this
can do. All right, so we've got the
finished result here. Let's pop it open
and then we can go through and see how
it built this. All right, so we've got
AI Titans comparison dashboard. We have
Nvidia, Microsoft, and Enthropic and
their stock price. Okay, we can see kind
of a financial comparison here of the
latest reported quarter. We have
quarterly revenue trends showing us
Nvidia versus Microsoft. And then
Enthropic, it's giving us a trajectory
because this is a private company. So it
actually separated those two out where
we have the publicly traded ones, then
the privately traded. Keep going forward
estimates. Okay. Analyst sentiment,
bullcase, barecase. We can have a look
at this here and see. And then it gives
us the latest news from all of them. And
we can see Microsoft. Okay. Frontier
suite March 9th. GTC 2026. March 14th.
Pretty cool. All right. So again, single
prompt. I don't know why it always gives
us light and dark mode, but we've got
that here. And if we go back to the
task, let's have a look at some of the
things it actually did here because
again, I'm trying to make the comparison
of like if I was going to do this in
OpenClaw, what would be required to have
this work? So, first of all, you can see
we had four sub agents running in
parallel or three I guess where we're
loading the skills here. So, research
assistant, finance, markets, website
building, which are already made for us.
We also can add our own skills. In fact,
if I go here, like I don't have any
right now, but I can make my own skill
if I want. It actually has the create
skill skill and then you can view the
markdown file and actually just copy
this or use it how you want. Anyways,
we'll go back here. So point is it ran a
bunch of these tasks in parallel. It's
then going to start setting up the
research. So it's researching this,
doing the financial data collection, and
then we can see it's running all of
these in parallel, fetching the tool
details. Same thing, running all of
these in parallel, running the tasks in
parallel. You can see here this used
opus 4.6, so it's telling us the
specific model. And then again, it goes
and completes everything else. So if we
were just to look at all of the things
that were ran here, again, we can
emulate this in OpenClaw, but most
people are probably never going to get
to a point where their open claw is
configured with all of these things and
have it functioning properly. In this
case, I just used it and it worked right
away. And I think that's the massive
benefit of this tool is that if you just
want something done instantly right away
without any config, you open it up and
it works. If I was to try to build this
in OpenClaw, again, like I mentioned, I
would have to have some way of
previewing the site, which is not easy.
I'm probably sshing into the instance.
I'm going to have to set up all of the
model config. I'm going to have to be a
little bit more explicit in terms of
what I want it to do. I'm going to have
to configure all of the skills. And even
me, probably one of the top 1% users of
OpenClaw right now in terms of tokens is
going to spend, you know, 45 minutes, 60
minutes getting this site up. We're
here. Let's check. This ran in 12
minutes, right? And spun everything up.
And to be honest, it's probably cheaper
if I do the math on the token usage pro
rata than it would be if I just used,
you know, my own API key with Enthropic
or something from OpenClaw. Okay. Now,
the next thing that I want to run here,
and this is the one that I was thinking
about the most when I heard Perplexi
Computer coming out, is something that's
going to run on some kind of schedule or
respond to some kind of events. So, what
I like about OpenClaw is that because
it's so configurable, it can actually be
proactive. It can like send you a daily
report. It can run cron jobs. It can
react to like a message coming in or
something. Right? So, what I want to try
to do first of all is make it so that I
can message with this in Slack, which I
believe is possible. And then I want to
see, okay, if I'm not actually telling
it to do something directly, can it go
ahead and do that proactively based on
some instruction I gave it previously.
So, like send me a daily report or
something, analyze my business, you
know, complete something, right? And the
advantage of the computer is that it's
always on and just running in the
background. So unlike even open call if
you're running it on like a Mac mini or
something if the power goes out or you
turn your Mac mini off it just stops
working right it can also very easily
crash as I'm sure many of you have
probably seen even on a VPS okay yeah
it's always running as long as the VPS
is running kind of same thing here right
it's just always on in the background
which I think is a massive benefit so
let's try let's go back here to the
computer and let's give this like a
business automation task okay so the
next task I'm going to give it is to
monitor my inbox every morning summarize
what's important flag anything urgent,
draft responses for my approval, and
then format the whole briefing to look
like a clean notion dashboard. Run this
daily and just because I think it's
going to be funny, speak like Mario. And
let's see if it can do that. Now, by the
way, I did have a few connectors on
before I'm running this, so I just want
to show you for the connectors. I did
connect Google Drive, Gmail, and Slack.
And with Slack, it was actually very
simple. All I had to do was just
authenticate my Slack and add the bot.
And now if I go here, I was just testing
this earlier. You can see that I have
computer and I can actually just tell it
to do something directly from Slack. So
if we take that same prompt, I can just
put it here. I'm going to say speak like
Mario. And I'm just going to send it to
the computer from Slack. And you can see
now the computer is working, replying to
my message. And hopefully that will be
done in a second. And then we can see it
give us kind of these daily briefs by
reading through my email. Okay, so it
just gave me a reply here. It says our
daily Mario inbox briefing is set up and
ready to go. Here's what's going to
happen at 9:00 a.m. Bangkok time. So, I
guess I just decided that is going to be
the time. Says the first briefing drops
tomorrow, Monday, March 16th. If you
want to test it right now, just the
timer, tell Mario to take a day off,
just let me know. Okay, so I'm just
going to say test it now and let's see
what it's going to give me here. Um, and
if it's able to actually go to the
inbox, pull the emails, etc. And
interestingly, here you can actually see
what was sent from Slack. You can see I
just said test it now right inside of
the interface for Perplexity. So you can
see it says like let me run the briefing
now as a test and it's running Sonnet
4.6 and generating it. So if you want to
see what it's doing, you can still see
that directly in the UI as opposed to
obviously in Slack here where it's just
going to give me the response. All
right, so it just sent me the DM. Notice
it actually sent it to myself. So it's
like me sending it to myself which is
kind of weird, but anyways that's how I
got it. And you can see it's a me your
morning briefing. Okay, Sunday. So, it's
talking like Mario. Obviously, I'm going
to have to blur a few things out here
because it is my actual real email that
I got this to go to. And obviously, we
need to blur out some of the names and
the details, but you can see it's giving
us some urgent stuff on like new
sponsorship deals or opportunities on my
inbox. 51 new emails, okay, sponsorship
and coins, going over like different
deals, whatever that we've been signing,
uh videos being live, all of this kind
of stuff, collaboration and crew. Now
again, most of this I'm going to blur
because I can't um you know show it all
to you, but looks like it is working and
it is pretty accurate. And if we go
here, it's also giving us another uh
kind of what is it message here with
replies that we could send to people. So
let me read one of them here like sorry
for the slow reply. I watched the trial
edit. Really appreciate the effort. Blah
blah blah. Hey Abby, thanks for the
note, etc., etc., etc. You get the idea.
Uh and we have all of that here. Cool.
All right. All right, so it works inside
of Slack giving me the daily briefing
and hopefully it will trigger again at
9:00 a.m. tomorrow because that's
actually going to be pretty useful and I
will just leave that on. All right, so
at this point guys, let me talk about
who this is actually for and when I
would use this over using OpenClaw
because the truth is I'm not just
completely ditching OpenClaw. I've been
using it since it came out. I have a
bunch of instances configured. They work
extremely well and while they were very
timeconuming to get up and running
because of how flexible it is, it's open
source. It is really up to you to
configure it and make it better. You can
do a lot more with it in my opinion than
you can with something purely like this
because of that infinite customization.
So I think for those of you that are,
you know, the top 5% of Open Claw users,
you're probably not getting rid of that
tomorrow and switching over to a tool
like this. You're probably going to keep
using that because you're okay with the
complexity, the setup, and you're you're
confident in what you're doing like I
am, right? However, what I have noticed
is that when you just want to do
something, when you have like a task
that you want to get done quickly,
that's not something that's like a
repeatable workflow in your business,
this works a lot better. So, building a
quick dashboard, spinning up, you know,
a quick, you know, research report,
whatever. In my experience, I get better
results from Perplexity Computer than I
do from my open claw because my open
claw is not designed to do that. But for
like analyzing sales calls data or doing
an automation or operation that I do all
the time in my business, OpenClaw works
better for that because I've set it up
specifically to do that. So the agent is
designed just for that and it's not like
a general purpose agent like we have
here. So that's kind of my take for all
my business automation stuff. You know,
repeatable tasks, things that I'm going
to do over and over and over again. I'm
going to stick with Open Claw because I
know I can configure it properly and the
time is worth it to have that just
running exactly as I want with all of
the config that I'm responsible for.
Whereas with this, if I just want to get
something done quickly, I want a
relatively complex task that I need an
agent for and I need computer use, I'm
going to go to Perplexity Computer. And
I think for those of you watching, you
have to ask yourself the question, do I
want to deal with the complexity? Do I
want to deal with the security concerns?
Am I confident setting this up uh on my
own with OpenClaw? If so, go ahead and
you have the advantage of the open
source software and also the cost is in
your control. Whereas this, it is $200
per month. If you're barely using AI, if
you need a few tasks, this probably
doesn't make sense. And having a quick
open cloth spun up on a $10 per month
VPS where you spend $5 in tokens, maybe
that's worth it for you over something
like this. So, really, you guys have to
use your own judgment. In my case, like
I said, I'm going to keep using Open
Claw. I'm going to use this more for
those one-off tasks and things that just
don't require as much configuration. And
I'm really interested to hear what you
guys think about this because genuinely,
yes, I know they reached out to Partner,
but this is a very cool tool. It works
better than I was expecting and I'm just
going to be using it a lot now because
of how effective it is. Anyways guys,
that's my take. Let me know what you
think about it in the comments down
below. I'm genuinely curious to hear
your opinion and I look forward to
seeing you in another video.