And from there we can look towards some
of those
larger areas that I've been pointing
out, right? We have that really bullish
big bullish shark that's still very
valid here as long as we are remaining
above this $60,000.
This is something that's taken a long
time to print. It's not going to get
here in a hurry, right? Usually it takes
a lot of time here as well. We got the
nice little base basically accruing down
here. And I would imagine if we're going
to make our way up towards that big
target one, it's probably going to be
middle of the year here. So, still you
know, several weeks, maybe even a few
months here out before we get really
going.
More than likely if we do break to the
upside this region, obviously it's
probably going to be met with some
haste, right? Because again, what comes
down fast if we get back into those
regions, we usually come back up fast.
So,
still pretty much just waiting to see
how this unfolds here. If you're going
to look for two lines in the sand
essentially, pretty simple where we are
now, right? Or basically we don't want
to lose our $60,000 low for any more
unless you do want to go short and
continue lower.
And as far as any more upside, need to
get above 75,000.
Especially on a daily closing basis,
right? On the last time we came up we
could just see we wicked above that. How
we had this high right here in place,
right? And essentially we just kind of
wicked up around these highs and came
back down. We don't want to see that.