Welcome back to Data Dash everybody. My
name is Paul Sampson and today is
Tuesday, April 7th, 2026. We've got some
really big tensions going on out there.
Everybody's well aware of it. I'm not
going to go over it any more than we
have to here. I want to start off in our
video today with thanking today's
sponsor, which is going to be Bit Unix,
which is our exclusive exchange partner
here at Data Dash. If you're interested
in trading whether it's short-term or
looking for any kind of areas to pick up
your next spot buys, be sure to check
out the Bit Unix link down in our
description area. Again, they're our
exclusive partner here. Thank you guys
at Bit Unix for all the support. Now, I
wanted to come on and cover a few things
here really quickly. A nice brief update
for you folks. And basically, what we're
having here is one of the biggest setups
that I see time and time again. And
realistically, when we have something
that is so
set in stone like what is going on
tonight. Right again, we have certain
timelines. There's a date on the
calendar.
When we get the chance to see that type
of stuff. Now, I'm pulling this you
know, politics and everything aside,
just looking at the technicals and
fundamentals to completely separate
here.
Very similar to an FOMC meeting, right?
When we have a really big rate cut
decision and it's coming down the
pipeline and you see everybody really
focused in on it. We we get the
opportunity to know when that volatility
might come.
We we tend to see the opposite occur,
okay?
And right now many many many are really
in in anticipating for the markets to to
collapse, to crash on the back of some
negative news here, right? Depending on
how things kind of you know
go forward here.
I guess at the end of this deadline
that's coming in a few hours from the
time of this video. And I really want to
point out here that again, we're at a
place where Bitcoin
specifically, I'm not going to cover all
the markets. I just want to kind of
cover Bitcoin here.
And I've been really looking at the same
things for the last few weeks. But one
of the biggest setups we see almost
every time we run into a big event. And
I know that this is a very rare event.
So I'm not necessarily putting in the
same caliber as like an FOMC meeting.
That's just one of the biggest ones I
can relate it to that we again get a
calendar date and time for. But more
times than not, you get a very similar
thing to this, right? So for me, I look
for the very short-term entry triggers
and movements of the market where we
have especially on the time of the week,
okay? So today we had our Monday range.
You hear me talk on this time and time
again, all right? Context is always key
in this sense where when this is
established, we look for a sweep of
either the low or the high and then
generally speaking, we make a run for
the opposite end, okay? In this case, we
started off Tuesday with taking out
Monday's low here. Nice reclaim here so
far and realistically by the end of
Monday now, it's again it's about 6:00
p.m. on
Eastern on time of recording and we've
now come up to the high.
Now generally, if we had not done
something like this here, I would look
for this sweep of the high right there
to be a big short opportunity. And I
guess it still could be, right? Cuz
realistically speaking, if I was to take
off, you know, the the key levels here,
what have we done? We've come up and
we've taken the liquidity here.
Potentially, this news comes out really
negative and and things kind of
transpire. But if we see this Monday
high claimed here very shortly, meaning
we start closing up above this 70,300.
I think it's a very likely that we
actually get a very quick move up to
about 75,000. Now this is a high
timeframe average. This is a
target that is going to be really
relevant for this entire quarter. So I
really want to point out that it is it
is possible to get a move to that level
and it's possible to get it very very
fast, all right? So it's like a mean
reversion play.
Again, it's really dependent on getting
above this 70,300, which is pretty much
where we are right this moment. So
looking to flip that and we could see a
very quick move up to here. Again, if it
could align with the news ending out,
you know, coming out a little bit more
positively.
For me, I've been tracking Bitcoin for
ever, but like really heavily recently
looking for a move actually to the
upside here. So far as like where we are
right this moment, some lines in the
sand, very locally, 70,300. Get above
that, I think we actually make a move
for 75. Alternatively, you know, have we
swept the highs and could see a move
back down? It's always a possibility,
right? And then we are right into
resistance. So it just really comes down
to this nice key level where we're at
right now. 70,300.
You know, tuning out everything aside,
but if we want to pay attention for how
things kind of
facilitate here. Again, with the context
being key, the fact that we've already
taken this low and made a move for the
high, generally speaking, we do that in
the sense of continuation. So for me,
I'm actually looking for this to get
flipped and a move up to that $75,000.
So we'll see how it all unfolds. That's
really all I wanted to cover tonight.
Nice and brief for you. Just want to
kind of give a highlight as we're coming
into some of those key areas on Bitcoin.
If you would like more updates like this
from me, you know where to find me. Go
ahead and drop down at datadashpro.com
down in our description area and you can
join the market intel community where I
put up all my updates, educational
content, everything like that. You have
direct access to me and stuff like that.
So
if you're interested, be sure to check
that out. Otherwise, thank you all so
much for tuning in. I hope you all enjoy
the rest of your day, evening, morning,
wherever you are in this beautiful
world. Till the next video everybody.
Cheers.