Bitcoin has just made a violent move
back towards $70,000. But what's driving
this rally might surprise you, or at
least it may appear that way. It seems
that this move did not come from an ETF
flow or anything of that nature. Uh for
me, I have been anticipating a little
bit of a move towards the upside, but
let's take the technicals aside and put
it around something that I think
everybody's going to be talking about or
has been talking about, which is the
news that broke over the weekend.
basically a series of unexpected
geopolitical headlines and posts from
Truth Social or expost from from our
president uh regarding the global
conflict involving Iran. And when
Bitcoin rallies uh on news like this or
around with news like this, the big
question for everyone becomes, is this
real strength here or just another
liquidity grab before the next move
lower? Because structurally, Bitcoin is
now testing a level that has rejected
price multiple times this year. And what
happens here could determine whether we
push towards $80,000 or rotate back
towards the $60,000 region. Welcome back
to Data Dash. My name is Paul Samson.
And really quick, I want to ask you a uh
real quick favor. I want you to stop
what you're doing. Drop me a one-word
answer in the comments section. I want
you to say pump if you think that the
rally here continues or the word fail if
you think that this move fades. This
helps me to understand where our
audience is positioned and it also
massively helps the algorithm get this
analysis in front of more traders and
investors such as ourselves. All right,
let's break down what's actually
happening here.
All right, again folks, we had a pretty
slow move here as we went through the
holiday weekend, right? We had Easter uh
over the weekend here. Uh yesterday as
we closed the week, we had this last
moment kind of burst that it came again
on the heels of some of those posts uh
that occurred on Truth and X five six%.
This is a little bit zoomed in here
though like right let's zoom it out here
and see what we're truly looking at. Uh
really nothing nothing of substance
quite yet. Right. So again we are still
just truly rangebound in this region. uh
seeing a series realistically however of
higher highs and higher lows right
across the board here on this where we
uh could very well see a substantial
bottom have been put in right here.
Right? So as long as we are holding
above that uh this could very well
continue to kind of trend a little
sideways and slowly make its way break
up above some key regions and actually
track higher uh into the middle point of
this year right throughout the summer
and stuff like that. And that's still
kind of what I have, you know, on on the
docket. Uh there's just so much we've
left up in this region. Uh on top of
that, we still have uh all the markets
pretty much in extreme fear. Yeah,
crypto still down at 13. Obviously, this
was updated 15 hours ago. It might track
up a little bit here, but it was at like
seven or eight. Overall, even if this
does kind of flow around in this region,
it still states that the markets are
basically extremely fearful here, right?
everyone's relatively bearish, expecting
lower, expecting a crash, expecting the
recession um to continue if you know
we're considered to be in one. Now you
obviously we have the global conflicts
that are constantly you know
everchanging which realistically or look
back I mean we are always in the middle
of something let's be honest and uh but
with this paired here and just the
structure of Bitcoin and how we are just
like basically just boring people to to
you know as boring as it could be I
guess in the bigger sense of like really
not doing much. We're getting these
exciting little pro uh pushes up. We're
getting these very scary drops down. And
realistically, these moves only seem
exciting or scary because that's all
we've known now for the last few months.
All right. When you track back to the
times where, you know, we were really
seeing big pushes. I mean, uh the moves
that we're seeing today would have been
nothing burgers in that sense. But now,
every 3 to 5% move, which is
realistically a huge move in Bitcoin, uh
does really excite the people, whether
it's a good excitement or or a negative
one. Uh, but I do have a couple things
highlighted here. Obviously, I have this
$75,000 level marked. That is our uh
high time frame average for this
quarter. Very likely to be met during
Q2. Um, so while we got to be aware of
some more local price action where we
just kind of taking the highs right now,
uh, could very well get some, you know,
shorter term pullbacks yet again. And
the 70k region has just acted as just
such a huge level across the board. But
uh ultimately I do anticipate us at
least floating up to 75,000
uh in the in Q2 of this year. And from
there that's our next key line in the
sand. I mean this is e easy as can get
to. I mean pretty much just structurally
we could see here that that's basically
where our last high comes in as well. So
getting back above that $75,000 is truly
what opens us up uh for more sizable
upside to start, you know, kind of re uh
gaining and recapturing some of these
regions up here. And from there, we can
look towards some of those uh larger
areas that I've been pointing out.
Right, we have that really bullish big
bullish shark that's still very valid
here as long as we are remaining above
this $60,000. Uh this is something
that's taken a long time to print. It's
not going to get here in a hurry, right?
Usually it takes a lot of time here as
well. We got the nice little base
basically acrewing down here and I would
imagine if we're going to make our way
up towards that big target one, it's
probably going to be middle of the year
here. So, still, you know, several
weeks, maybe even a few months here out
before we get really going. Uh, more
than likely, if we do break to the
upside this region, obviously it's
probably going to be met with some uh
haste, right? Because again, what comes
down fast, if we get back into those
regions, we usually come back up fast.
So, um, still pretty much just waiting
to see how this unfolds here. If you're
going to look for two lines in the sand
essentially, pretty simple where we are
now, right? are basically we don't want
to lose our $60,000 low for any more
unless you do want to go short uh and
continue lower. Uh and as far as any
more upside need to get above 75,000 um
especially on a daily closing basis,
right? On the last time we came up, we
could just see we wicked above that how
we had this high right here in place,
right? And essentially we just kind of
wicked up around these highs and came
back down. We don't want to see that uh
when we come back up here again because
we all know again that's just what we
do. It's just constant liquidity sweeps
uh each and every time. Uh but in
general, when you're starting to see,
you know, this type of formation, all
right, where we're having these higher
highs and higher lows, especially in a
long period like this, this is from
February 6th to, you know, it's been two
months now today. And uh generally
speaking, we're going to see this range
resolve uh relatively soon. Okay? So,
meaning that we're going to break one
way or the other here. Uh so, the key
for any more sizable upside is simple.
It's 75,000. All right? for the time
being from where we are now from 68 to
69 I I would say it's likely we push up
to that region it's just going to be are
we going to hit our head there reject
and roll over are we going to push
through decisively uh hold that on a
daily closing basis and then get that
next move up right so that's what we're
looking for kind of being patient here
in the in the bigger picture uh there's
going to be a lot of smaller time frame
moves we see it each and every single
week um but yeah uh this this is overall
higher time frame outlook I'm looking at
probably at least a move to 75,000.
That's our line in the sand for any more
sizable upside. Before we move on to
Ethereum and the broader markets, I also
want to thank Bit Unix, our exclusive
exchange partner here on the channel. If
you've been actively trading or looking
for another platform to diversify where
you execute your trades, uh Bit Unix has
been one of the exchanges I've been
working with recently, and they've put
together some great exclusive perks for
the Data Dash community. If you sign up
using our link below, you're going to
unlock special benefits, including the
opportunity to receive up to $100 per
month during our campaign. when you're
part of the Market Intel community. So,
here's how it works. If you join Market
Intel, where I share all my deeper
analysis, trade frameworks, and ongoing
market updates, which you can find over
at data-pro.com. This is where you can
access the market intel. And once you're
there, you can head into the Bit Unix
verification area inside the community.
And there you're going to find the
simple steps to qualify for the monthly
rewards. This was designed to
essentially help offset your membership
cost while you're learning and
participating in the community. So, if
you're interested, you can find the Bit
Unix link down below in the description
and check out the details there. I look
forward to seeing you in the community.
All right, Ethereum is generally
trailing with Bitcoin for the most part
on, you know, the setups at hand, uh,
what they tend to kind of produce
together. And same thing kind of applies
here, right? We're putting in a pretty
good, uh, looking set of higher lows in
this long, uh, period here where we're
just pretty much trending to the side.
uh really getting everyone worked up on
again each and every single smaller
move. Uh but overall holding relatively
well here at that $1,700 low back in
February. Uh we have had some you know
more recent highs here come back down
towards the lows but like I said we're
seeing consistent higher lows across the
board here which generally tend uh to
lead to a move back up to the upside.
Okay. So, um, yes, again, we have our,
you know, key inflection points to be
aware of. Uh, but for similar to Bitcoin
here, if we get back above that 75,000,
you know, what could we see out of ETH?
Uh, we have a couple of things, uh, left
above here, tracking all the way back up
to like $3,400, right? And again, these
are high time frame averages that are,
uh, statistically likely to be met in a
certain time frame. And this one is, you
know, just so happens to be the first
half of this year. All right? So,
between now and the end of June. So
again, that summer time frame, uh, just
really lining up for, you know,
potential big moves here out of the out
of the market because if we did get that
liftoff from where we are now, it's
about a 60% push out of out of Ethereum.
Uh, which would obviously probably bode
well for the entire market if we saw a
move of that nature. Uh, it would be in
line with Bitcoin, you know, probably
coming up to some of those shark
harmonic targets. Okay, so that's uh,
what I'm looking at here on ETH as well.
Pretty much just simple and sweet here
as far as that goes. We do have a 1856
uh volume level down below to just to be
aware of. Uh still haven't come down for
it, but ultimately we don't necessarily
have to right now. Um and looking to see
if we, you know, basically claim that
$2,400 as our, you know, our next line
in the sand above us for any more
sizable upside uh to seek out if we're
going to continue that move up to the up
towards that 3,400. Now, the S&P 500 has
really given a little bit more
excitement here than it has been in the
last few months, right? We've pretty
much been in an up only environment
since last April. Held our uh, you know,
our own up here around this region. Got
a nice little dip down to these areas
here. We have a couple of things stacked
up just a little bit lower about 6,200
6,000. You know, our previous highs back
here, yearly average right here, 382
retracement zone, which is very common
to come down and tag. Um, again, don't
necessarily have to, but that's just
where I'd be looking for to get
interested in anything if I was, you
know, personally looking for any kind of
new positions here. But we did see a 10%
decline here in the S&P 500. Uh which is
a pretty pretty good move off of there.
Right. So uh from here again to me this
is really like a limbo stage as far as
like higher time frame does go. I think
that we have almost equal potential to
get a push up to this region as well as
to get a push down into this region.
Okay. It's just where we are in the the
market at this point. So, if you're uh
an, you know, investor already, um, be
aware that, you know, we could easily
see a push back up towards these $7,400
regions, if you're looking for any kind
of, you know, DCA opportunities or just
being aware of where the market could
come down to naturally, uh, that's, you
know, basically between $5,500 and
$6,200 in the in the coming weeks here.
All right, NASDAQ uh, tagged 50, not
50,000, it's Dow Jones. Uh, but NASDAQ
has come down, kind of front ran the 382
area as well. So that's something of of
note here is that both the S&P and the
NASDAQ both front ran key levels. So
again, nothing's perfect in this market,
but uh generally speaking, what happens
when we see that type of thing is that
you do get a little push back up to the
upside and then you know, you got to be
aware of that followthrough or you come
back down, take that liquidity sweep,
right? Because what happens, we all
know, people start to re-enter the
market here or enter new positions in
general because they're thinking we're
going to just rally straight back up.
you know, so far we're technically
reclaiming some ground here. So, in
theory, you you you know, you want to be
able to look like that or look at it
like that. Um, but yeah, in this sense,
again, we're very high up here. If
you're taking new positions, you know,
you almost want to be ready and willing
to take profits pretty aggressively into
like four to six% moves, which most
longer term, you know, outlooks aren't
going to really uh want to do that.
That's more for like a short-term
trading outlook. But uh the reason I say
that is because we could easily just do
something along those lines for a few
weeks. And I do say weeks because we all
know how slow, you know, this could all
just kind of move really nowhere uh over
the course of a few weeks and months and
ultimately come back down, take out that
low, meet our target right here, at
least one of them. Um, so that's
something we'll just kind of keep in
mind here in the next few weeks and
months because again, both the S&P and
the NASDAQ both front running those two.
Uh, usually sets that up for for a
return to those levels at a later time.
Dow Jones um, living down below
47,000ish here, right? We got as low as
about 45,000 after tagging that $50,000
mark basically to the te. So a nice
clean just $50,000 rejection, a what
about a 10% decline here as well. So
10%, you know, push back on S&P, 10% on
the Dow. I would assume that the NASDAQ
was probably about a 9 to 10% pullback
as well. Uh those are very common in the
sense of continuing the trend. So, you
know, just do really want to be aware
here that uh we could very well get this
next few weeks where we push back up.
All right, so everything's kind of taken
out a uh or taken a deep enough breath
to where it's it's likely to see us, you
know, kind of retrace back now up to the
upside. Again, that doesn't mean we have
to come to new all-time highs, but just
at least to kind of get a breather back
up and then maybe we get a rollover
later on uh in a few more weeks, but uh
all three of them, Dow, NASDAQ, and the
S&P all kind of align with that similar
situation. All have pulled back pretty
pretty decently here. All have taken out
relative lows uh to at least give us
some short-term relief. All right,
everyone. That's going to wrap things up
for today. Uh right now the most
important thing to watch is whether
Bitcoin can hold the structure uh as
well as build acceptance above these key
levels I'd mentioned today. All right?
So because that's going to tell us
whether this move has real strength
behind it or if we're looking at another
failed rally and push back down. Uh if
you got any value from today's
breakdown, please be sure uh to like the
video, subscribe to the channel if you
haven't already. It really helps us grow
the channel and continue building one of
the best market intelligence communities
out there. Uh if you'd like to stay
ahead of these moves, you can head on
over to data-pro.com. This is where you
can sign up for our free data dash uh
newsletter where we break down the
biggest developments across crypto and
macro each and every single week. As
well as if you want to go even deeper,
you can check out market intel uh where
I share my ongoing crypto analysis,
trade frameworks, key levels I'm
watching, and the monthly Dash report of
course where Nick breaks down the bigger
macro picture and long-term market
positioning. So if you're serious about
improving how to navigate these markets,
that's where we share our best work. Uh,
all of it is available again at
data-pro.com. Thank you all so much for
watching. I'll see you all in the next
video. And until then everybody, cheers.