Bitcoin saw a small relief rally
following the ceasefire news the other
day, but the momentum seems to be
fading as we head into the weekend. Now,
this is pretty typical behavior when
markets react to geopolitical headlines.
We often see an initial reaction move
followed by a period where traders
reassess whether the move actually
changes the broader trend. And right
now, price is actually sitting at a very
important decision area and the levels
that we hold or lose here into the
weekend could tell us a lot about where
Bitcoin heads next. So, in today's
update, I want to talk through the key
support and resistance levels I'm
watching and what they could mean for
the short-term structure.
And before we begin, I'd like to thank
today's sponsor, our exclusive exchange
partner, BitUniex. Now, as markets
remain active, execution quality and
platform reliability matter more than
ever and BitUniex continues to expand
its trading infrastructure globally. So,
if you're interested in learning more,
you can find their link and current
promotions down in our description area
below. Thanks again to BitUniex for
supporting Data Dash. Now, let's
continue to the analysis. All right, so
again, more of a local outlook here on
Bitcoin. We did get a pretty sizable
move on uh the other night after the
ceasefire news, right? Or leading up to
about a 7 and 1/2, almost 8% rally. Uh
and so far, we're actually still holding
that move relatively well, even though
like I said, it does feel like it's
beginning to fade a little bit. Um I do
want to point out the key areas that
we're looking to as we approach the
weekend here. And but realistically, as
long as we are holding above uh
currently here about 69,260,
uh that would be probably the the
biggest level for the remainder of this
week at least, right? So, we want to see
that level hold. I will point out uh
that we could do something along these
lines here where we actually come down.
There's two key pieces right below about
68,500 uh that we did leave on the big
rally up, okay?
And a lot of times, we will see
uh a lot of these moves get retraced a
bit back into some of the key
components. It's just like watching the
the chart basically come back and it
could be viewed almost as like a gap in
the chart or like an inefficiency,
right? that the market may come back and
fill in. Uh so, those two key levels are
sitting down here about 68,500 to
68,800.
Um and realistically, we could see
something along those lines and still
come back wick above or wick down
essentially, close back above that
69,200 and continue on our way. Uh
either way, even if we are to come down
to these regions or not and just hold
from where we are now,
again, looking at this in the in the
eyes of the trend, more than likely
actually continuing up. I just wanted to
showcase why if we did see a little bit
of a drop down about two it's not even
uh but 2% probably from where we are
now, 2 and 1/2% almost three,
uh would be very very normal to see.
Again, key regions, key levels are
existent down there and it does make
sense for us to come and revisit that
even before heading higher.
Uh on the flip side of that, we have
broken through uh that really nice level
here again, 69,200. We're holding above,
we're holding above previous highs here
as well. And if we're zooming it out
just a little bit, we are continuing,
right? With these higher lows and higher
highs across the board here. So, even if
we were to come back down again, that
would put in what? Another higher low
around this region.
Uh and I do believe that we're actually
on track to push higher into our higher
time frame average, uh which is this is
the average of last quarter, likely to
be met this quarter in Q2 of 2026. And
that is 75,048.
Now, I've pointed this out pretty
heavily recently, but that 75,000 is a
pretty critical level for a multitude of
reasons. So, again, the short-term
outlook here as we're coming into the
weekend, walking into the next week,
uh realistically, I mean, I think that
we're still in line to kind of get that
push up into that 75,000. On the case of
where we could pull back to and why, I
think that there's a really good case
that we would down towards about 68,500
uh in that region,
come back fill a couple of uh
inefficiencies here. Like I said, look
at that almost like a CME gap
essentially uh that's down below us
again. Uh where would a local gold
pocket be? I'm sure that's a little low
or a little These are a little low for
it.
But either either way, uh really really
decent little areas to be aware of right
there like 68,500 like I said. But from
where we are to just seek out
continuation, I think that that's truly
the the the way we're probably going to
be leading into
uh and that is up there about 75,000.
Now, pushing all the way up there, now
we're just going to lead into a little
bit of a higher time frame view. Uh just
to kind of give us a little bit of an
overview. Again, I covered this pretty
heavily on Monday, but realistically, if
we were to just go ahead and straight
up, you know, block off a range here
that we've been in since February time,
our wick down,
uh we can easily see here that, you
know, we've got a clear range and we are
slowly making our way through it, high
side and low side. The high side coming
right in about that 75,000, low end
coming in about 62,000.
So,
not only is this our high time frame
average that's likely to be met here
soon, uh it is the number one level that
if we were going to get above it, uh
that is where we can seek out some
sizable continuation to the upside,
right? So, um it does also mean on the
flip side that that's an area where we
could see a push all the way back up to
and technically nothing really
materialize outside of a short-term
rally, okay? Now, tomorrow, we have some
new economic data that's going to be
released and it's the first one so far
ever since the Iran issue that we've,
you know, been fake well, the the
ceasefire and all the, you know, things
that were kind of taking place earlier
this week. Um
so, it could be a little bit of a news
catalyst as far as timing goes. So, that
is tomorrow, right? So, if we're going
to see uh either the move back down
about 68,000 or get that push up towards
75,000, it could occur tomorrow on a
Friday, which
uh weeks and weeks ago, we saw pretty
much our largest moves take place on
almost every Friday, it felt like. So,
uh to see something like that would be
pretty pretty much on par. Again, in
with pairing that with the economic data
that's going to be presented, I just
kind of make sense to potentially see a
move tomorrow.
Uh but then, yeah, the big key here,
folks, is just to even if we get that
burst up towards about 75,000, we really
need to flip that on a daily closing
basis. Again, this is a 4-hour time
frame. You can see we've only wicked
above it just once.
Uh so, we want to close a day outside of
that. And if we can even do one better
and close this week above that if we get
up to it, uh that would look really
really nice. Uh and then again, we would
be just continuing the uh larger picture
track here for our bullish harmonic
setup uh that that could take us back
upside of 90,000
uh in the coming months here, right? So,
again, this is a big picture view here
now.
Uh everything I just discussed, we were
talking about this little area of the
price action where we could see small
two, three percent, maybe a 10% move
back up. Uh now, this would be a sizable
move that truly does unleash if we start
to close daily and weekly above that
75K, all right? Until then,
um can't get overly, you know, excited
for anything of that nature. And but at
the at the moment here though, folks,
again, this is a very valid setup. The
timing of this completion zone was right
on time. Everything about it is in line
at the moment. So,
uh in in theory here, we could see this
move unfold. And again, larger time
frame
uh pattern that's printed here, it took
almost a year to print. So, it probably
would take a few months up to six months
to reach some of these targets, okay?
Doesn't mean it has to hit uh just
target one in that region, but around
the three to six-month mark is where we
can start to
uh really anticipate if we're going to
continue on and see this pattern unfold.
Uh that's the time frame. So, probably
around this number uh would be the the
window of that. And then again, this
would
potentially look like we have something
where we have those higher low, our
higher high, our higher low. We start
putting in that next higher high, this
is going to start to look like a sizable
low in Bitcoin. Um where even if we
don't see new all-time highs out of
this, this could lead up into that next
move, which again is is sizable. This is
a potential
uh 30% move from where we are now and an
overall 50% move from the low just to
get back up to 93K, which in theory
wouldn't be that exciting in the grand
scheme, right? Because you're still
putting in lower highs across the board
and all that good stuff. So, we'd have
to see how things kind of shape up
around there. But yeah, big big
potential move to be had in the coming
months and just a little bit of a relief
as we move into the summer here. And
then all that opens up with 75,000.
All right, everyone, that is going to
wrap up today's update. As always, the
key right now is watching whether
Bitcoin can hold these key levels as we
head into the next week because that
will likely tell us whether this was
just a short-term relief rally or the
start of something more constructive. If
you found this breakdown helpful, please
be sure to like the video, subscribe to
the channel if you haven't done so
already. It really helps us get this
research out to more traders and
investors such as ourselves. And if you
would like more structured analysis like
this, you can always check out our
website datadashpro.com
where you can sign up for our free
newsletter here where we share a bunch
of market insights as well as learn more
about our premium products such as the
Dash Report by Nicholas Merten or the
Market Intel community where I share
deeper technical breakdowns, trade
frameworks, and ongoing market updates
as well as my
included educational series that comes
along with your membership. You can find
all of that link down below. Again,
datadashpro.com for that. Big shout-out
and again, thank you to BitUniex for
supporting the channel. Thank you all so
much for watching. As always, be sure to
stay disciplined, manage your risk. I'll
see you all in the next video. And until
then, everybody, cheers.