All right, so here's the situation with
XRP right now and I think it's worth
laying out clearly because on the
surface you'd look at this asset and say
things are actually moving in the right
direction. You've got ETF flows
returning. You've got the one of the
largest XRP conferences in history that
just wrapped up in Tokyo. You've also
got a Senate bill that could unlock
institutional partnerships that are
currently sitting behind NDAs and yet
XRP can't get above a dollar 35. It
seems to get sold into each and every
single time. So the question here I want
to answer today is that is this
distribution here or is this a
accumulation disguised as weakness
because the two of them look exactly the
same on the chart until they don't. Now
before we get into the analysis, I want
to know where you stand out there in the
audience right now today to April 10th
2026. Are you bullish or bearish on XRP
over the next 30 days? Drop it in the
comments down below the word bullish or
bearish. I always love to see which way
the audience is leaning. So looking at
the chart again folks, when we're
looking at the most recent couple of
months here, is this distribution or is
this accumulation because again, the two
of them can look very similar until they
don't. What I mean by that is we tend to
we tend to get a break of either way,
right? So price action has been
basically stalling around this dollar 35
cents, the average of where we've been
around these last few months. Now I've
taken off all my analysis here just to
kind of get a really simple overview of
the price, okay? We've had a high up
here about 368 back in July of 2025 and
a slow grind back down. And if you
actually zoom out a little more here, we
can actually see we had a monster rally.
XRP was actually one of the few that if
you would to look couple years here,
probably could say or be said that it
had an actual alt season in that sense,
right? Where you have that traditional
really sizable move to the upside over
6-700%.
From the lows that were put in place
again back in like really we were
sitting there from basically 2022 to
2024 slowly putting in higher lows,
higher lows, higher lows, higher lows.
This is again something that when we're
looking at can you know
Again, when you're looking at something
that is potentially building for
accumulation or distribution, this is
one of those times that looks like it
could be either you know, go either way
essentially.
But this one ended up you know, giving
us a really nice move to the upside. So
we have a smaller version of that now. I
do want to point out again though that
we are still even at a dollar 35 sizably
to the upside, you know, so we're still
pretty much a well above where we were
just a couple of you know, years ago. So
that must be said
and I want to cover now the the more
local price action here. What we can
anticipate out of XRP. We've got a bunch
of decent you know, news catalysts that
are wrapped around this. Those don't
always interact
with the price immediately, right? So
that's one thing I do want to point out.
Generally speaking, I can look at I tend
to look at just the overall TA and I
like to go off of that pretty pretty
heavily. But I I will kind of intertwine
some of the the more fundamentals into
this video specifically.
But yeah, let's take a look here. So
let's go ahead and add the drawings on.
So this is what I put up in the market
intel community recently, okay? We're
just looking at this just the other day.
I wanted to point out that we have a
lower case B volume profile here, okay?
So that's when you see this volume
basically tapered you know, at the top
here and it's all consolidating down
here at the lows, which we can obviously
see from this region. So one of two
things occurs here. Usually this
actually does lead to continuation,
okay? So what that means is that we've
got this you know, nice decline down.
We've been consolidating here and I
guess you could put into the
distribution phase, right? Where we're
going to distribute that and then we're
going to head lower, okay?
So that is one thing that must be said
here is that we are you know, in a place
where that is
something that does tend to happen here.
Now now on the opposite side of that,
this is the result of just what we were
talking about in the beginning where we
are accumulating at this region. So
if we're going to give a couple of key
levels to really be aware of here,
right? So I always like to give the
lines in the sand for especially the
more local price action so that we are
aware of where things can change here,
where things do become a little bit more
bearish, where things become
exponentially more bullish as well. And
when we're trading down at these lows, I
always like to point out that you know,
currently if you know, you're looking at
just from where we've been to where we
are now, you're down about 65% from
July's highs, okay? So you don't always
you don't really ever want to get too
bearish at support like that, all right?
Even though we could overall still roll
over lower, we want to really be looking
for the the bounce opportunities more
than anything or the opportunities for
us to actually see an impulse move back
up to the upside. So let's go ahead and
take this off. I do want to you know,
just kind of want to highlight that, but
let's go ahead and hide that for now.
The big key level for me
is going to be 2025's low at a dollar
and 25 cents and you can see how we've
been respecting this you know, really
really nicely ever since that February
low that we put in place when we dropped
down about a dollar 12. But we've been
above that 2025 low, dollar 25 line in
the sand. Let's just put that there
pretty clearly. We don't want to see
daily candles starting to close down
below that. If we do see that, then we
do look at this more of a distribution
phase and maybe we are going to see a
little bit lower price action,
which in the sense of how high XRP has
you know, lifted from those lows from
years ago, that 50 cent region,
we we could see a revisit to that. We
don't want to see that if you want to
see XRP's price continue higher here.
But so far we're holding this region
pretty well and we are we do have you
know, a good amount of key regions that
are left above us, okay? So two main
ones and this is just realistically if
we were to almost break this off into a
more local range that we've been trading
in, right? Makes a little bit of sense,
right? So one is at 141. So this is
compounded of a couple of volume levels,
high time frame averages. It's right at
the middle of the range as well. You see
this dotted line. So 141 is a current
more local key level we'd like to see
XRP get above. It's it's probably going
to come up and tag it regardless. We're
only at about $1.35 right now. It's not
very far away. But flipping that level
would give us the little more positive
reinforcement that we're probably going
to see the high side of this range back
towards the dollar 55, which is where we
were just trading at on March 18th. But
realistically we have a new high time
frame average that has come into play.
Very likely that we hit that in Q2 of
this year. So that's where we are where
we are currently between now and July
and that does sit up here at about 161.
So again, not really anywhere we haven't
been in the last few months. It's pretty
much at the high side here about a 20%
move there. But if we're going to get
any type of exponential move back up to
the upside where we could see pretty
much all of this price action recovered,
that is the level that we want to get
above. So more you know, like a small
you know, little green flag I guess you
could call it like something that kind
of gives us a little bit of glimmer of
hope is getting above 141 shows a little
strength. 161 is definitely the one we
want to see and again these are daily
candles we want to see closes above not
just these wicks like we see over here
and over here that end up in reversals.
We want to see a daily candle body
closing out here, a back test maybe and
then we'll look for that next lift off
back up towards the $2 range plus. So in
the sense of the lines in the sand for
XRP for any more sizable downside or any
more sizable upside, 125 we need to
hold. If we lose that, more downside can
occur and 161 is the area that we could
get up to. Really nothing materializes
aside from a 20-25% pump. And if we flip
that, that's where we could have a
really nice move potentially again back
to $2, $2.20 area, which would probably
make the XRP community relatively happy.
So yeah, that's what I'd be looking for
here. So 125, 161. Now on the
fundamental side of things, I just want
to kind of touch on a couple things here
and probably the most significant
development for XRP that most people
aren't discussing with the urgency that
it deserves is probably the clarity act.
I mean I know some are, some aren't, but
this could be really big in this sense.
And coming up next week, the Senate
returns on April 13th. That's this
coming Monday. What's expected to follow
is a committee markup of the the clarity
act, which is the bill that would
formally define the regulatory status of
digital assets including XRP. Now why
this matters so much is that for one
specific reason is that the Ripple
president Monica Long confirmed publicly
that there are institutional
partnerships currently under NDA that
expire once that bill passes.
Partnerships that Ripple can't even name
yet and that's not speculation, that's
direct statement from the Ripple
leadership. Now think about what that
actually means structurally. If those
NDAs unlock, you would see a wave of
announced institutional integrations
that the market has not priced in yet
because it doesn't know what they are.
That's the kind of asymmetric event that
can reprice an asset pretty quickly, get
us probably to get a nice move to the
upside towards that $2, $2.60 range. Now
the question is timing because the
committee markup doesn't mean the bill
passes, but it means it's moving and
every step forward narrows the
uncertainty that has kept the
institutional capital on the sidelines.
Before we keep going, I want to take a
second to thank today's sponsor
iTrustCapital. Now this is a platform
that I actually personally use and
especially when I'm thinking about
long-term. Because for me it's not just
about trading XRP or crypto in the
short-term. It's about how I'm
positioning for the next 5, 10 or even
20 years. And what I like about iTrust
is that it allows you to invest in
assets like XRP inside of tax-advantaged
retirement accounts. So instead of just
holding crypto in a regular account,
you're thinking in terms of how do I
build long-term capital in a more
efficient structure. You can roll over
old 401Ks or IRAs, which I've actually
personally done in the past from a
previous employer and then actually
reposition that capital into digital
assets. And another piece that's really
interesting about iTrust is the ability
to borrow against your assets. So
instead of having to fully liquidate
positions, you can still access
liquidity while maintaining your
long-term exposure to crypto. Now
platforms like iTrust, these should be
viewed as tools and you still need to
understand how they work and be able to
use them responsibly. But when used
correctly, this is how people start
thinking about more strategic ways to
enhance their portfolio for the
long-term. If you want to check it out,
I trust is currently offering a $100
funding bonus when you sign up using our
link down in the description area below,
which in my opinion, is basically
getting rewarded just for taking the
time to set up and explore the platform.
Again, I'll have the link down in our
description area below to I trust
capital. Big thank you to the team again
for supporting the channel. So, XRP
Tokyo 2026 just wrapped up two days ago
on April 8th in Tokyo, obviously, with
over 3,000 attendees, more than 20
speakers, Ripple leadership, SBI
Holdings, which is one of Japan's
largest institutions. This was Asia's
largest conference dedicated exclusively
to XRP and the XRP ledger. Now, here's
the context piece. Japan's tokenized
real-world asset market is already
sitting at $2.8 billion in institutional
platforms. The projections for growth
over the next few years are significant.
Japan doesn't move slowly on frameworks
once they commit, and they've committed
to a digital asset structure that is
favorable to XRP's utility layer. Now,
the irony here is that XRP closed Q1
down 27%
six straight red months, and the
conference still drew 3,000
institutional attendees. That tells you
something about the divergence between
price action and the institutional
development. Those two things don't
always move together, but sometimes the
build-out can occur near a local bottom.
Now, two things that happened this week
I want to connect is that yesterday on
April 9th, Ripple minted 2 million RLUSD
on Ethereum, and if you don't know,
RLUSD is Ripple's stablecoin that's
backed by reserves. The fact that
they're expanding the multi-chain
footprint specifically onto Ethereum
tells you that they are positioning
RLUSD as an institutional liquidity
instrument, not just an XRP ecosystem
play. And at the same time, a company
called Trident Digital Tech Holdings
announced a $500 million corporate XRP
treasury uh specifically to provide
liquidity for African cross-border
payment corridors. The phase rollout
targets mid-2026, and once that
liquidity is in place, Ripple turns on
ODL corridors with the African partners.
And to put that in a context, the global
cross-border payment market Ripple is
targeting sits at about $13 billion
annually, and if ODL routes even a
fraction of that volume through XRP, the
demand mechanics shift structurally. The
challenge historically has been that
corporate treasurers prefer stability,
and that's precisely why RLUSD matters.
It gives institutions a stable on-off
ramp with the XRP ecosystem while still
using XRP as the settlement rail. This
is not just price action today, but it's
the architecture that price action
eventually catches up to. Now, let's
talk about the ETF situation because
this is where the market has gotten
confused, and understandably so. XRP
spot ETFs were approved in November last
year, and the market expected a similar
reaction that Bitcoin had when their ETF
was approved, which was a large spike.
Instead, XRP actually dropped and
continued to decline during Q1 of 2026.
Now, this week we saw a good amount of
new XRP ETF inflows, a small but notable
shift back from the outflows that
dominated in March. And here's what I
think is actually happening here. I
think the ETF is approved, but
institutional capital isn't flowing in
at scale because the underlying
regulatory question. XRP's formal
commodity status under US law still
isn't resolved at the legislative level.
Clarity Act, I think, is what's going to
unlock that next wave. And ETF approval
was necessary, but it wasn't a
sufficient enough move, especially in
the timing of the market. I think the
setup is something along the lines of
approval, partial inflows, waiting on
the Clarity Act right now, potential
second wave of institutions inflows
once the bill advances, of course. And
is that a guarantee by any means? No,
right? There are real downside risks
here. Again, another great example of
even with the ETFs is that Ethereum and
Bitcoin both received ETFs recently and
have both seen multiple 50% or more
drawdown since. So,
it doesn't necessarily just mean up only
comes from there, but just in the
shorter term when looking at the price
action with some of the catalysts coming
up, I try to pair them up to see what we
could get and why
along these, you know, next few weeks
and months. Again, those key lines in
the sand for any more downside is that
$1.25 for XRP, and then any sizable
upside comes when we clear that 161. All
right, if you're watching this and you
want more daily breakdowns of XRP,
Bitcoin, the macro, and the broader
market as well, I put out a full
briefing every single day inside the
Market Intel community. That's my
premium community where members get the
analysis, the levels, the context before
the market opens. If that sounds useful,
the link is down in the description at
data-pro.com where you can find us over
there. Be sure to check it out if you're
interested. All right, so where does
that leave us with XRP? So, structurally
still the trend is bearish, right? Uh we
are down again 65% from the highs, and
that's just what the chart is saying,
right? So, lower highs, sellers showing
up at 135, 140 pretty consistently, and
the price is below uh some major
averages and all kinds of things like
that, right? So, we've been
consolidating in this region. I'm not
going to fight the narrative on that as
far as the TA would go. But again, we do
have a little bit of more upside
potential from where we are currently,
in my opinion. I think that 141 and 161
are likely to be met in a relatively
soon manner.
Um and if we lose 125 on that daily
basis, that's where things will change,
and things will continue to look a
little bit more bleak, and we'll
anticipate more downside at that point.
Thank you as always for tuning in with
this video. If you would like it, found
value, please like, subscribe to the
channel. I'll see you all in the next
video, and until then, everybody,
cheers.