Everyone is about to miss the next major
move in Bitcoin. While most traders are
still stuck in fear and hesitation, the
chart is telling a completely different
story here. Bitcoin is setting up for
what could be weeks of upside back
towards about $100,000. And if this
happens, it changes everything for the
market. And here's the part that no
one's talking about. The stock market
also looks ready to push into new
all-time highs, even while sentiment has
been absolutely bearish for weeks. All
that and more in today's episode. My
name is Paul Samson. Welcome back to
Data Dash. Before
we get started, I just want to thank
today's sponsor, our exclusive exchange
partner, Bit Unix. As the markets remain
very active here, execution, quality,
and platform reliability matter more
than ever, and Bit Unix continues to
expand its global trading
infrastructure. So, if you're interested
in learning more, you can find their
link and current promotions down in our
description area below. There's even a
way where you can join the market intel
where I provide all my daily setups,
updates, educational resources, and you
can actually offset that membership with
joining Bit Unix through that link. Uh
this is where you can actually get $100
per month airdropped via your Bit Unix
account, which again pretty much offsets
the market intel uh membership if you're
interested. Once again, check that out.
Big thanks to Bit Unix for supporting
Data Dash. Now, let's continue with the
analysis. So week after week, folks,
we've been in this decline here on
Bitcoin ever since that $126,000
area, which is a zone that to me was a
an area where we were going to see that
next pivot in the market. Yes, I did
anticipate more around the 130 mark uh
when we came down to it, but ultimately
within $4,000 and just a few% uh we came
into that zone really perfectly on time
as well. Again, we were putting in uh
two versions of this setup that before
any type of a four-year cycle, you know,
kind of end date or anything or I guess
you could say it was in align with it
like at the end of the day. But
regardless, uh the analysis was spot on,
right? We were looking for about 122 to
140 for a completion zone of a harmonic
here known as the AB equals CD. And
again, this is there's two versions of
this. This is the smaller one. Uh the
larger one dates all the way back to uh
2018's, you know, $3,000 low. But off of
this one here, this was our uh what was
that? The uh tariff. Now, this was our
carry trade low, our inauguration day
high, our tariff low, and then
ultimately our high that again I was
targeting for the week of September 29th
of 2025. We topped one week later um on
the 6th. Okay. So, very much in line,
very much around the target area. you
know, realistically, uh, even back here,
I was noting that this was technically a
valid setup all the way back here in
July, but we did kind of hold through,
came through on the exact date. And
again, I wanted to point out that this
was an area where if there was going to
be the next notable retracement, uh, 30
40%, you know, was anticipated.
Obviously, we went a little lower. Uh,
it was going to come from that region.
All right? And especially around that
time. So, we obviously got that. Again,
looking back, I did expect a little bit
more of a push. At the time, we didn't
get it. At the same time, we had to have
that risk, you know, around that time
frame, right? This was the biggest
window of um of risk. That's all we
could say. Since then, we have seen our
huge decline, right? So, a good old 55%
pullback uh in here. And realistically,
uh, while maybe not all-time highs are
on the on the docket here, uh, we are
setting up now and poised for, I
believe, a move that takes us back
towards at least $93,000 and if not 100,
uh, plus. Um, so I say 100 just to kind
of give it a nice rounded number there.
Uh, and if you have been, you know,
following along with, uh, my analysis
over the last several weeks, you know,
I'll kind of touch on it once again, but
this pattern setup has already been
played out. We were anticipating it, you
know, along this way. The only way to
take advantage of this is when this is
completed. All right? Because then we
can target lower or be aware of it. One
of the two things there, right, folks,
is that I don't anticipate everybody to
take advantage of every single move in
the market. Even I don't do that, right?
It's impossible at times. Uh depending
on your, you know, your schedule and
everything you got going on. And a
bigger piece of it is just to be aware
of why the price action could do, you
know, something and be aware of it ahead
of time, right? Because the worst thing
we want to do is just start scrambling
when we get all this negative news. And
um and a really great example of this is
just what we had a couple weeks back.
How many people and probably still kind
of are, right? We still have tariff, you
know, headlines dominated the market a
year ago. This year it is now the global
conflict, right? So every time something
happens, a tweet goes out or a new
headline comes out, everybody really
gets panicked and worked up on these
smaller moves when in reality those tend
to be where we see the biggest
reversals, right? So, let's go ahead and
click out of this again. Last year,
huge, huge fear right here around the
lows, around those tariff wos back then
and got a nice little sizable rally. At
that time, we did get a new all-time
high. Uh, in this case, again, let's not
look at $100,000 flat. Um, I'm going to
give the reasoning behind why I foresee
a real opportunity here for Bitcoin to
have put in a sizable low here. Been
putting in a pretty decent amount of
higher lows and higher highs here. All
right, which indicates that we will
actually see a little bit more of a move
to the upside very similar to what we
got at the end of uh 2022. All right, so
when we had all these lower highs,
right, when we were kind of trending
sideways, putting in and we could zoom
in here, but we had a real nice series
of higher lows, higher highs, and just
kind of broke out to the upside. Okay,
now again, that's a bare market low
scenario. Um, is this what that's going
to be at this point? I don't necessarily
know at this moment. Uh, I still think
we have a potential to even get a big
big rally back up and still roll over at
some point. But in the near term, and in
the sense that I'm saying near-term, I
mean like weeks and months here, right?
This is where we're looking at, um,
maybe from now through the summer, uh,
we could see this really, really nice
little move here, right? And it all
depend, it all comes down to yet again
the number one setup in at least Bitcoin
for the last few years, uh, which is
known as the shark. All right. If you've
followed any of my analysis over the
last several years here, you will have
seen time after time, we've gotten shark
after shark in Bitcoin. And again, this
is a setup that is derived off of
destroying everyone's emotions. Okay?
You come in and you have a low in place
here. You have a high in place here. So,
what happens? You get a sweep of the
high, which gets everybody in a
breakout, you know, excitement. This was
back on the 126, right? uh the push
towards 130,000 even at that point or
150,000. Everybody gets really excited.
We're breaking past the high yet again
only to get a you know huge meltdown.
You come down below the lows. You take
out that really big emotional piece
right there. Right. So everybody that
had been in a long position or a short
position over the last year essentially
gets wiped off the map. Um the again
everybody's back and forth and it's just
it's just taking a toll on everyone. Uh
right now we have huge huge negative
news as we're down at the low side here.
In this case, when we have a shark that
is completing into the downside here,
this is just very much like a a falling
wedge, a descending channel, right?
They're usually a bearish formation
right on the way down, but it is a
bullish setup. Okay, so nice clear
invalidation. Obviously, we want to stay
above our current low that $61,000.
We're a little bit aways from it right
now. Um, and then the key here for any
more sizable upside is flipping 75,000.
So, keeping those in mind, I've been
hammering on that for for quite a while,
right? That these these things can get
invalidated. It's nothing's guaranteed
in this world, but in my opinion, I
think that this is the the most likely
path at the moment. Uh, clearing 75,000
I think will open up the gates for this
really probably really quickly. I know
that many are looking at like 85,000.
Probably just looking at the, you know,
the low side right here, the previous
resistance. So, we probably will hit our
head on that for a little bit. Um, I do
have some, you know, key levels lined up
at there as well. But definitely
something to keep in mind, but in this
sense right here, uh, 93,000 is the is
the target. Okay, pretty decent move to
the upside to be had about 30%. If we
flipped over into the altcoins, that
would probably mean that we seeizable
rallies out of the alts as well. During
that time, the entire market would be
relatively bullish, right? So, um the
the key here again not not to get overly
excited, right? You know, again,
monitoring this information. Uh we are
floating up. Nothing really materializes
until we flip 75,000. Um and at that
point, then we I like I said, I think we
could get a pretty quick move even with
all the war and negative headlines
around that we've seen the last few
weeks. And by all means, I mean, we
probably had some as we led into this,
but the most, you know, scary ones came
when we were at the lows here, just like
we see time and time again. And on the
flip side here, again, this is a bullish
setup where we actually have upside
potential here. Uh, a really great
example of a bearish one that we had of
this exact magnitude was all the way
back here. All right, it's a smaller
smaller setup when you look back. Uh,
but this was inauguration day, right?
This is when we had uh, you know, the
most This is when we had inauguration
day. is when we had the most bullish
admin team coming into uh you know the
the White House as far as crypto would
go. We had the crypto reserves all
underway. Uh all these things that were
extremely exciting up here and yet we
had a bearish shark form. So right now
I'm pointing out how we have a bullish
shark with extremely negative news at
the lows which again usually triggers a
reversal. And this is just one example
here. this there's literally I could I
could take you back through every
notable high in Bitcoin over the last
few years and each and every single time
there was a shark present. Uh but this
was you know a really good example here
again we took out the lows right here in
uh January of 2025 again just to put it
you know a nice little break up to the
upside 110 12,000 up here. This is where
this is where the price breaks past the
previous high. Everybody gets excited.
Again this was literally right on
inauguration day. Why wouldn't the
market just continue to soar? And yet we
came down, had extreme, you know, not
extreme, but targets down below us. Uh,
a pretty decent little retracement,
right? This was about 25% at the time.
Uh, which was enough to really get
everybody worked up. It It obviously
went a little bit deeper. These aren't
the end- all beall. This is just giving,
you know, key areas to be aware of more
conservatively. Uh, but definitely was
something that we could look to when we
were here and be aware and take
advantage uh that we were coming down to
these levels, right? So, uh, this is a
bullish version. Like I said, I wanted
to point it out because again, news was
high as can be when we were at the
highs. All right, guess I will give you
one more. Again, the break to 72,000
74,000 back in March of 2024, right?
Right before we got a huge 35% pullback,
right? Now, this was when we got the
carry trade low, right? But again, we
had no reason at this time. ETFs were
hitting hard. Ethereum's ETF just hit uh
Bitcoin broke its previous $69,000
all-time high. The news and everything,
the catalysts were all lined up for more
upside, yet we put in this bearish setup
at the highs, at least indicating a
short-term pullback, right? So, it
wasn't necessarily the end all beall.
Gave us a 35% pullback. Again, you can
only take advantage of this when we're
at the completion zone because it's
really not going to do you much good to,
you know, get involved down here. You
have to look for the next setup. But
again, extremely bullish news and just
good vibes obviously when the price is
high uh only to get a pullback where it
just seems like it shouldn't have
occurred. So yeah, with this um again
timing for the completion zone was
perfect. The outliers of the news and
everything around it is as per usual,
but the setup is here and it's valid.
That's the biggest key point, right? So
again, the other two I just showed you
were extremely bearish setups uh that
you don't want to see. This is however a
bullish version, right? So again, it
doesn't necessarily mean we go right
back to all-time highs. Uh we do have a
very very big crucial target that if we
get up to this level, we'd have to get
through. Otherwise, this is a definite
area you want to be aware of as far as a
major takeprofit and a major level of
resistance that I don't think many
people are aware of. Um and then other
than that, it's, you know, 100,000 plus,
right? So I don't think that we stop, if
we got up to these regions, I don't
think we stop at 100. I think we push it
uh pretty well. And again, one of the
biggest factors around this time frame
is that we got the good old extreme fear
right now on top of it. Okay, so
with that being said, um, crypto is an
extreme fear even at these levels, which
is yes, we've been higher and we've come
lower and I know the altcoins have been
just an abysmal, but it is an
interesting standpoint to look at as an
investor. take a step back and and I
always joke about this because I've been
around this market for a long time is
that we always used to joke and say, "Oh
my gosh, Bitcoin one day will crash, you
know, to $60,000." Like $60,000 just
five years ago, six years ago, whatever,
2021 was such an accomplishment and such
an exciting area for for this market.
And we haven't even breached down back
below that in the last, you know, at
least year or so now, ever since getting
up to 120. But it's because we've been
to 120 obviously and we've come back
down 50%. That people look at this
sometimes. Your friends, your family are
gonna, you know, it's like, oh, it's
it's a scam yet again just because it's,
you know, correcting and cooling off
after extreme moves to the upside. Uh,
but realistically, we're at extreme fear
at a place where had we gotten to this
point five years ago, this would be
euphoria, right? So, it's just how you
approach the market. Of course, this is
again a bigger macro edition here. And
um I think that we're looking for you
know some more upside here. Uh the
conditions are ripe for the taking. Uh
and then as well as the stock market.
Now the stock market is ticking up a
little bit here. It is still technically
in fear. Uh but I do think that the
stock market's going to push up to make
make some new all-time highs. At this
point we're actually almost there. So
we'll take a look at that here in a
second, too. And before we do, let's
just take a look at our ETF flows. Uh
which this is not the overall like, you
know, outflow and inflow type of sheet.
I just like to look at it. You know,
Nicholas Martin did a really good job of
covering this one as well. And it is for
the not the first time. I think we've
seen it before, right? So, this is from
the inception on a quarterly basis of
all the ETFs uh that for Bitcoin, right?
So, January of 2024 here, we had about
621,000
increasing quarter over quarter. Maybe
right here we had oh uh yes, right here
we had a little bit of a decline. Uh and
so did we right here. So one small
decline right around this region between
1.125698
and you know about 500 less I guess over
the one quarter here between Q4 of 24 Q1
of 25
which
is interesting because of you know
quarter one is where we kind of had that
high side come in and then we got the
pullback and then across the board we
still had pretty decent increments.
We've been declining ever since Q
3, the end of Q3 of uh 2025, right? So,
we kind of peaked out at about 1.321
million uh then 1.3 at at the end of the
year last year and slowly kind of coming
down a little bit, but now it looks like
we're ticking back up even. So,
the bigger picture of this is that
obviously we are still overall uh on the
upside. something I like to bring up a
lot because I I know a lot of people
like to look and say it's the ETF flows
that are kind of causing this or that
and maybe it is. It's definitely a
piece. I wouldn't say that it's not the
the overall end all, but we've had so
much price action occur between this
time, you know, between the time the ETF
was born and and now, right, to where
again when we're looking back, you're
basically talking about ETF came into
the play right here around 30 $40,000.
And since then, we've seen huge moves
unfold. We still haven't even actually
made it back to that uh window of time
or that price action. But uh yeah, it's
it's I think it's a piece that a lot of
people will look to in the day-to-day to
to kind of give a little credence to why
the price action may be moving one way
or the other, but I don't think it's
like utilized in the way that it should
be. Um because again, when we're looking
at this price action, the current price
action I just pointed out, and then
we're looking at the overall, it is
tring up at the same time. Yes, we've
seen some decline, but on the few times
we've had the decline, uh it's not
necessarily aligned with every single
major here, right? Because we've had
some pretty big declines, even, you
know, more two two other ones, I guess,
before we even got to the most recent.
And even still, we're not really
dropping a a ton off of the uh you know,
the ETFs there. So, something I'll keep
monitoring, you know, trying to make a
good comparison with that. Maybe that's
not the best way to to kind of point it
out, but yeah, very interesting times
nonetheless. All right, S&P 500. I've
pointed it out for what feels like
forever and that $6,200 zone, right?
It's our yearly pivot. It's the 382.
2024 is high. So, just like looking at
this structurally, right, you get a
pretty decent little base that likely to
come back and back test. Now, one thing
that I look to specifically uh at times
is when you kind of can look across the
board, and I don't I don't really follow
a lot of social media. I'll be honest
with you. Uh, very rarely am I, you
know, watching a ton of other people's
things. For one, I don't have the time.
For two, I don't know. I just I just
follow my own strategy, so it doesn't
necessarily help or or hurt me, I guess.
But when I do kind of come across uh
quickly like on X, X is kind of probably
the best way I I do kind of like consume
content personally because you can just
kind of read it really quickly and get a
really big dose of what what the
sentiment is like across other creators
in the space and other traders and
things like that. And I do know that it
was very much agreed that, you know, we
were heading back to $6,200.
Uh and not to say we didn't get a decent
pullback here because we did, you know,
about 10% almost. uh but we front ran a
couple of key levels. So I will say the
keep 6219 on the on the radar for this
year because that is very much uh a high
time frame average that is likely to be
met this year. But I feel that we're
actually going to push up to new
all-time highs here. Right? So we're
back up to 6,800 again. It doesn't seem
too crazy at this point. We're only
about 2 3% 2 and a half%. Uh the way we
had this I don't want to call it a fake
out, right? But we, you know, came down,
took out our lows, right? So, you had
that nice pullback over 10%. Lows are
taken out. Reclaim of that low so far.
That is one of the most bullish signs
you could see uh in something like this.
And we've already got a nice little push
back up, right? A little gap right here.
Maybe comes down and fills. But now, as
long as we're holding back above this
6,500, uh, new all-time highs are on the
board and likely that we push up to this
74 to $7,700 box that I've had marked on
this chart for almost two years now. So,
is that all she's got as far as a
pullback goes? It does it does align
well at least with uh with a decent
pullback, right, that we've kind of seen
the S&P put into play before
continuation, right? these 10%
pullbacks. Uh we had the bigger one last
year obviously. What was that like?
Maybe 20, maybe it was 15. Yeah, 20%. So
that was our big tariff war uh from last
year. And uh yeah, so so far nice little
push. It did look a little heavy, right?
We needed some sort of a correction to
some degree. Got to 10%. Now we've
reclaimed our ground. That's where
things flip back to the bullish side. Uh
so while we're holding that, I
anticipate that we push up towards that
64 uh 7,400 7700. NASDAQ front runs the
382 just a little bit as well, right?
And then of course you could almost uh
you know this is a one and a half
percent. So you could almost consider it
hit is what it is, right? But same same
scenario here, right? The more important
thing to note is that we had this low in
place and what did we do here? You come
back down, you back tested and now we
are, you know, closing generously above.
Uh obviously we just opened up for today
but uh yeah be be aware that as long as
we're above 23887 on NASDAQ we're
probably heading up for the new all-time
highs as well. Target remains 28272
above us and the Dow Jones. So we came
up to to 50,000 perfectly kissed it and
then dropped uh a nice well-rounded
number and a nice 10 11% pullback too.
So when looking just structurally at
this same deal, right? We had pretty
much an up only scenario. Up only, up
only, up only. Our most notable low, you
know, comes in right here. What do we
do? You come down, you wick below it,
you reclaim it, you get that bounce back
up to the upside. So again, now as long
as we're holding above 45 389, the setup
at hand is that we get the runup next
major target 53,000 just about on the uh
on the Dow Jones.
So all three SP, all three, the S&P 500,
the NASDAQ, the Dow Jones, which
obviously in turn means that the overall
market is in a relatively healthy shape
right now alongside Bitcoin, everything
just has a more bullish tune to it right
now. Okay, so I do want to just kind of
point that out. Um, of all the things at
the moment, you know, I'd probably say
that Bitcoin has the uh better entry
area, I guess, if you're looking for
one, right? It's hard to come into
Bitcoin at $70,000 um and enter for any
kind of longerterm positions because
like I said, this is also an all-time
high just from a few years back. But it
is at a discount today. So again, that's
up for you to decide. I'm just pointing
out where the uh market is likely to
head based on probabilities, trying to
position myself as well as I can around
it, and then to bestow that information
to you as well for you to consider in
your own strategy and game plan. And
that's going to wrap it up for today's
episode, everybody. If you got value
from this breakdown and want to stay
ahead of these market moves, make sure
to head on over to data-pro.com.
It's where you can sign up for our free
newsletter, which is going to keep you
updated on the latest insights across
crypto and the traditional markets. And
if you're looking for deeper analysis,
you can check out our premium platform,
Market Intel, available on the website
as well. As always, thank you all so
much for watching. I'll see you on the
next episode. And until then, everybody,
cheers.