Most people are absolutely confused on
what's going on in the markets right
now. The S&P 500 just hit yet again
another new all-time high above $7,000
and the Nasdaq is pushing higher as
well. And the Dow Jones is right behind
it. And that's all happening right now
with geopolitical tensions, recession
fears, and everything we've been hearing
for months. Now, that doesn't happen by
accident. And at the same time, we just
saw Bitcoin push up to about $76,000 and
get a small pullback so far. And
everyone's reading this as extreme
weakness. I don't necessarily think it
is because when you zoom out and look at
what's happening across the markets,
Bitcoin, equities, and even micro
strategy, they're all aligning in a way
that we don't see very often. And if
these current structures hold, there's a
very specific move on the table that
most people are just, I still think, not
really prepared for. Let's break it all
down. My name is Paul Samson. Welcome
back to Data Dash.
All right, before we dive into the
charts, I do want to take a quick moment
and talk about something that I
personally use, and that is I trust
capital. As the markets start moving
like this, especially when we start to
see strength in both equities and
crypto, I'm always thinking about how
I'm positioned long-term and not just
short-term trades. And that's where I
trust Capital comes in. It's a platform
that lets you build a crypto IRA so you
can hold assets like Bitcoin, XRP,
Ethereum in a tax advantaged account.
Something I've used for years and which
is now a part of my long-term strategy.
So, if you've been watching this channel
for a while, you know that I'm not just
focused on catching moves. We're focused
on building positions over time. And if
you want to take the time to check it
out, you can use the link down in our
description area below. And they're
currently offering a $100 funding bonus
when you sign up. The link is down in
the description below. Now, let's jump
in to see what's going on with Bitcoin.
So, again, we're really just hovering at
this key area here, this $75,000,
$74,000 mark. Again, this was a uh major
high time frame average that was likely
to be met in quarter 2. alone with that.
It's our high side of the range that
many people could look at it, you know,
if that's the case as well. And one
thing I want to point out that I see a
lot of, right? And and again, nobody
knows which way the market's going to
go. Still waiting. We still need to see
that break above $75,000 to get any type
of upside here. But what I like to do is
when we're trading around these low
areas is be prepared for what's, you
know, the next most likely move because
I I do see that many people are trying
to just kind of blindly short this,
right? We get the rejection right there
and you got the big pullback. You get
the rejection here. We got a pullback.
We're trading up here and consolidating
which most people are looking at as a
bit of weakness because it doesn't seem
like price can break through that
$75,000 mark. And on the flip side,
unlike what we saw right here where we
saw this pretty quick, you know, one
move up straight down from there, we've
been kind of holding this area for the
last couple days now. So, a lot of times
that's actually consolidation before we,
you know, continuation essentially
before we break through it. again, need
to get above it, you know, for that to
confirm. And uh if that's the case, I
just think that we're in a position
where, you know, we could actually get a
really sizable move on our hands uh to
the upside. Now, one thing I see many
many doing right now is that they're
really looking at this as a similar
fractal, right? Like they're looking at
what happened in 2022 and just truly
believing that Bitcoin is just so simple
that it had done this in the past and it
has to do it again or it's most likely
that it'll happen. And it's it's just
something that yeah, I guess any time,
you know, we could take fractals and we
could take the probabilities of things
that have happened in the past and see
how they, you know, react again. And and
realistically, I guess that's really all
we're doing most times when we are
looking at technical analysis. We're
identifying patterns that we see time
and time again and the probabilities of
how they react. The thing I just see a
lot of right now, and again, I don't
watch a lot of social media. I don't
listen to many other voices in the
space, and not not negatively. I just I
just don't make the time for it, you
know, personally. And but the few things
that I do pick up on usually is like,
you know, what the majority are probably
seeing. Um because it's like the
occasional uh you know, post I'll come
across. And and again, X is a big one
because you can easily just kind of
consume a lot of content there just by
reading it. And many many many people
are pointing out that that fractal or
that situation there, the bare flag, you
know, where they're anticipating more
downside, right? So, as always, I'm open
to anything and everything. Uh, but when
looking at other factors currently, uh,
I just see a world where we actually,
uh, make a move to the upside, right?
So, the key is really breaking through
75K. Uh, for that, I would see a pretty
decent move back up towards about 93. As
we all know, I've covered that many
times already. And another big factor
that I like to, you know, the other
major factors that I like to take into
account are, let's just look at the
other, you know, the markets now, right?
So, we've got the stock market, the S&P,
you know, totally front ran. Again, uh
something that I'm kind of I'm not happy
in the sense of like for anybody that's,
you know, taking shorts and getting, you
know, wrecked or anything like that, but
it just it it very well was too easy,
right? Because again, including myself,
you know, when we're getting this little
roll over here, it was going to be most
likely that we would come back to the
previous consolidation here, our 24
highs, our 382 level, and we have an
untapped high time frame average that
all kind of stacked right here. Um, for
me, I just didn't love that it was also
right next to that. And again, if you
looked around, pretty much everybody uh
and their mother was happily shorting or
selling out of the stock market,
thinking that we would just really see a
a sizable crash. Then the global
conflicts occurred and kind of added
fuel to that fire and only to see us
just rip back and on Monday I just
described how you know what we did here
was extremely bullish, right? Because
what did we do? This is our most notable
low. We came down, you took that out. So
again, what that incites is it initiates
the the FOMO for people that are uh
wanting to short or you know getting
afraid and they want to sell out of
their positions before the market
crashes even lower or people enter new
short positions because they're thinking
that it will accelerate to the downside.
breakout traders I will look at this as
you know oh we broke a low it's got to
head lower
um and then if you don't have an
invalidation meaning that where is that
wrong well it's when we go back above
that previous low because at that point
now that's a trap essentially uh
liquidity sweep however you want to call
it and we tend to get a big quick I mean
it's a short squeeze at the end of the
day right it's a hard and fast move to
the upside in the stock market this is
no simple move this is you know
trillions of dollars I'm sure coming
into this market for a almost 8% rally
straight up from there and obviously uh
over 10% from the actual low. Now NASDAQ
is just now basically just you know
inching into the new all-time high as
well. Slightly front ran a couple of the
key levels also but again what did we
do? We reclaim that low right here and
just away we go, right? I call it the
sweeping low and go. Dow Jones uh is the
one of the three at least of the bigger
indices that has not yet made that new
alltime high. You know, could we see it?
You know, we' be looking for that
$50,000 mark. And the next notable area
again is that 53,000 that we've uh that
I've had my eyes on for quite some time.
We kind of front ran it over here. Uh so
we'll be looking to see if we get that
out of the Dow. But so far uh both the
uh S&P and the NASDAQ have made that
move up. And as far as Bitcoin goes,
again, 75,000 is a huge huge, you know,
area that I want to see uh just flipped
on a one daily candle above 75K. And
honestly, the fireworks can really get
going there. And as far as coinciding
with micro strategy because a lot of
times what we see out of micro strategy
does correlate sometimes it's it's not
like a guarant it's it's not a 100%
correlation I guess but um usually when
Bitcoin is doing well Micro or I guess
usually when Micro Strategy is doing
well Bitcoin is doing well and vice
versa and Micro Strategy also has a
major bullish setup here I mean that is
again been printing since February or
January of 2024
uh with our current low here around that
$100 zone. So, two years a two-year uh
setup that has been, you know, basically
in the cards here uh with a couple of
major targets. One of which is back up
here about 223 to 250. All right. And
again, I want to highlight that this is
a 2-year, you know, setup. I don't
expect this overnight. Fun fact, last
time I said that uh about something, we
actually got it overnight. So, we'll
see. But that aside, but truly, like,
let's look at this, you know, neutally
here. 140. What is it? 141 is truly that
level. We've been flirting with it for
for what feels like weeks down here. Uh
a true blue close, a decisive close
above 141. And I think that the marched
back towards 220 to 250 on Micro
Strategy begins. Uh which is a sizable
move, right? And again, I don't expect
this overnight about 70% there. And uh
I'm I'm assuming that that'll correlate
into Bitcoin as well, which leads into
my $93,000 target on on Bitcoin if we
get above 75K. So yeah, I think that uh
things are just aligning here really
well. Um do want to kind of state, you
know, not to get overly bullish at this
exact moment because that is we are at
places where we could see sharp
pullbacks shortterm. Um you know, we
don't want to get really bullish into
major resistance on Bitcoin as we are
trading at 75,000 that key level. So we
could still see small pullbacks back to
70,000 again uh before we you know fully
get through there if we're going to
push. So, it's it's just a time to again
not not secede to any type of uh FOMO or
anything like that. Just kind of take a
step back, you know, view the market as
it is. Uh and then interesting times uh
nonetheless here, right? So, we'll see
how everything kind of plays out uh as
we enter into the weekend. So, overall,
when I step back and look at everything
right now, Bitcoin, equities, and the
broader market structure, this just
doesn't look like weakness like really
anywhere to me. So, uh it looks like
positioning. And if it continues to
hold, I do think that there's a real
case for further upside that most people
just really aren't prepared for. But as
always, I'm not trying to predict the
market. I'm trying to be prepared to
react to what the market gives us. So,
uh, that's what I'll be watching. This
is how I'll be viewing the market in in
the coming days, and I'll keep you
updated here on the channel if anything
does change. If you found this helpful,
be sure to subscribe to the channel if
you haven't done so already. Please give
us a like on the video. It helps us to
distribute uh this information to other
traders and investors such as ourselves.
And if you would like to go deeper, I do
post daily setups and market breakdowns
inside the market intel community. And
that you can find that available at our
website data-pro.com.
I appreciate you all for watching. As
always, thank you all so much for tuning
in. I'll see you all on the next video.
And until then, everybody, cheers.