Everyone has been extremely bearish on
Bitcoin and that's exactly why it's
about to move much higher. Now, ever
since the 6th of February, over two
months now, when Bitcoin came down to
59, $60,000 depending on exchange, we've
been trending sideways, putting in a
huge series of higher lows across the
way here with multiple attempts at this
$75,000 area. Again, $75,000 being a key
region as it is a high time frame
average uh for this quarter, which was
very likely to be met during quarter 2
of this year, which is now. Now, short
term, can we reject off this region?
Absolutely. This is still a major area
of resistance where we're running into
right now. So, we can't get overly
bullish right at this exact moment,
brand new. Of course, that's where you
want to be looking around these lows and
building your strategy and plan at that
point. The next region of confirmation,
however, is if we actually flip $75,000,
which is basically going to mean that
we're going to flip 90-day average. So,
many people will look at the 200 day,
the 50-day moving averages. This is a
90-day non-moving average, but still an
average of price. And it's very simple
here. Bearish below and bullish above.
So flipping $75,000 on a b on a daily
basis here is going to in turn mean that
we will be looking for sizable upside to
continue from here. Now, where Bitcoin
could head after $75,000 is the
question. And one thing that I've been
tracking since we put in this low here
at uh $60,000 is this bullish setup
called the shark. It is a harmonic. It
is a sequence of Fibonacci which has
very specific ratios, very specific
targets uh and rules that accompany it.
And this is one of the most perfect as
far as timing goes uh and as far as
sentiment goes, right? We had nice
extremes down here, right? Very fearful
at these lows. Every single low has been
an extreme fear at this point. Uh which
sets us up just for an simple sentiment
run. I say that because the shark is a
huge setup that runs off of emotion. You
take the highs, you take the lows, you
wipe out everybody, and you get
everybody very emotional along the way.
You have these long drown out ranges
that occur at the lows or the highs as
well. From this setup here, we are
targeting as long as this low is held at
60K, we are looking for a runup to about
$93,000 in Bitcoin in the coming weeks
and months. 75,000, however, is the key
for more upside. This is why I focus on
positioning folks, not just reacting.
And part of that is using platforms like
iTrust Capital. I've used this platform
for many years for tax advantage crypto
investing. And if you'd like to try them
out, you can get a $100 bonus with the
link in our description