The crypto market is celebrating and
it's all because of one reason, the S&P
500 has hit a new all-time high. We know
there's correlation between stocks and
Bitcoin. At the top is the S&P 500, at
the bottom is Bitcoin. Both tend to
bottom out at the same time, both tend
to top out at the same time and now we
have a nice stock rally fueled by a
potential easing of the Iran conflict.
And so risk-on assets go up, altcoins go
up. But the question is for how long?
This year comes from Glassnode. It shows
the realized price, the true market
mean, the active investor mean, and the
short-term holder realized price. There
are many resistances close to the 80K
mark. Let's have a look at the
short-term holder cost basis or the
realized price in a bit more detail. It
tends to be a somewhat reliable support
during a bull market and resistance
during a bear market. We have bounced
off that resistance in the middle of
January of this year. And again, now
that resistance is at 80K or to be a bit
more specific, $80,896.
When we look at the number of short-term
holders in profit or in loss, that's
very much balanced right now. The
overall average cost basis, so the
overall realized price is still below
the current price though. That's at
$54,000.
And in prior bear markets, we tended to
fall below that price level before we
could turn around. So what is it? Will
altcoins continue to rally because the
S&P 500 goes up more or do we face
massive resistance and are we in for
another sell-off and do we have to come
below that realized price first? Have a
look at the realized profit and loss
ratio. So this is a 30-day exponential
moving average. We tended to fall in the
negatives, in the red at the end of
every bear market. We have already
fallen below it this time, but note how
in the past we also had our fake outs.
We had more loss realization than profit
realization over here and over here, but
subsequently Bitcoin still fell from 50K
all the way to 15K. So this signal
unfortunately is not very reliable. What
signal is reliable though? Let's have a
look at the perfect golden cross or
death cross. I've made an analysis for
Bitcoin. I checked all the different
combinations for a shorter term and a
longer term moving average. I tried to
figure out what's historically the best
for Bitcoin. Some moving average
combinations work better than others.
The best combination is over here, the
two-day with the 116-day
simple moving average. If you take a
fixed betting price, this is how our
equity line develops over time. So it's
a very nice constant winner. And while
we have already crossed the 116-day
simple moving average with the price, we
have not yet crossed it with the moving
average. So that's why the backtests are
useful. If we stay at our current price
level today on the 18th of April and we
close the day, UTC time zone, midnight
at that price level, then the moving
averages will cross. We've got a golden
cross and that would be bullish. But
there might also be the slight risk that
today isn't that bullish, that we sell
off again and then we get rejected one
more time. This is an extremely close
call. We had that close call on the 26th
of October of last year. We had that
again in the middle of January of this
year and now it's yet another major
decision that's going to be made over
the course of the next hours. Here's how
much that strategy of the two-day and
the 216-day simple moving average
outperformed just buying and holding. We
move from 21% per annum, so we start the
backtest in 2018 to 152%
per annum. The maximum drawdown is
comparable though, the maximum drawdown
duration is not. We do have some
volatility because we do introduce some
leverage as well. This is the optimal
leverage, 2.5x long and 2x short. And if
you're wondering how often does this
strategy change positions, on average
it's every 60 days. We can also look at
how well does this work over time
because this year is for the entire data
set, from the beginning of 2018 to
today. But here is what that looks like
over time. So this is our selected
moving average combination and the star,
that shows during a particular four-year
period what was the best combination at
the time. So we go here with half-year
increments. We look at four-year
windows. We check what was the best
golden and death cross for Bitcoin. And
we do see that for the majority of the
time, this particular combination is
actually not that bad. So I continue to
use it. It's actually not just
simulations. We started trading that
strategy in October of last year. We are
up somewhere around 5 to 10% while
Bitcoin during the same time period lost
37%. So again, we've got our
outperformance to a similar degree as we
expected with the backtest. Here's where
we started. Here's where we are now. And
interestingly enough, the current
resistance that we already see in the
short-term holder price level and that
we see here [snorts] with our backtest.
We can even see this in the trend
channel, in those two parallel lines.
Those lines have been drawn quite a
while ago. The Bitcoin price respected
it and so let's just see what happens
today. If we suddenly sell off and we
should continue to stay bearish or if we
suddenly break out and things become
very bullish. We might just stay at the
current level. That would already be
enough to satisfy the condition to buy
according to the best moving average
combination. So if you want to be part
of the Bitcoin trend follower, that's
over here. Automatic copy trading,
that's for the premium members. There's
also a similar trend follower for
Ethereum and for Solana. And there's
another one where we bet on altcoins
long-term to underperform. That's a
strategy that's independent of market
movements. Since the beginning of the
year, it's up roughly 10% and it's also
in line with our expectations, which is
44% per annum. So everything is going
according to plan. We will get a
decision very soon. We will see whether
or not the crypto market will freak out
about those high prices and take profit
or if it's open to continue to get
carried by traditional finance, to
continue to emulate the gains that are
being made in the stock market. If you
got some value out of this video, feel
free to give it a like. Feel free to
also subscribe. I publish videos
regularly on this channel. You can also
check out the premium membership. Again,
this is where you can join the copy
trading. You can also get access to the
analytics platform and create your own
backtests as well. So that's when you
want to dive a little bit deeper and
refine your altcoin trading. Thanks for
watching and see you next time. Bye-bye.