This market is fascinating. In the
short-term, there's a lot of noise. Some
altcoins are going up, others are going
down. This is true for the daily, the
weekly, and the monthly performance.
Once we zoom out for 1 year, there are
only very few winners. Check out the
performance in the last year uh based on
market cap. It was only the largest
market caps, 1 to 200, that were able to
make money on average. The rest all
lost. Now, this video is about Bit-
Tensor. Again, there was already a video
published 2 weeks ago. And just
yesterday, we had another mention of
Bit-Tensor Tao by a Jason Calacanis on
the All-In podcast. So, he's got an
investment in the project and he's
trying to push the token. Now, I don't
believe in marketing hype, I don't
believe in narratives, I believe in
numbers. And that prior video on this
channel,