This seems to have been a quite obvious
omission. RAVE DAO has rallied massively
in the last week and the question is how
much longer can this rally last? Who is
buying here? Who is selling here? Let's
have a look at the on-chain data, the
data most people are not considering.
Try to figure out how we can time RAVE
DAO. The token climbed into the top 100
cryptocurrencies in terms of market cap.
It appreciated by almost 6,000%
in a week. And that's then the resulting
chart. It's pretty much a hockey stick.
We are now close to $16.
And 2 weeks ago, we were at 25
cents. Now, on Ethereum, there are
11,000 holders. On the base chain, there
are 12,000 holders. And on the Binance
Smart Chain, there are 27,000 holders.
It is interesting to look at the number
of holders over time. Now, this is
Ethereum on the left side. We've got the
number of wallets here.