Zcash is one of the top performers this
week. The question is why? Who is buying
here? Who's selling here? Let's have a
look at the on-chain data, the data most
people are not considering to try to
figure out how much longer this rally
might last. Now, the main reason for the
price rally in the last 24 hours is
derivatives pressure. So, that's buying
and selling of the asset via bets on the
price, via perpetual futures. If you
bet, say, $100 with 10x via the perps,
we move $1,000. If we say buy for those
$1,000, the market cap goes even up by
more than $1,000. So, there are two
types of leverages here, the leverage
through the perpetual futures and the
leverage through liquidity that pushes
up market cap even more. Have a look at
the trading volume. On the spot market,
we had 192 million worth of trading
volume on Binance. On the perpetual
futures market, we had 1.3 billion,
almost 10 times of what happens on the
spot market. So, really, the perps are
driving the price, and what do we see
recently? We're seeing a short squeeze.
There are more people betting on falling
prices than on rising prices. That's why
the funding rates are currently
negative. It's very popular to bet on
falling prices of Zcash. And at the same
time, the number of bets on the price
went up. So, have a look at this. This
is open interest in green. How many bets
are currently made on Zcash? It's close
to 600 million now. But, check how much
this correlates with the price as well.
When there are more bets on Zcash, then
the price tends to go up. When there are
less bets on Zcash, the price tends to
go down. So, really, the derivatives
market is driving the price. That's not
necessarily true for every asset. For
Bitcoin, for example, the perpetuals are
not the primary driver, but for many
altcoins, they are. This is another
confirmation that we are looking at a
short squeeze. There have been a lot of
short liquidations in the last 24 hours,
more than 12 million. And on a typical
day, we tend to have less than 1
million. So, what's happening here is
that the market makers have a lot of
supply of Zcash. They are watching how
many people are currently betting on
falling prices of Zcash. And if there
are enough people, they could
potentially get squeezed out of the
market. Then, the market makers buy up
on the spot market and squeeze all of
those perps out, make liquidation fees
in the process. Now, there are many ways
to look at the data of an asset. This is
what most people do. It's just a linear
scale. It's the asset measured in US
dollars. But, at least, we should change
to a logarithmic scale, so that then we
get an impression of how percentage
changes move over time. In the end, we
are interested in percent gains, not
necessarily in US dollar prices. On a
linear scale, we really have no idea
about percent changes. This here is a
300% change, while the same delta higher
on the chart is only a 15% change.
Really, at least, we should change to a
logarithmic scale. But, the better way
is to not just change to logarithmic,
but also to compare Zcash to a
benchmark. Now, that benchmark can be
the others market cap, so the entire
altcoin market cap. It could also be
Bitcoin, as long as we know how one
asset is performing relative to the
rest, we get a much better idea of
what's specifically going on with that
asset because of all the correlation,
right? When Bitcoin goes up, all the
altcoins go up. When Bitcoin goes down,
all the altcoins go down. But, the
relative performance is what matters.
So, here's Zcash relative to the others
market cap. It shows us that up until
the middle of 2024, it tended to
underperform very consistently. And
then, things turned around, and then we
got the massive rally starting in Q3 of
last year. Now, let's zoom into that
rally. Let's switch from a daily chart
to a 4-hour chart. And we can see that
the recent short squeeze is still within
regular volatility. The momentum has
clearly slowed down. The peak relative
to other altcoins was reached on the
21st of November, 2025. Since then,
Zcash, even with that rally,
underperformed by 45%. But, there's a
good chance Zcash still continues to
outperform until we hit the resistance.
That's another 23% from here. And that's
personally my plan. I don't want to bet
on the current rally. I think it's
better to just wait until we are very
high on the trading range, and then
trade with the general momentum. And the
general momentum is negative. Zcash has
a very hard time going beyond that level
of November of last year. Can Zcash
outperform in the very near future?
Definitely. Will it outperform in the
next months? Probably not. This year was
already a short squeeze-driven rally,
and that might continue for a bit
longer. But, short squeezes deflate
after a while. The market makers do have
to sell the spot holdings that they
acquired in order to initiate the short
squeeze in the first place. If it's your
very first time here, feel free to
subscribe. I publish news regularly. A
like would be very much appreciated as
well. It helps the channel grow. See you
next time on YouTube, or potentially see
you also in premium. This is where I
share my own trades. Thanks for
watching. See you next time. Cheers.