Now I've already talked about this in
prior videos. I like to use data to
trade assets and crypto, especially
Bitcoin, tends to move in trends. And so
a nice trend-following strategy is to
use golden crosses and death crosses. So
that's a cross of two moving averages, a
faster one and a slower one. Now most
people just randomly pick two moving
averages, say the 10-day moving average
with the 100-day moving average, and
they say, "Okay, now it's a golden
cross, now it's a death cross. Let's go
long, let's go short." But this channel
is about using data. And so what we see
here in the background, that's
simulations of buying and selling
Bitcoin using different durations for
the moving averages. Yes, granted, it's
a pretty complex chart, but the idea is
that we look at all possible
combinations of slow moving averages
here on the x-axis and fast moving
averages here on the y-axis. We look at
what kind of moving average crosses
should we use and whenever this is
green, it means this particular strategy
of two moving averages performed pretty
well. Whenever this is red, it means it
did not perform well at all. This data,
by the way, comes from Bitcoin strategy
analytics and that's the backtesting
platform available to all premium
members. And have a look at how well the
two-day combined with the 116-day
simple moving average works for Bitcoin.
Buying and holding through the time
period, so we are backtesting since the
beginning of 2018 would have given 21%
per annum. But the trading strategy
gives 76% per annum. And yes, we do have
financing fees included, so 11% and we
also have a trading fee, 0.05%.
Both of those numbers are typical for
perpetual futures exchanges. And so I've
already talked about this strategy
several times on this channel. I don't
want to repeat this too much, but there
are several buckets of information for
that strategy. And this is how the
performance looks like over time using
those golden and death crosses. And
that's without leverage and that's with
a fixed betting size. So very nice
consistent money maker. And really, the
two-day moving average is just a very
slightly smoothed version of the price
chart. So we just remove a bit of the
volatility. Right now, we are still
bearish. The two-day moving average is
below the 116-day moving average, which
by the way, is currently at a bit under
$78,000. There's also copy trading for
this particular trend-following
strategy, so for Bitcoin, but we've also
got Ethereum and Solana. The Bitcoin
trend follower made roughly half a
million so far since October of last
year. Then we try to figure out what's
the ideal leverage for the long
position, that's 2.5x. For the short
position, that's 4.5x.
But if we are a bit more conservative
with our short, we reduce the volatility
as well. That's then how the portfolio
measured in Bitcoin goes up over time.
Now why am I making this video again?
Why am I talking again about this
strategy? It's because we've got a
refinement to this chart now. This looks
at the entire history since 2018. What
crosses worked the best? But it's hard
to say, should we maybe potentially take
the crosses over here over the crosses
over here because maybe those moving
averages worked better in the recent
past. And those are just a relict of
maybe the price crosses in 2018, 2019,
2020. How did actually the
best-performing moving average crosses
develop over time? How consistent are
those results? We know that the
particular strategy has quite consistent
return, but we don't necessarily know if
the particular strategies over here
perform better in the recent past. And
so that's why there's now a new tool,
the rolling window tool. What are we
doing here? We again analyzing the best
golden and death crosses, but this time
we take a particular time window, so in
this case four years, and we roll that
time window half a year after half a
year and check the picture over time. So
does the particular strategy work better
in the early days or in the later days?
We're just rolling that performance over
time to see the consistency. And so then
we get this chart. This just shows the
performance from January 2018 to January
2022, so four years. But once we click
play, we see how this develops over
time. We're jumping half a year every
single time and we can see our selection
over here, right, the two-day and
116-day, and we can see how this
compares over time. So is this actually
the best selection over time? Now we see
here in the early days that this is
mainly the green area and we see then in
the later years how this area becomes
more profitable. It seems like in the
early days it was mainly the
shorter-term moving averages that did
well. And then as time progressed, as we
get closer to today, there's more and
more green on the right side and more
and more green here at the bottom. So I
do think, just looking at this analysis
over here, that we should rather error
on the side of longer-term moving
averages between 110
and 200 in combination with something
between 0 and 30. Again, we use this
data point over here because that's the
best over the entire time frame. That's
again this chart here. But this analysis
very nicely shows that the market does
mature over time, that things that used
to work don't necessarily always
continue to work, that as an asset
becomes more mature, becomes less
volatile, we want to also account for
that with longer time horizons. There's
also now a consistency score in the
backtester. So this strategy has a 70
out of 100. And what we see here at the
bottom, that's again four-year windows,
how was the absolute return? Here we've
got the relative alpha again for every
four-year period trading Bitcoin
according to the two-day plus 116-day
simple moving average outperformed just
buying and holding. And it outperformed
to different degrees. In the last
four-year time window, it was by 246%.
Again, right now we are still bearish
despite the recent price increase. If
you enjoy content like this, feel free
to subscribe. I publish videos
regularly. A like would be very much
appreciated as well. It helps the
channel grow. See you next time here on
YouTube or potentially even in premium
if you want to know my trades or if you
want to use the backtesting tool. Thanks
for watching and see you next time.
Cheers.