The market has been pretty brutal for
most all coins last year. But even
though Hyperliquid is an inflationary
token, it tends to see more supply over
time. The demand is growing quicker.
This is Hyperliquid's price relative to
the altcoin market cap excluding the
stable coins. Hype has just hit another
all-time high. And since the beginning
of last year, it outperformed the
altcoin market by 161%.
But it also had its volatility at
temporary drops of 50%. The question is,
is there potentially a way to time the
market for Hyperliquid? So if you are
long-term bullish on hype, you want to
accumulate, then maybe a way to get
better entry opportunities compared to
just say dollar cost averaging, compared
to just buying regularly every month. I
do like Hyperliquid quite a bit. We've
got 3 million in this vault and another
3 and 1/2 million in this vault. And
while we are trading cryptocurrencies on
Hyperliquid, the reason for the recent
growth is the adoption of traditional
finance perpetual futures. So the
trading that happens on the oil market,
trading that happens on derivatives of
the stock market and commodities in
general, that's really what's driving
the growth of Hyperliquid. Hyperliquid
is the very first case in crypto where
the technology of crypto shows how it
can be superior to traditional finance
simply because it settles very quickly,
simply because it's open 24/7. Those
differentiators help Hyperliquid getting
adoption from the regular Wall Street
guys. Now let's have a look again at a
backtest of how we can time the hype
token. So this is from Bitcoin Strategy
Analytics, our backtesting platform
available to the premium members. Here
is the hype token relative to the
cryptocurrency market cap excluding the
stable coins. We are optimizing for a
price cross relative to the simple
moving average. We are going both long
and short with an 11% financing rate.
This is the typical financing rate on
hype. And here is the best moving
average. It's the four-day SMA. Now
that's when we optimize for the
annualized return. When we optimize
instead for the Sharpe ratio, we get a
very similar outcome. Again, the
four-day SMA is the best. And that's
then how that looks like on a chart. You
would have bought on the 7th of April
and you'd be long since then. You would
be betting on rising prices since then.
Here's the alpha of that strategy.
Buying and holding hype would have given
us annualized 227%, but timing long and
short according to the four-day SMA
gives 293%.
Now it's not very common to trade that
actively. By the way, there are also
trading fees included in that
simulation. The Hyperliquid trading fees
of 0.05%
per transaction. But it's very annoying
to buy and sell that frequently. And so
an alternative approach would be just to
try to pick the bottoms and potentially
sell the tops. So whenever we fall below
the 30 threshold on the daily relative
strength index, we are buying because we
are oversold. Whenever we go above the
70% mark, we are overbought and we'd
rather get out of the market. How well
does that work? So let's run a
regression analysis again on the same
asset, the 14-day RSI. We look at the
performance in the subsequent 14 days
after such a signal. So ignore all the
signals in the middle. We just go long
when we are low on the RSI, we go short
when we are high on the RSI, and we hold
for 14 days. How well does that work?
Here is the result. So this is the RSI
value on the x-axis, so it goes from 0
to 100. That's this over here. And on
the y-axis, we've got the performance in
the subsequent 14 days. So we've got our
different data points, we've got our
thresholds. Very low RSI, very cheap
over here. Very high RSI, very expensive
over here. And everything in between.
And this orange line, that's the
regression line. So this is the line
that best represents all of those data
points. How does a 14-day holding period
on average perform in the middle and on
the left and on the right? That's over
here. The medium performance for the
oversold and the neutral area is pretty
much the same. But the overbought
performance is not good at all. In other
words, we want to stay away from hype at
least for the subsequent 14 days when
the RSI is above 70. And we're getting
very close to that value again. Have a
look at the last time we hit 70. That
was on the 18th of March. And
subsequently, the next 14 days hype went
down by almost 11%. So we are not there
yet. The moving average is of course
still bullish. But if you go up a bit
further, the asset might be heated
enough to justify rather being cautious
again. It might make sense to rather be
cautious again. Now why is this strategy
working? I think it's working because
the Hyperliquid team gets token unlocks
as well. And very likely, they are
taking profit when the hype token
comparatively speaking is rather
expensive. Why would the team take
profit when the price is very low? And
since the token unlocks happen monthly,
I think the 14-day forward-looking
return makes a lot of sense as well.
When the RSI is high, there tends to be
a lot of selling. The higher it is, the
more selling there is. And we are
potentially approaching a high level
again. But if Hyperliquid outperforms
again tomorrow and the day after
tomorrow, the data suggests that it
makes sense to lock in some profit.
Again, I don't have a crystal ball here
either. I'm simply just sharing the data
as I see it. I'm simply just sharing the
backtest. And I hope that's useful. If
you got some value out of this video,
feel free to give it a like. Feel free
to also subscribe. I publish these
regularly. If you want to get access to
the backtesting tool or if you want to
see what trades I do or if you want to
join our Hyperliquid vaults, which have
made 370k and 200k respectively. That's
over the course of the last 5 months
roughly. Then check out premium. The
link to premium pops up here on the
screen. Thanks for watching. See you
next time. Cheers.