There is this lie that everybody tells
you that you should be buying
investments. You should buy stocks
because they go up all the time because
it's a great investment. In America, for
example, here for the S&P 500. But
that's a lie because the S&P 500 goes up
due to monetary debasement. The US money
supply grows by 6.8% per annum. So this
is the S&P 500 relative to the US money
supply. If the money supply was not to
go up, if our money base was completely
flat, then the growth is extremely
modest. The growth is only 66%
over the course of 66 years. And who
knows how sustainable that growth is.
Valuations are currently very high and
during dot-com, we subsequently crashed
by 56%. And this year, that's the
dot-com bubble crash. I'm not saying
that we're going down from here, but I
just wanted to recap this very important
connection. The S&P 500 is going up over
time because the monetary base expands
over time. Now we can refine this a bit.
We're looking at US stocks and at US
money supply. Let's see how well this
holds for other markets and let's see if
we can potentially develop a trading
strategy from that or rather an
investment strategy. This here is the
European M2, EU M2, the money supply of
the Eurozone. And here is the Euro Stoxx
50. So that's a stock index of Europe.
Now have a look at this. This is the
Euro Stoxx 50 divided by the European
money supply. This chart doesn't have as
much duration compared to this one here.
This starts in 1959
for the S&P 500 relative to the money
supply, but this chart only starts in
1987,
1 year after I was born. But still, it
gives us an insight whether or not
stocks might currently be comparatively
expensive or cheap. The dotted lines
here, by the way, that's the average
ratio. Maybe that's an equilibrium
price. We could definitely make that
argument for the S&P 500 relative to the
money supply. Sometimes we're extremely
cheap relative to the equilibrium,
sometimes we're expensive. This is just
the average. So maybe this works for
Europe as well. Maybe European stocks
are currently cheap. Why don't we make a
more direct comparison? So again, US M2
relative to Europe M2. Then we're
getting this chart. Now it becomes
interesting. We've got a growth phase of
the European monetary base relative to
the US money monetary base and then
we've got a phase of a relative decline
where Europe expanded its base slower
than America. Now what impact does this
have on relative stock market
performance? That's what we see over
here. This is the Euro Stoxx relative to
the S&P 500. We can see that during a
phase where the European money supply
expanded quicker than the US money
supply, stock market performance was
relatively even. Once Europe expanded
its monetary base slower than the US,
the stock market in Europe did much,
much worse, an underperformance of 70%.
So it seems like the US has a structural
advantage over Europe. Europe can only
keep up with its stock market
performance when they are printing money
quicker. Once they don't print money as
quick or once they even get more
restrictive on monetary debasement, the
stock market collapses. Over the very
long term, Europe has a harder time.
Those two data points are also quite
comparable and of course the European
stock market did much, much worse than
the US stock market in aggregate. But
now Europe seems to start to expand its
base a bit quicker again. And so the
relative performances in the stock
market aren't that different anymore.
Now this is the entire European Union
relative to the US. Let's take the gem
of Europe. Let's take Germany. It's the
leading economy in the US. Here we do
see that German stock prices did
outperform the US stock prices during
times of expansion, but of course there
was also the underperformance. Now
there's a little hint here. Germany's
stock market actually did not do much
better than Europe as a whole. The
reason why here the German DAX relative
to the S&P 500 outperformed was not
because German investors made more
money, it was because the German stock
market is a performance index and the
S&P 500 is a price index. So in here, we
have a positive drift for German stocks
of roughly 2% per annum, right? The
dividends that get paid every single
year. So this is actually overstating
how well Germany does relative to the
US. In the end, it seems to all flow to
the US. The US market is outperforming
everything long term. So we've got the
US money supply, we've got the European
money supply. Let's see how well this
effect works with another example. Let's
have a look at the Japanese money
supply. Here is the Nikkei 225 relative
to the Japanese money supply. Here's
that average ratio, so we're very close
to the potential equilibrium. This chart
is very long in duration though. It
starts in 1960
and Japan did have a quite good run up
until the beginning of the 1990s. So
let's see what happened with the
Japanese monetary base relative to the
US monetary base. Here is the chart.
Japan expanded its monetary base very,
very quickly up until 1990. That's when
the US started printing money faster
than Japan. Now this is not just random
central bank printing because a good
chunk of the monetary base gets expanded
by people just taking loans. If you
create a business, if you buy a house
and you go to the bank and you apply for
a mortgage, then due to fractional
reserve banking, new money is created
and that expands the money supply. So a
growing economy is reflected in a
growing monetary base at least partially
as well. Now have a look at the Nikkei
225 relative to the S&P 500. When Japan
didn't expand its monetary base anymore
as quickly as it used to, the Japanese
stock market relative to the US stock
market collapsed by 93%.
And why do I find this analysis so
interesting? I find it interesting
because the trends in the relative
monetary base are somewhat consistent.
They are much less volatile than stock
prices. With stock prices, we don't
really know what's doing better and
where is the trend headed. But with
those comparisons in the monetary base,
we do see relatively constant trends and
we also see how Japan continues to
underperform with its monetary base
expansion compared to the US. So based
on this chart, I don't think the
Japanese stocks will outperform US
stocks in the next 10 or 20 years. At
least if this continues to go down,
which is probably quite likely. Again,
those are very long term trends.
Interestingly enough, Europe is a bit
more erratic in its monetary policy
relative to the US. When Europe is okay
to print more money, they can
temporarily keep up with the US. When
they don't print more money, they're
having a hard time. And currently, they
are printing slightly more money. But
again, we do know the long term trend is
very much pro US and so I do think there
is a good chance that stock market
performance and global power in general
will continue to concentrate in America.
People will continue to buy US stocks.
People will continue to buy into the
global tech monopolies and that's going
to drive economies around the globe. If
you found this interesting, feel free to
give it a like. Feel free to also
subscribe. I publish these regularly on
this channel. If you want to know how I
manage my money, what kind of
investments I do and how I trade, feel
free to also check out the premium
membership. Link to premium is down
below in the comments and here on the
screen. Thanks for watching and see you
next time. Bye-bye.