Gold has done the opposite of what
everybody was expecting. War is raging,
uncertainty is on the rise, yet gold is
selling off. Shouldn't it be the
opposite? When things get uncertain,
when oil prices go up, when risk-on
assets sell off, gold should be the safe
haven, but that's not what's going on.
The official narratives don't work
anymore. It's not when stocks are going
down that gold is going up. They we can
simply have a diversified portfolio and
something will go up all the time. Times
have changed. In this video, we're going
to look at the factors that actually
drive prices. Because from the all-time
high, gold has already lost 18% silver
has lost even 41%
and that's all happening while the oil
price increased by 84%
in the last weeks and we all know the
reason for that price increase. Here is
what I think it