Everybody looks at prices, but the real
money is made beyond this. It's made by
the people that look at the actual
forces of demand and supply. What we see
here is the Nasdaq 100 over time. It's a
very long-term chart and it tells the
story of why stock investments long-term
make sense over just holding fiat
currency. Now we can make several
adjustments to this data to make it more
useful. For example, we can look at a
logarithmic scale instead of a linear
scale. The logarithmic scale tells us
how many percent a particular asset is
growing over time. So a constant
vertical distance equates to a constant
percentage gain. That's not true for the
linear scale where we just get dollar
changes, but really we are interested in
how much percent we can actually
generate. This gives us the dot-com
crash. This gives us