Ethereum is on the edge, and most people
are not prepared of what's likely going
to come. This year is the Ethereum
dominance, and we've got clear
narratives of why Ethereum outperforms
the rest of crypto, or why it
underperforms. This year was in
anticipation of the merge, when Ethereum
moved from proof of work to proof of
stake. Once that happened, once the
tokenomics of Ethereum improved, that
was a sell-the-news event, and Ethereum
sold off much more than the rest of
crypto. And then Tom Lee stepped in. He
started buying at the historical
all-time low in Ethereum dominance. But
he slowed down his purchases since the
end of August of last year. Now, the
standard measure of Ethereum dominance
just looks at Ethereum's market cap and
compares that to the entire
cryptocurrency market cap. Now, we can
adjust