Oil just broke the system and most
people are panicking. The market is
selling off but the smart money is
already rotating into the winners.
Because here's the thing, there's always
opportunity during times of crisis. It's
not just a stock market sell-off and
everybody is losing money. Some people
are making money here. And in this video
I want to share how we can take
advantage of the current situation. This
here is the oil price on two different
measures. In green we see WTI, so the US
oil. In blue we see Brent, so that's
mainly European based. We went up
somewhere between 60 to 70% in the last
months. And while those two prices are
highly correlated, they move in the same
direction at the same time, if you're
trading very actively, there's a lot of
opportunity just from those two oil
prices. Have a look at this here. This
is WTI relative to Brent. This