The idea is simple, but it's way easier
said than done. Sell when everybody is
hyped about an asset and buy when
everybody is fearful. Now, what we see
here in this chart, that's the perpetual
market directional premium. So, the
short-term traders that are betting on
Bitcoin, they might have very high
financing costs. It costs a lot to bet
on rising prices of Bitcoin, or they
might even have negative financing
costs. They get money to bet on falling
prices. When this is high, everybody is
bullish. When this is low, the majority
of short-term traders are bearish. And
currently, we are exactly at those low
levels. Doesn't it make sense to buy
this dip now? Unfortunately, the
situation isn't always that clear. For
example, have a look at this. This is
the total supply that's currently in
loss. Met