Isn't that fascinating? We live in a
system where everybody that's working
hard, that's saving money, is forced to
become an investor. And we are all
buying into the lie. Just buy a part of
the economy and long-term you'll make
money. And the lie is very convincing.
This is the S&P 500 over the long-term.
This chart starts in the 1980s and it
tends to go up over time. But the story
that nobody is telling us that this line
going up is not a reflection of the
economy doing well. Because why then is
a shiny piece of metal, the gold price,
going up just as well? Yes, there is
geopolitical conflict right now. There's
a lot of uncertainty. People look for
safety. But I'm not talking about the
day-to-day here. I'm talking about the
long-term. This here is the US money
supply over time. And it grows by 6.8%