The longer I look at the data, the
longer I follow the official narrative,
the more I'm convinced that it's all
just a scam. It's intentionally warping
public perception. Because why?
Apparently, the economy is growing
year-over-year, yet most people feel
poorer over time. The official narrative
is that the GDP just constantly grows.
It goes up over time, people become
richer. Because what's a GDP number
really worth it when it's measured in US
dollars, and when the number of US
dollars is also growing over time. When
we are debasing the currency, it makes
no sense at all to compare the GDP, say
20 or 30 years from now, to today's GDP.
The monetary base, on average, grows by
6.8%
per annum. Now, that compounds. So, over
the course of 66 years, we now have 77
times more money floating around. When
we measure the GDP in US dollars, it's
like measuring a race with an
ever-accelerating clock. It seems like
we are faster and faster, but that's not
really what's going on. It's just the
clock ticking faster and faster. Or in
this case, the US dollar becoming weaker
and weaker. So, what does the picture
look like if we had a constant monetary
base? If the monetary base wasn't
expanding over time, how would then the
GDP develop? The answer is in this chart
here, and that's very surprising. This
is the US GDP divided by the US money
supply. And we did have some growth from
1960 to 1997. The GDP grew slightly by
23%,
but since then, since 1997,
it actually went down by almost 40%. If
the US dollar was not devalued
year-over-year, we actually would
measure lower GDP numbers. When the
publicly stated GDP is going up, it's
actually just a derivative of the US
dollar devaluing. And I don't think
that's a coincidence. I think the system
is purposely designed this way. It's
designed that way to show numbers like
this. This is the real median household
income. Real meaning we adjust for the
inflation numbers. We do have some
growth. This is by the Federal Reserve.
So, apparently, people are becoming a
bit richer year-over-year. How much
richer? On average, is 0.82%
per annum. Not a lot, but at least it's
positive. At least times should be
better today compared to say the 1980s.
Now, the inflation numbers that are
behind this calculation, they're over
here. The official stated US consumer
price index, it on average grows by 3.3%
per annum. That's the dotted line. We've
got our fluctuation. When the
fluctuation tends to go down over time,
3.3% is what happens long term. So, when
household incomes on average grow by
0.8% in real terms, in nominal terms,
they would go up by 4.1%.
So, on average, every household has 4.1%
more US dollars year-over-year, and that
gives more purchasing power of 0.8%
year-over-year because of inflation.
That's the official narrative. Now,
doesn't it feel somewhat strange that
something's expanding by 6.8% per annum,
but apparently its value is going down
only by 3.3% per annum? What I think is
going on here is that the economy became
more productive over time. So, it
becomes easier and easier to produce
consumer goods. If we had a constant
monetary base, we actually should see
prices come down year-over-year because
of technological progress, because of
optimizations. The fact that consumer
prices still go up by 3.3% every year
just [snorts] means that we print money
so quickly that it gets harder and
harder over time to keep up. We have to
ask ourselves, what's really closer to
reality? Is the money devaluing by 6.8%
because its supply grows by 6.8%? Or
should we believe the official narrative
of 3.3%?
This is very important because it's a
3.5%
delta. It's the answer if households
really grow their purchasing power by
0.8% per annum, or if they're falling
behind on average by 2.8% per annum. If
minus 2.8% is the true number, and
that's how much it gets harder over
time, that means that over the course of
40 years, there's almost a 70%
purchasing power reduction. So, 32% is
left after we compound 0.972
by 40. Now, let's have a look at the
gold price since then. It did it go up
maybe by roughly 3x? The answer is it
went up even much more than that, by
1,200%.
So, something that's supposed to hold
its purchasing power, it went up by much
more than our conspiracy theory of
actually losing purchasing power by 2.8%
per annum. Apparently, we lose
purchasing power much, much faster even
if we just measure this in gold. I think
the system is designed this way just to
keep people calm. If you tell people
that household incomes are at all-time
highs in terms of real purchasing power,
then it's all fine. Everybody is doing
all right. Yes, there might be some
imbalance in terms of wealth, but
overall, everybody is doing better.
That's the story of capitalism. On
average, it might only be 0.82%
better year-over-year, but it's still
something. It's still a graph that goes
up into the right. The government would
never show the GDP numbers relative to a
constant money supply. The government
would never tell its people that over
the course of 40 years, almost 70% of
purchasing power is suddenly siphoned
away. But what does this mean it gets
siphoned away? Who suddenly has all the
wealth? I think the system is set up
this way because there are people that
are obviously benefiting from all of
this monetary debasement. The money is
going somewhere. It's just not coming to
the average person. Your paycheck is
worth less and less year-over-year, but
your investments, they are keeping up.
There is a way to exit this insanity,
and that's to hold things that are not
the US dollar. If your salary was
measured in ounces of gold, or if your
salary was measured in parts of the S&P
500, you would be doing fine. This is
the S&P 500 relative to the US money
supply. Yes, it's not growing much, but
at least the inflation tax is completely
gone. Here is gold relative to the money
supply. Again, the same thing. It might
not long term appreciate, but at least
it keeps pace long term. And of course,
recently, it outperformed. This whole
idea of money printing, of money
creation, of expanding the monetary
base, it's all in the benefit of the few
people that own the capital, that have
the vast majority of investments. The
system is purposely designed this way,
and I don't think it's a coincidence.
It's a central banking system, and I
think people like Jerome Powell know
about this. I don't think that the
median household, the average Joe, feels
better today than say 10 or 20 years
ago. It gets harder and harder to buy a
house. It gets harder and harder just to
keep up with expenses. This is not an
individual problem. This is a broad
problem. Not just in the US, but
globally. But since we're looking at US
data, I don't think that it's a
coincidence that the birth rate is
constantly going down. It's just harder
and harder to take on this additional
responsibility. Most people want to have
healthy families. Most people want to
build lasting relationships, but very
few people are able to do that. And
purchasing power and financial security
is a strong part in that. I think this
is a global phenomenon of capitalism. It
gets harder and harder just to stay
afloat. And that's maybe also why people
get more and more picky with their
partner because they know if they don't
get a top-tier partner, it's pretty much
impossible to have a happy life. Being
average isn't enough anymore. The vast
majority is suffering more and more
year-over-year. The official narrative
is different, but I don't trust the
official narrative. I don't trust the
3.3% inflation. I think the 6.8%
inflation is much more closer to reality
because that's how quick a bar of gold
even is appreciating over time. And
nobody can tell me that a metal rock
should actually be worth more long term.
It's the same metal rock it was 100
years ago. It should have the same kind
of value. And if your thing against a
metal rock is going down long term
because that metal rock appreciates with
the monetary base. It goes up by 6.8%
per annum, and your income does not go
up. It go only goes up by those 3.3%, or
maybe by 4.1%, then obviously, things
are very much out of balance. And who's
benefiting from this? It's the people at
the center of the system. It's the
people that get very cheap access to
credit, that get money at a cheaper rate
than the 6.8% per annum, that can debase
their debt, that can grow their wealth
at the expense of the median household
that still believes they're doing okay.
And that's the interesting thing about
it because it's the vast majority of
people, 90 or 95% of households, that
are actually doing worse year-over-year.
It doesn't necessarily feel like this
compared to say the working colleagues.
It only feels like this compared to the
small elite. But the small elite is far
away. We don't really have a feeling of
how much better they are doing. We only
have a comparison with our direct
working colleagues, for example. But
obviously, when you can escape this
massive drag. So, here's the value of a
US dollar, So the inverse of the
monetary base. If you're not going down
at this pace with your purchasing power,
and if you even benefit from that, then
you want to keep that system alive. And
the issue really is that most people
that have understood how to play the
system, they normally don't talk about
this. In theory, it would be in my
interest to never talk about this,
right? When I take on cheap debt and I
buy Bitcoin and the S&P 500 and gold
with that debt and the debt devalues
much faster compared to what I pay in
interest, I make money from the system
at the expense of most other people. And
I shouldn't talk about this because this
could potentially lead to a revolution
maybe even. But I think that enough
people still have sufficient purchasing
power not to revolt. People are not yet
hungry. People still have enough money
to just buy junk food and scroll on
their TikTok feed. And so they're
continuously getting exploited by the
people that actually take advantage of
the system. Again, one easy way to take
advantage of all of this is to have very
cheap credit. If you can take out a loan
and you pay less than 6.8% per annum and
you buy something that holds its
purchasing power versus the monetary
debasement, you are a winner. You're a
winner to the degree to how much
purchasing power you're generating from
those investments. You lose with your
active income because it's likely not
going to appreciate, let's say you're
employed, but you win with your
investments. And once that flips, once
your investments are large enough and
they make more from that interest rate
arbitrage relative to how much you're
losing because the income doesn't grow
as much. At that point, you become part
of the minority. Learning about
investments is not optional anymore.
This has real-life consequences. I don't
have a solution to the system, but I do
have a solution for every individual
that's willing to put in the effort to
beat the system. And with the content
here on YouTube, I try to help towards
breaking out of the system. If you got
some value out of this video, feel free
to give it a like. It helps the channel
grow. Feel free to also subscribe. I
publish videos regularly. See you next
time here on YouTube or potentially also
see you in the premium membership. This
is where I share my own trades. See you
next time. Cheers.