Here is the common narrative that
everybody is telling you. Forget about
timing the market. Just buy, say, into
the S&P 500 every single month
irrespective of price. Buy $100 every
month and over the long term you will
make money. While this is true because
the US dollar is devaluing over time,
this does generate returns, it's not
necessarily ideal. We can tweak this a
little bit. We can have a fixed rule how
we put some variety into the purchases.
We don't buy $100
every month, when the market is cheaper,
we buy a bit more. Maybe when the market
is expensive, we buy a bit less. Now,
this rule has to be extremely simple.
And in this video, I've run simulations.
I've tried to figure out how can we
potentially optimize buying into the
market regularly. So, here's what I've
done. This comes from Bitcoin strategy
analytics. That's the platform available
to the premium members of this channel
and there's a tool called dollar cost
average optimization. So, that's a tool
trying to figure out how much we can
potentially outperform just simple $100
purchases, in this case, monthly. And
so, we've got a very simple approach. We
buy more when we draw down from the
all-time high. Now, all-time high is an
exaggeration here. We just look back for
the last 10 years. If the current price
is close to the highest price in the
last 10 years, we buy less. If it's
close to the lowest price in the last 10
years, we buy more. And this is then how
that looks like over time. We've got the
S&P 500 at this point, white line, and
we've got a buying indicator. How much
should we buy? We buy more when we have
crashed in the last 10 years. We buy
less when we have hit a new all-time
high. So, when we put a bit of variation
into our buying, how does this actually
affect performance? So, let's have a
look. Constant dollar cost averaging,
that's the line in gray. Dynamic dollar
cost averaging, so adjusting our
purchases based on how much we have
drawn down from the highest price in the
last 10 years, that's the line in
orange. So, how many S&P 500 shares have
we accumulated over time? This year is a
very long-term simulation. It starts in
1950. So, this is 80 years of data and
maybe that's not necessarily
representative because the market has
changed over the decades and also there
might be an impact of whether or not we
start our simulation at a very high
price point or at a very low price
point. Now, in this video, I want to be
as objective as possible and so let's
run through the different scenarios.
What happens when we use dynamic dollar
cost averaging and we start at the
height of a bull market versus, say, at
the bottom of a bear market? And how
does this develop over time long term?
But again, let's go back to the 80-year
simulation. If you bought over 80 years
$100 every month, you would have
invested $91,000
and you come out with 5.8 million.
That's for dynamic dollar cost
averaging. With constant dollar cost
averaging, we are at 5.1 million. So, a
difference of 700k or 13%.
Now, nobody has a time horizon of 80
years, but at least it gives us an idea
of what the potential difference can be
over the market cycles. So, in general,
dynamic dollar cost averaging seems to
outperform just fixed dollar cost
averaging and this is a very simple
trading rule. We can get more advanced
if we wanted to, but in general, I just
want to figure out is it maybe a good
idea to not completely blindly buy, but
to buy more when we go down. Now, we can
change the adjustment. How much do we
actually want to buy when we are low
versus high? How much do we want to
deviate from the $100? I've got here a
5x maximum multiplier. So, that means
the lowest purchase is $15, the highest
purchase is a bit under $400, but it
averages out to $100. So, the amount
invested is exactly the same for dynamic
DCA versus constant DCA. That's the idea
of the simulation. But again, this is
very long term. What happens actually
when we start at different points in
time? This year is the Shiller PE ratio,
a very long-term chart. So, this shows
how expensive currently stocks are
relative to their earnings. It starts in
1871 and we could make the argument that
maybe currently we are rather high in
the price. We've got a Shiller PE ratio
that's comparable to the height of the
dot-com bubble. Then we had the dot-com
crash, then we had the global financial
crisis and then Bitcoin was born. Now,
what happens if we start our dynamic
dollar cost averaging at the height of a
bull market? So, let's start it, say, in
the year 2000, at the beginning of 2000.
So, here's the S&P 500. We are buying
quite a bit during a bear market. We
then buy gradually less as the price
goes up. And then we buy much more, in
this case, during the global financial
crisis and gradually less and less and
less. What happens then over time?
Here's the result. Constant dollar cost
averaging gives us this line in gray.
Dynamic dollar cost averaging gives us
this line in orange. So, that's the
number of S&P 500 that are accumulated.
And over the course of those 26 years,
we have 31k invested and that turned
with constant dollar cost averaging into
125k.
With dynamic dollar cost averaging, it
turned into 169k.
So, that's 44k more. That's this is
worth noting.
Now, the most important thing is to
start with investing in the first place,
right? Just $100 a month can grow into
quite a bit of wealth. 124k
for such a small contribution is not bad
and we have started at extremely high
valuations. But the optimization, I
believe, is still worth it. 35% extra or
44k, I think is pretty good. Instead of
4xing the money, we more than 5x the
money. And again, the idea is to simply
just look at the all-time high of the
S&P 500, check its price in the last 10
years and see where we currently are and
adjust accordingly. When we are very
low, we buy up to four times our $100.
If we are very high, we buy only a
quarter. So, for example, over here,
this is the S&P 500 relative to the
money supply. We just look at the last
10 years. We see where are we now
relative to those 10 years. In the
middle, we buy exactly $100. At the
bottom, we buy 400. At the top, we buy
much less. And of course, I don't know
if 10 years is optimal. Maybe we should
rather take 20 years. I also don't know
if the 5x multiplier is best or if we
should just buy, say, $200 instead of
400 at the bottom and also have less of
a reduction when we are close to the
all-time high. So, I have not run the
optimization in that regard. But in
general, being dynamic with our
purchases and buying more when we
dropped and buying less when we are
closer to the all-time high seems to
make a lot of sense. Now, let's play
with the opposite scenario. What happens
if we start our simulation at the very
bottom? So, let's say at the beginning
of 2010
when we mainly just had a bull market.
Then we get this chart over here. This
is 2010, goes all the way to today and
still dynamic dollar cost averaging it
did outperform just constant dollar cost
averaging. We are buying much less as we
hit our all-time highs, but we take
advantage of the drops, like during
COVID, and that has quite a bit of an
impact. Now, unfortunately, the impact
is less if we don't go through any major
bear market. Here, the outperformance is
only 5% for dynamic dollar cost
averaging versus constant dollar cost
averaging. Roughly 20k had been invested
and instead of having 55k, we have 58k.
So, of course, the charm of this
strategy is to buy very aggressively in
a bear market. If we don't have a real
bear market, we never really have
depressed prices, we don't really gain
that much with dynamic dollar cost
averaging, with deviating from our $100
per month purchase. But looking at the
historical Shiller PE ratio, I wouldn't
be surprised that at some point we do
get again a bear market. I think this
simulation here, starting in the year
2000, is probably closer to reality
compared to the simulation starting in
2010. We are probably rather expensive
right now. We are closer to this
scenario than we are to this scenario.
And that means that the benefit from
dynamic dollar cost averaging is quite
high. Again, this was 35% more return.
We should, thus, if we take those
numbers seriously, buy less month over
month when we are still close to the
all-time high and we should buy more and
more aggressively as the S&P 500 drops.
And if it doesn't drop, we just continue
to just buy a little bit every month. We
dollar cost average less aggressively.
Now, in this simulation, we just talk
about the buying more versus buying
less, but we can actually take this a
step further and I'm considering to make
an analysis, a quantitative analysis on
this as well. We could simply look at
the asset that has dropped most from the
all-time high and buy more into that.
So, let's say we invest $100 and we
split those $100 between stocks, between
gold, between Bitcoin, between all kinds
of things and then we just buy more
aggressively into the thing that has
dropped more. So, we always invest our
$100, but we just buy the thing that has
come down more. And of course, we have
to do this with assets that we want to
hold very long term, where we do believe
they have an extremely high chance of
still being relevant, say, in 20 or 30
years. Maybe we should not start dollar
cost averaging in more aggressively as
prices come down into a random altcoin,
for example. We want to be very
selective in where we dollar cost
average in. But for the assets that we
want to hold long term, that suddenly
drop from the all-time high, it might
make sense to buy more and more. A
simple dynamic dollar cost averaging
strategy works very well for the S&P
500, especially if you are are
high in valuations. But it also works
over the very long term for 80 years of
data, and the harm isn't too bad if
you're always just going up, and our
price corrections aren't really that
significant as happened since 2010. So,
I think the risk to reward is worth it.
And again, we can just play around with
different asset classes, and then buy
the thing that drops most. If you got
some value out of this video, feel free
to give it a like. It will help the
channel grow. Feel free to also
subscribe. I publish videos regularly.
If you want to get access to the
backtesting tool, that's available to
the premium members, link is over here.
Thanks for watching. See you next time
on YouTube, or see you in premium.
Cheers.