Let's be honest, nobody knows where the
Bitcoin price will go. We're all just
guessing. We try to draw parallels from
the past. We're trying to find structure
in the data. And while we can't be
certain about anything, there are some
good arguments that we might have
already bottomed in Bitcoin. One of the
best arguments is over here. It's the
weekly RSI. What we see at the top,
that's the Bitcoin price. What we see at
the bottom is the weekly relative
strength indicator. And in the past,
when we went into this oversold
territory, we tended to also bottom out
in the Bitcoin price. And we have just
hit a low in the weekly RSI again. And
so there are always those two competing
forces. There's the valuation of an
asset and there's the current momentum.
If momentum is negative, if the trend is
currently bear