Pepe isn't just a meme coin. Pepe truly
shows how the market psychology is
behaving. In this video, we're going to
look at the data. We skip the hype.
We're trying to figure out where the
price is headed from here because there
are some indications that Pepe might
actually see a quite quick rally in the
near future. Now, of course, there's a
lot of correlation in crypto. When
Bitcoin goes up, many altcoins go up.
When Bitcoin crashes, most altcoins
crash. And that's why I think it's very
important to look at relative
valuations. How is an altcoin doing
relative to all the other altcoins? Is
it currently outperforming? Is it
underperforming? Is it really worth the
risk to get into something like a
mid-cap meme coin? What we see over
here, and that's the Pepe price relative
to the altcoin market cap. So, this is
not a US dollar price. This is relative
performance. We have seen a very quick
rallies of almost 500% but we've also
seen devastating crashes lasting almost
an entire year and bringing Pepe down
relatively speaking 90% Since the middle
of 2024, we are in a somewhat constant
trading range. Every now and then, we
see very quick price appreciations then
follow with slower price bleeds. Now,
what I think is going on here is that a
lot of people bet on falling prices of
Pepe or maybe people simply take profit
over time. But every now and then, we
see those quick rallies. That's maybe to
liquidate all the shorts, to liquidate
all the people that are betting on
falling prices. Market makers just buy
up the supply very quickly, move the
price so quickly that nobody can react
to those movements. Because have a look
at this. This is the open interest, the
amount of bets that are currently made
on the Pepe price. This topped at 1
billion dollars in the middle of last
year. And currently, it's rather at a
low level, below 200 million. Why does
this matter? It matters because there's
correlation between the price of Pepe
and the open interest. When open
interest goes down, the price tends to
bleed. When open interest goes up,
there's a chance for a price rally every
now and then. Now, there has been a
change in the funding rates for Pepe in
the last few weeks. And this does matter
because it indicates that now there's
potentially more and more retail
investors betting on falling prices,
which could again induce a short
squeeze, a very quick rally in the
price. Pepe is among the most viewed
cryptocurrencies and it's the fourth
largest meme coin in terms of market
cap. Still, its market cap is 1.4
billion. Number one is Dogecoin with 14
billion. So, that's potentially another
10x if Pepe was to flip Doge, which
isn't very likely but still, it gives a
reference point how much maximum upside
there might be. Now, I like to use
trading rules. I like to determine the
best trading rule for an asset because
following the narrative of the day,
following the news of the day, that's
usually not quick enough. Very often
when a narrative is out, the price has
already adjusted. But using statistical
methods to trade an asset removes all
the emotional component. It makes
performance more consistent. What we see
over here, that's the best moving
average backtest for Pepe, which is the
80-day simple moving average. The idea
is that we buy whenever we are above the
moving average, we sell or bet on
falling prices whenever we are below the
moving average. Have a look at the Pepe
price at the top and at the performance
using that strategy with a fixed betting
amount. We can time the market quite
well this way and we have included
trading fees in this analysis as well.
There is 0.05% trading fees. That's the
typical perpetual futures swap fees
without discount and we've got 11%
financing fees. So, that's for the long
side, you pay 11% per annum and you get
11% per annum if you short, if you bet
on falling prices. That's typically what
happens with large perpetual futures
platforms like hyperliquid, for example,
or Binance. Currently, we are above that
80-day simple moving average. So, that's
our first positive sign. But we can take
it a step further. We can look at the
best combination of two moving averages
and that usually tends to outperform
simple price crosses. So, we look for
the best golden cross, we look for the
best death cross. But we have to figure
out what's the best moving average
combination for that strategy, again
based on data. And here is the result.
So, on the x-axis, we've got the slow
moving average duration. On the y-axis,
we've got the fast moving average
duration. And the best combination is
over here. That's what has created most
return. So, let's have a look at the
numbers over time. Buying and holding
Pepe over the time period would have
given us 140% per annum with a lot of
volatility. So, that's 169% volatility
and the maximum drawdown of 88% but have
a look at the golden and death cross
strategy using the 6-day and the 9-day
simple moving average, the best
combination. It gave a much lower
maximum drawdown, only 55%. It gave us
less volatility and it gave us an
annualized return of almost 500% every
single year. And that's then how this
looks like over time. Again, that's with
fixed bet sizing. So, if you get a buy
signal, we bet, say, $10,000. If you get
a sell signal, we short with $10,000
irrespective
of our portfolio size. This tends to
reduce volatility quite nicely. The
problem, of course, is that our capital
doesn't really compound and we are also
not using optimal leverage. But let's
talk about this in a second. Let's first
look at where we currently are. When the
shorter-term moving average in orange is
above the longer-term moving average,
then we are long. And when orange is
below blue, then we are short.
Currently, orange is above blue. So, we
are long and the cross happened on the
3rd of April. Let's optimize leverage.
So, for the long side, that's 2x. For
the short side, that's 1x. The long side
gives us much more return than the short
side. So, the leverage on short isn't as
important. We might as well just go in
cash whenever we have seen a death
cross. Still, it's good to know that we
can go all the way up to 2x for trading
Pepe with that approach. When we then
include compounding, so we bet our
entire portfolio and we do this with a
2x leverage, then we get the following
return, much more volatile but also much
higher. Of course, we don't want to do
this with all of our capital but it's
one of the riskier positions. The equity
is in blue, buying and holding Pepe is
in gray. The portfolio measured in Pepe
tokens is here in purple. So, pretty
much every year, we tend to have more
Pepe tokens than the year before. What's
the annual alpha? It is massive. But
again, this is extremely risky. We are
going 2x long with the entire stack.
Again, buying and holding gave us a bit
under 140% per annum but trading the 6-
to 9-day golden and death crosses with a
2x long and 1x short gave us more than
1,000%
every single year. Our maximum drawdown,
unfortunately, also becomes very similar
to buying and holding. So, this is
definitely at least as risky as buying
and holding Pepe for the long term. This
is not a risk mitigation strategy. This
is a return maximization strategy. But
the returns can be very nice, right? The
best year in 2024 made more than a 40x,
4,000% return. Holding Pepe directly
only gave a bit over 14x. So, a bit over
1,000% return. Now, all of those numbers
are extremely impressive and of course,
it doesn't look very realistic that
those rules will perform just as well in
the future. But I still think that if
something traded in a particular
pattern, in a predictable pattern in the
past, that at least this will to degree
also reflect in the future. Maybe it
won't be thousands of percent every
single year but maybe a few hundred
percent, that wouldn't be too bad. I
don't even think that the 2x leverage is
too problematic because Pepe is very
likely less volatile today than it was
in the early days. And we are looking at
the entire price history here. So, let's
say we are really bullish. Let's say
both the golden cross and the price
cross strategy, since they are both
optimistic about Pepe, what would be our
upside in the very short term if we
entered with 2x leverage? Here, I think
is the answer. We have seen already a
similar short squeeze at the beginning
of the year. And we started the video
with the negative funding rates. So,
many people currently betting on falling
prices. If we see another similar short
squeeze, the price could very easily
increase by 60% and then doing a 2x
leverage on that more than doubles the
capital. Now, I don't have a crystal
ball either but I do think that the
setup looks quite interesting, again,
for risk-on capital. If you're trading
meme coins anyway and you're okay with
the volatility, you're okay to see a
position go down temporarily by 80 or
90% and maybe now is a potentially good
entry opportunity because again, the
momentum seems to currently be turning
around. There are a lot of bad signals
with this strategy as well but at least
historically, it tended to outperform
buying and holding Pepe quite
consistently. Again, this year is the
portfolio line measured in Pepe. Now,
the platform that we are looking at
here, that's Bitcoin strategy analytics.
So, it's a backtesting platform
available to all premium members of this
channel. You can also set up alerts. So,
let's say you want to get an email
whenever a buy or sell signal is
triggered with a strategy, you can just
click over here. You can also get
signals via Telegram. The signals also
send the corresponding chart. And I'm
using this for several strategies
already. Here are some strategies for
Bitcoin, Ethereum and Solana and the Bit
Tensor. and the community of course has
also created quite a lot of interesting
results. If that sounds like too much
effort, there's also automatic copy
trading. So for the Bitcoin trading
strategy, we created a copy trading
vault half a year ago. It's already up
by 600k. So yeah, let's see where Pepe
is going from here. If you got some
value out of this video, feel free to
give it a like. It will help the channel
grow. Feel free to also subscribe. I
publish here as regularly. See you next
time on YouTube or see you potentially
also in premium. Cheers.