Crypto has been around for many years
now, and I find it interesting how still
today very few people actually look at
relative valuations. Is Ethereum
expensive? Is it cheap? It's not visible
in US dollar charts, because in US
dollar charts we just get the general
ups and downs of the market. But here we
see Ethereum's market cap relative to
the altcoin market cap excluding the
stable coins. So this is total three ES,
and this trades in a range. This is a
chart that starts in 2017. We have an
upper bound, we've got a lower bound,
and we've got the average ratio
indicated as this dotted line. Is
Ethereum currently expensive? Is it
currently cheap? At least relative to
the altcoin market, it's very close to
balance with currently positive
momentum. How much more potential upside
do we have?