And this is one of the concerns that I
have about the doomers describing the
end of work and killing of jobs. If we
discourage people from being software
engineers, we're going to run out of
software engineers. And uh the same
prediction 10 years ago, some of the
doomers were saying that whatever you
do, don't be a radiologist. Radiology is
is going to be the first career to go.
The world's not going to need any more
radiologists. Guess what? We're short of
radiologists. If we scare this country
into thinking that AI is somehow a
nuclear bomb so that everybody hates AI,
if we scare everybody out of doing
software engineering jobs because it's
going to kill every software engineer
job and we don't have any software
engineers as a result of that, we're
doing a disservice to United States. We
misunderstand the difference between a
job and the task the job of a
radiologist patient care task to read a
scan. If we misunderstand that so
profoundly, we're not going to have
enough radiologists and good enough
healthcare.