Alpha really isn't about AI. A massive
fraction of the success there is the
protein data bank. So it's it's X-ray
defraction, it's NMR, it's cryom, and
the several billion dollars that was
spent obtaining whatever it's 180,000
odd struct protein structures. It's
basically the story of we spent many
many decades obtaining protein structure
just by going out and looking very hard
at the world experimentally and then we
fitted a nice model at the end of it and
that was like a tiny fraction of the of
the entire investment. But it's
definitely not you know that's a story
of data acquisition principally. It's
not only I mean the AI bit is very very
impressive.