Astrology was very important for a very
long time. People like Galileo and and
Kepler made some of their money much
more from their astrological work than
than they did from their scientific
work. And it was important often to you
to to kings and sort of other uh very
very important people. They would have
court astrologers and so astronomy
actually kind of you maybe it's
developing for that reason. To your
point, the Danish government was
spending 2% of its annual government
budget on funding Taiko Brahi's
observatory, which then obviously led to
all this data that Kepler used. Um, also
Kepler was employed as the imperial
astrologer for the Haspber. I mean, what
is 2% of the US GDP? What is that? What
do we do with 2% of our GDP? The reason
all this is saying was literally am I
going to win the next battle? Who should
I marry? or whatever these kinds of
questions, it's like why our
understanding of the solar system was
revolutionized.