Darwin's theory, the theory of natural
selection, is conceptually easier than
the theory of gravity. There there was
this contemporaneous biologist with
Darwin, Thomas Huxley, who read this and
said, "How extremely stupid to not have
thought of this. God, why didn't I beat
you to the punch here?" No. And so,
yeah, what's going on here? Why Why did
Darwinism take so much longer? It's not
actually that the idea was hard. It's
not even that the idea was really
entirely new. It was that actually he
had something different to do than
Newton had to do. He spent 5 years on
the Beagle. He endured, I mean, terrible
terrible trials. And and then took
decades more work for him to assemble
all of the evidence. It's just a It's a
different kind of a project, and it is
also extraordinarily hard in its own
way, even though it sort of It appears
simpler to have the idea. Yeah, I mean,
I'm sort of punting on the on the
question. I'm I'm just I am pointing out
that it is It is maybe a lot harder than
it necessarily appears.