Gauss
>> [music]
>> was interested in the prime numbers, and
he computed the first 100,000 prime
numbers or so hoping to find patterns.
>> [music]
>> And he did find a pattern, but maybe not
not the pattern he was expecting. He He
found a statistical pattern in the
primes that that if you count how many
primes there are up to 100, 1,000, 1
million, and so forth, they get sparser
and sparser. So, he conjectured what we
now call the prime number theorem.
The number of primes up to X is like X
divided by the natural log of X, and
[music] he had no way to prove this. It
was data-driven. It didn't tell you
exactly how many primes there were in
any given range. It just gave you an
approximation that got better and better
as you went further and further [music]
out. It was the first in many
conjectures like this, which sort of
started consolidating the idea that the
prime numbers actually didn't really
have a pattern. And this allowed us to
make all these other predictions. So,
there's a still open conjecture in in in
number theory called the the twin prime
conjecture, that there should be
infinitely many pairs of primes that are
twins, distances two apart, like 11 and
13. We can't prove that, but because of
this statistical random model of the
primes, we are absolutely convinced it's
true.
We We know that if if the primes were
sort of generated by by random chance,
it's like infinite monkeys at a
typewriter, we would see primes appear
over and over again. And we have over
time developed this very accurate
conceptual model of what the primes
should behave like based on statistics
and probability, but it's all mostly
heuristic and non-rigorous, but [music]
extremely accurate. So, we we have this
conjectural concept framework for
understanding the primes that everyone
believes in. And you know, it's the same
reason why we we believe the Riemann
hypothesis [music] is true, why we
believe that cryptography based on the
primes is basically um is mathematically
secure, things like that. It's
It's all part of this this this It is
this belief