History has always moved fast, but when
we teach it in high school, we're trying
to move over large chunks of time
quickly, and so we pretend that it moved
slowly. We have this lie that there were
long periods of stagnation. But you can
zoom in anywhere, and you're going to
find every decade feels different, and
people in the 1320s are nostalgic for
people in the 1300s, right? Right? It's
always felt like history was moving very
quickly, and things rose [music] and
things fell. It's the lies we tell
ourselves in history books written in
the 19th century that are trying to
group all of these things together and
make modernity special. They confuse us
about this.
>> Right. I I I I guess the difference is
that technologically we know that they
weren't moving as fast.
>> Technologically they were moving fast.
We just don't care about those
technologies anymore. They were
constantly inventing like all sorts of
things. We just take them for granted,
right? The invention of chairs with
backs, the invention of scissors, the
invention of improved metallurgy so that
steel could do things steel couldn't do
before. There was always technological
change happening.