Why is it the case that there's so many
different Italian polities that are
independent and going to war with each
other when around this time all the
other major European powers seem to be
more unified?
>> So two things. The first is again we
cannot [music] underestimate how much
richer per square meter
>> Italy is than everywhere else. Italy is
the bread basket and it's also the
center of big oil which is to say big
olive oil which is both fuel oil for
light and industrial oil for production
as well as cooking and eating oil. and
the other major major industry of the
period which is big wool. These are
really wealthy towns and the wealthier
you are the more coherent and internally
strong you can be. So the less
concentrated [music] population centers
of northern Europe where towns are
smaller, a smaller town is easier for
somebody who's trying to make himself
king to take over. The other half is
that it's the papacy's fault. And Rome
being present in the middle of Italy
means that every time there's a papal
election, some new family suddenly
[music] becomes powerful and the city
they're from suddenly becomes powerful.
And so there's [music] this massive
turnover of power and centralization.