I think you should discuss the fact that
the Medicis are the bankers for the
papacy. What what does that mean? Why is
that necessary? And how they're able to
make money off of that from the interest
on the float?
>> When Cosimo de Medici swings the
contract as banker for the Pope, it's
important to remember that when you
can't wire transfer money, collecting
taxes is very difficult and complicated
system. It is generally done by the
centralizing power that has the right to
tax [music] delegating somebody local
who knows. So, if you're in a town,
there'll be a local tax collector. It's
his job to go around to everybody and
collect taxes and then send a portion of
those taxes home to the central power
and keep a remainder to pay himself.
This delegate system means that you
depend a lot upon the person whose job
it is to collect your taxes. So, when
Cosimo is papal banker, he is the person
who is collecting and channeling the
money from every church in Christendom
when everybody puts a coin into a
collection box or pilgrims come and put
money. All of the wealth that's supposed
to flow back to the papacy is actually
flowing to Cosimo. Cosimo is passing it
on to the papacy after taking a cut. So,
[music] that is a lot of money moving
quickly. It is also a lot of ability to
make contracts and contacts. We all know
how important networking is. And he
rises in prominence from a banker to
somebody who has enough money to
effectively take over his state.