Machiavelli's 29 when he's made in
charge of diplomacy. How does that
happen? How's that a 29-year-old?
>> This man saw his country nearly fall six
times by the time he was 12.
>> Right. He has grown up fast and he has
grown up scared. So, he gets work as a
secretary. Machiavelli isn't the ruler.
He's at the right-hand side. He's like a
chief of staff. He's in the cabinet.
When your actual ruling council are only
in [music] office for 3 months, there's
needs to be connective tissue there. The
people who keep records of what was
going on. It takes 2 days to get a
letter to Milan and back. So, if you're
trying to negotiate a treaty with your
next-door neighbors, you're out of
office by the time you've exchanged the
equivalent of four emails. You need this
bureaucratic layer. And he is a very
smart, very effective young bureaucrat,
and he starts working in that
bureaucratic world, and soon comes to be
referred to as Soderini's lapdog.
Soderini being the man who is elected to
be the leader of that council and
effective head of state during the
iteration of the Republic that
Machiavelli [music] works for.