I believe an iPhone has 12 GB of memory.
Each gig used to cost roughly $3 or $4,
so it's 50 bucks. But now the price of
memory is like triple. Apple has to
either pass it on to the consumer, A, or
B, they have to eat it. I don't see
Apple reducing their margin too much.
Maybe they eat a little bit. But at the
end of the day, that means the end
consumer is paying $250 more for an
iPhone. But that's the high end of the
market. That's only a few hundred
million phones a year, right? Apple
sells what, two 300 million phones a
year. The bulk of the market, this
mid-range, low end, right? Uh used to be
1.4 million smartphones were sold a
year. Now we're at like 1.1. Uh but our
projections are we maybe get down to
like 800 million this year and next year
like 600 or 500 million. And we look at
like you know there's some data points
out of China. Xiaomi and Oppo are
cutting low-end and mid-range smartphone
volumes by half. Why this is like a big
deal is if smartphone volumes let's say
half the halfing will frankly happen in
the low and mid-range not in the high
end. And what this does to the market is
quite drastic right? This probably leads
to like people hating AI even more
today. Hey, you already see all the
memes like cat dancing videos and it's
like this is why memory prices is
doubled and you can't get a new gaming
GPU.