If you have a system where you lottery
people, sort is the technical term for
it. This is a very old form of
government. Ancient Athens uses it. It
actually works really well. But like any
institution, it is corruptible. And in
the same way that you can corrupt voting
by bribing people or manipulating the
machines or manipulating voters, you can
also corrupt sort by bribing the people
who pull names out of the bag or by the
simpler mechanism which Cosmo uses first
of if you're a giant big wig in the city
and you employ a third of the people in
the city and a third of the people in
the city are on your payroll and nine
guys at random are chosen out of a bag,
three of them are going to be your guys
[music] just statistically. And so if
you tell all your guys, I want this
policy, this policy, and this policy,
and if you have questions, send for me,
and I'll tell you what to do. When the
plurality on a random council all have a
plan, and it's your plan, you
effectively control the city. And so in
that way, the Medi effectively control
this lottery system because they've
guaranteed that the plurality [music]
in a situation that doesn't have a
majority will always be