when Petrarch's successors like Ficino
was young, you had to be a masterful
Latinist to read these ancients. You had
to have an enormous vocabulary. There
are no dictionaries, there are no
glosses, there's nothing to help you.
Only a tiny slice of expert [music]
classes that could actually read this
stuff. By 100 years later, there are
translations into the vernacular, there
are footnotes that tell you the hard
[music] vocabulary. Any med student can
read Lucretius's discussions of
materialist information. When Poggio
found it, there were two dozen people in
the world who could read it. A hundred
years later, 30,000 people can read it.
When all different kinds of people read
it. Med students, law students, people
in different countries, people in
different places. They ask new
questions. [music]
They wonder whether they can test the
hypotheses. They are the generation that
discovers that the heart is a pump.
They're the generation that takes
seriously the question, maybe there are
atoms and maybe that's how diseases work
and maybe we can develop the germ theory
of disease. That's the 1560s, 1580s. So,
when we get to 1600, which is almost
exactly 200 years after this begins.
[music] We've had time to say, let's
make the libraries, have the libraries,
use the libraries, realize we failed in
how we use the libraries, use the
libraries differently. And that's the
generation of Francis Bacon [music] and
Galileo, who say, "Hey, let's use the
information differently. Let's use
nature as a case book of examples the
way Machiavelli said we should use
history. [music] Let's examine, let's
doubt, let's rethink, let's do stuff in
new ways."
>> [music]