You said in the late 17th century, the
most extensive laboratory in all of
Europe is the one in the Vatican run by
the Inquisitors.
>> They decided after Galileo that they had
a duty to verify the truth of the books
that they were sent to censor and that
if people were going to be doing
mechanical experiments, they needed to
repeat the mechanical experiments to see
whether they were true. So they
effectively, the Inquisition invented
peer review,
which is to say they invented a second
laboratory trying to recreate the
results of the first.
>> It was really interesting to learn from
your book that of all the thousands of
people killed in during the Inquisition,
one guy was executed for
>> science related stuff. Yeah. And even he
had these ideas of reincarnation number.
>> So I think probably the number executed
for atheism would be about 100. Okay.
>> There are 12 total trials of scientists
about science. Galileo is one.
Jordonaldo Bruno is one. Journal. Bruno
is the only one executed.