If in 2019, Huawei was not banned from
using TSMC, they would have kept gaining
share and they'd likely be TSMC's
biggest customer. The Huawei Ascend was
like 2 months before the TPU and like 4
months before Nvidia's A100, I think.
It's very arguable that Huawei, if they
had [music] TSMC, would be better than
Nvidia. Huawei is arguably the only
company in the world that has all the
legs, right? Huawei has cracked software
engineers. Huawei has cracked networking
technologies. That's in fact their
biggest business historically, right?
But furthermore, beyond Nvidia, they
actually have better AI researchers. And
furthermore, beyond Nvidia, they have
their own fabs. They were the first with
the 7-nanometer AI chip, as well.