I think the United States ought to be
ahead. But how is shipping chips to
China keeping the US
>> no. Am I in the United States? Do you
consider me part of the United States?
Yes. You consider Nvidia a United States
company? Okay. Number one.
Why is it
that we don't come up with a regulation
that's more balanced so that Nvidia can
win around the world instead of giving
up the world? Why would you want United
States to give up the world? Dario had
this quote where he said, "It's like
Boeing bragging that we're selling North
Korean nukes but the missile casings are
made by Boeing." And that's somehow
enabling the US technology stack. Like
fundamentally, you're giving them this
capability.
>> Comparing AI to anything that you just
mentioned is lunacy. But AI is similar
to enriched uranium, right? And then it
can have positive uses, it can have
negative uses. We still don't want to
send enriched uranium to other
countries. Who's Who's sending enriched
>> The analogy of enriched uranium is like
this.
>> a lousy It's a lousy analogy.
It's a illogical analogy.
I guess that then the question comes
down to how does selling them chips now
help us win in the long term? Like Tesla
sold extremely good electric vehicles to
China for a long time. iPhones are sold
in China extremely good. Didn't cause
them lock-in. China will still make
their version of EVs and they're
dominating and smartphones are
dominating.
>> The premise that
even if we competed in China, that we're
going to lose that market anyways.
You're not talking to somebody who woke
up a loser.
And that loser attitude, that loser
premise makes no sense to me. We are not
We're not a car.
We are not a car. The fact that I can
buy a car this car brand one day and use
another car brand another day, easy.
Computing is not like that.
There's a reason why the x86 still
exists. There's a reason why ARM is so
sticky. Conceding a marketplace based on
the premise you described, I simply
can't acknowledge that. It makes no
sense.
Because I don't think the United States
is a loser. You
industry is not a loser. And that that
losing proposition, that losing mindset
makes no sense to me. Okay, I'll move
on. I just I just want to make sure that
>> have to move on. I'm enjoying it.
>> Okay, great.
>> Yeah.