The day that Deepseek comes out on
Huawei first, that is a horrible outcome
for our nation.
>> Why is that? Cuz I mean, currently you
can have a model like Deep Seek that can
run on any accelerator. Why would that
stop being the case in the future?
>> Well, suppose it doesn't. Suppose it
optimized for Huawei. Suppose it
optimized for their architecture. It
would put us at a disadvantage. You
described the situation. A company
develops software, developed an AI
model, and it runs best on the American
tech stack. I saw that as good news. You
you set it up as a premise that it was
bad news. I'm going to give you the bad
news that AI models around the world are
developed and they run best on not
American hardware. That is bad news for
us.
>> But there's a reason they're buying it
from you, right?
>> Because our chips are better. Can you
acknowledge that Huawei had a record
year? Can you acknowledge that a whole
bunch of chip companies have gone
public? Can you acknowledge that? Can
you acknowledge that? Can you can also
acknowledge that the fact that we used
to have a very large share in that
market and we no longer have the large
share in that market. We can also
acknowledge that China is about 40% of
the world's technology industry. To
leave that market, concede that market
for United States technology industry is
a disservice to our country. Your
argument starts from extremes that if we
give them any compute at all, we will
lose everything.
>> No, I think what my argument is
>> those extremes they're
childish.
>> The idea is any marginal compute is
helpful, right? So if you have more
compute, you can train a better model.
If the AI models that run on those
chips,
>> yeah,
>> are capable of cyber offensive
capabilities. It enables a weapon of a
kind.
>> The the the logic that you use, you
might as well say it to microprocessors
and DRAMs, you might as well say it to
electricity.
>> It feels like you're making two
different statements. One is that we're
going to win this competition with
Huawei because our chips are going to be
way better if we're allowed to compete.
And another is that they would be doing
the same exact thing without us anyways,
right? How can those two things be the
same at the same time?
>> It's obviously true. In the absence of a
better choice, you'll take the only
choice you have. How is that illogical?
It's so logical.
>> The reason they want NVIDIA chips is
they're better. Better is more compute.
More compute means you can train better.
>> It's better. It's better because it's
easier to program. It's e we have a
better ecosystem. Whatever the better
is, whatever the better is. And of
course, we're going to send them
compute. So what? So what the fact of
the matter is we get the benefit of
developers working on the American tech
stack. We get the benefit as those AI
models diffuse out into the rest of the
world. The American tech stack is
therefore the best for it. We can
continue to advance and diffuse American
technology. That I believe is a
positive. It's a very important part of
American technology leadership. The
policy that you're advocating resulted
in the American telecommunication
industry being policied out of basically
the world to the point where we don't
control our own telecommunications
anymore. I don't see that as smart. It's
a little narrow-minded and it led to un
unintended consequences that I'm
describing to you right now that you
seem you seem to have a very hard time
understanding.