Leonardo da Vinci was not a scientist.
And what I mean by that is that to be a
scientist is to publish your results and
share them with a community of other
scientists so that they can test them so
that the whole human civilization
progresses a little bit. What does
Leonardo do? He writes everything he
discovers down in coded mirror writing
so that nobody but him can possibly use
it. And he refuses to share even with
his students and assistants the secrets
of what he's doing. Because Leonardo
does not want to contribute to human
progress. Leonardo wants to make unique
masterpieces so that he would be
marveled at by the future exactly the
way he and his peers marveled at the
works of the ancients. And they look at
something like the Colosseum or the
Pantheon in Rome with its enormous dome
and they say, "Oh, how did they do it?
If only we could work that out. We could
make one and then make sure no one else
could." That is an inventor, but in the
sense of a community of scientists. This
is not a servant of human progress. This
is actually a sabotur of human progress.
If anything, who deliberately makes
progress and then tries to cut it off at
that point so that no one else can be
his peer.