Late in Makavel's life, he was part of
the resistance regime that ruled while
the Meduchi were in exile. They were in
power. They were kicked out. When they
returned, they viewed him as an enemy.
He is arrested, tortured, exiled. When
Florence exiles you, they tell you, "Go
to ex place and wait. Be good. Send us
letters informing us what's going on.
When we have diplomatic needs to talk to
the king, we're going to send letters to
you, and you're going to forward them,
and if you're good, you get to come
back." That's not quite what they did
with Machaveli. with Machaveli. They
banished him to a hamlet in the middle
of the Tuscan countryside near nothing
important and said, "Go sit in the
country and rot." What they expect is
that Mchaveli will break that promise
and leave. He does not do that. He stays
in the country and he rots. And he
continues writing letters home saying,
"I will serve you or nothing." That is a
weird thing to do and not normal for the
many other Florentine intellectuals who
ex experience similar banishments in the
same period. I think it's important to
remember how much he falls from power
and how much more power he could have
had in the last chunk of his life if he
had been willing to work for somebody
that isn't Florence.