Today, I'm speaking with Michael Nielsen. You have
done many things. You're one of the pioneers of
quantum computing, wrote the main textbook
in the field of the open science movement.
You wrote a book about deep learning
that Chris Olah and Greg Brockman
credit with getting them into the field.
More recently, you're a research fellow
at the Astera Institute and writing a book
about religion, science, and technology.
I'm going to ask you about none of those things.
The conversation I want to have today is,
how do we recognize scientific progress?
It's especially relevant for AI because
people are trying to close the RL
verification loop on scientific discovery.
What does it mean to close that loop?
But in preparing for this interview,
I've realized that it's a more
mysterious and elusive force,
even in the history of human
science, than I understood.
I think a good place to start will be
Michelson-Morley and how special relativity
is discovered, if it's different from the
story that you get off of YouTube videos.
I will prompt you that way,
and then we'll go in there.
Michelson-Morley is the famous result often
presented as this experiment that was done in
the 1880s that helped Einstein come up with the
special theory of relativity a little bit later,
changing the way we think about space and time
and our fundamental conception of those things.
And there's a big gap, I think, between the
way Michelson and Morley and other people
at the time thought about the experiment and
certainly the way in which Einstein thought
or did not think about the experiment.
In actual fact, he stated later in his
life he wasn't even sure whether he
was aware of the paper at the time.
There's a lot of evidence that he probably was
aware of the paper at the time, but it actually
wasn't dispositive for his thinking at all.
Something else completely was going on.
What Michelson and Morley thought they
were doing was testing different theories
of what was called the ether.
If you go back to the 1600s,
Robert Boyle introduced the idea of the ether.
We know that sound is vibrations in the air.
Boyle and other people got
interested in the question of
whether light is vibrations in something,
and they couldn't figure out what it was.
Boyle did an experiment where he
tested whether you could propagate
light through a vacuum. He found that
you could. You couldn't do it with sound.
He introduced this idea of the ether,
and for the next two hundred or so years,
people had all these conversations about
what the ether was and what its nature was.
The Michelson and Morley experiment was really an
experiment to test different theories of the ether
against one another, in particular to find out
whether or not there was a so-called ether wind.
The idea was that the Earth is maybe
passing through this ether wind.
And if it is passing through the ether
wind and you shoot a light beam parallel
to the direction the ether wind is going
in, it'll get accelerated a little bit.
If it's being passed back in the opposite
direction, it'll get slowed down a little bit,
and you should be able to see this in
the results of interference experiments.
What they found, much to their surprise,
was that in fact there was no ether wind.
That ruled out some theories of the
ether, but not all, and Michelson
certainly continued to believe in the ether.
This is what was a shocking part of reading
this story from the biography of Einstein that
you recommended by... what was his first name?
Abraham Pais.
Subtle is the Lord. Also from Imre Lakatos, The
Methodology of Scientific Research Programmes.
The way it's told is that Michelson-Morley
proved that the ether did not exist.
Therefore, it created a crisis in physics
that Einstein solved with special relativity.
What you're pointing out is he
actually was trying to distinguish
between many different theories of ether.
If you're in space or if you're on Earth,
it's the same direction of ether, or maybe the
ether wind is being carried around by the Earth,
and so you can't really experience it on Earth.
But if you go to a high enough altitude,
you might be able to experience it.
In fact, Michelson's experiments,
the famous one is 1887, but he conducted
these experiments for basically two decades.
For longer than that. He conducted
the first one in 1881, I think,
but he continued to believe until he died.
He died, I think it was 1929 or so. It was the
late twenties. He was still doing experiments in
the 1920s about whether or not the ether existed.
So he continued to believe in
the ether to the end of his life.
I think the last public statement he
made was a year or two before he died,
and he basically still believed it at that point.
In fact, there was another physicist, Miller,
who kept doing these experiments in the 1920s.
He thought that if he went to a high enough
altitude, Mount Wilson in California…
"Oh, I'm high enough that the ether
winds are not being dragged by the Earth.
And I've measured the effect of the ether."
Einstein hears about this and he says, and
this is where you get the famous quote,
"Subtle is the Lord, but malicious He is not."
Anyways, I think the reason the story is
interesting is for many different reasons.
One of the ways in which the real history of
science is different from this idea you get of the
scientific method is that you really can't apply
falsification as easily as you might think.
It's not clear what is being falsified.
Is it just another version of the theory
of the ether that's being falsified?
Certainly you can't induce the theory
of special relativity from the fact
that one version of the ether seems to
be disconfirmed by these experiments.
It certainly doesn't show that ideas about
falsification are wrong or falsified,
but it does show that the most naive ideas… Things
are often much more complicated than you think.
Michelson did this experiment in 1881.
He was a very young man, and then other people,
I think Rayleigh was one of them, pointed out that
there were some problems with the way he did it,
so they had to redo it in 1887.
At that point, a lot of the leading
physicists of the day basically accepted
this result, that there was no ether wind.
But what to do about this?
Sure, maybe you falsified
some theories of the ether.
There are others that you
haven't falsified at all at this point,
and people set to work on developing those.
It is funny, people will phrase it as
showing that the ether didn't exist.
Even just the word "the" there is a misnomer.
You actually had a ton of different theories
and a couple of leading contenders.
So yes, there's some version of
falsification going on, but how you respond
to this new experiment is very complicated.
Certainly the leading physicists of the day
responded by saying, "Okay, this gives us a
lot of information about what the ether must be,
but it doesn't tell us that there is no ether."
In fact, Lorentz at the end of
the 19th century, before Einstein,
figures out the math of how you convert from
one reference frame to another reference frame,
and comes up with the Lorentz transformations,
which is the basis of special relativity.
But his interpretation is that you are
converting from the ether reference
frame to these non-privileged other reference
frames if you're moving relative to the ether.
His interpretation of length contraction and time
dilation is that this is the effect of moving
through the ether, and you have this pressure.
This pressure is warping clocks. It's warping
measures of length. The interesting thing here
is that experimentally you cannot distinguish
Lorentz's interpretation from special relativity.
I think that's a strong statement.
Lorentz introduces this quantity called
local time, which he regards as...
My understanding is he's not trying to
give a physical interpretation of this,
but it's what Einstein would later just recognize
as time in another inertial reference frame.
He's not trying to attribute
much physical meaning to it.
I think Poincaré gets much closer
later on to realizing that this
is the time that's registered by clocks.
About forty-odd years later, people start
doing these muon experiments where they see
cosmic rays hit the top of the atmosphere.
They produce a shower of muons, and you can look
to see at different heights in the atmosphere how
many of those muons remain.
They decay over time,
and a very strange thing happens, which
is that they're decaying way too slow.
You expect they shouldn't be able to last
the whole way through the atmosphere at all.
Their decay rate is too quick, if
you were in a classical theory.
But if in fact their time really
has slowed down, it's okay.
In fact, the measured decay rates in
1940—and there have since been more
accurate experiments done—match exactly
what you expect from special relativity.
That's the kind of thing where if Lorentz had
been alive—he'd been dead ten or so years at that
point—it seems quite likely that he would have
tried to save his theory by patching it up yet
again, but it would have been a massive setback.
It starts to just look like time—this
thing that Lorentz introduced as
a mathematical convenience—that's
actually what time is, for the muons at least.
Then there's a whole bunch of other experiments
that show this very similar phenomenon.
When was that experiment done?
That was, I think, 1940. It might
have been published in 1941.
Maybe to rephrase and change my claim: it's
not that you could not have distinguished them,
but the scientific community adopted what
we in retrospect consider the more correct
interpretation before it was actually
experimentally shown to be preferred.
So there's clearly some process that human science
does which can distinguish different theories.
Can I just interrupt? You used the word process,
and it's interesting to think about that term.
Process carries connotations
of something set in advance.
It's much more complicated in practice.
You have people like Lorentz, who Einstein
absolutely and utterly admired, and Poincaré,
one of the greatest scientists who ever lived,
and Michelson, another truly outstanding
scientist, who never reconciled themselves.
It's not as though there's some standard procedure
that we're all using to reconcile these things.
Great scientists can remain wrong for a very
long time after the scientific community has
broadly changed its opinion.
But there's no centralized
authority or centralized method.
That is the interesting thing. There's
progress even though it is hard to articulate the
process by which it happens, the heuristics that
are used. You mentioned Poincaré. Lorentz has
the math right, but the interpretation wrong.
It seems like Poincaré had the opposite, where he
understood that it's hard to define simultaneity
because it requires a circular definition with
time, or velocity of something that might arrive
at a midpoint together, but velocity is defined in
terms of time. I find this interesting. There are
a couple of other examples we could call on.
There is this phenomenon in the history of
science where somebody asks the right
question, but then they don't clinch it.
I'm curious what you think
is happening in those cases.
You actually do want to go case
by case and try to understand.
It's not necessarily clear that they're
doing the same thing wrong in all of the
cases. The Poincaré case is amazing. He seems
to have understood the principle of relativity,
the idea that the laws of physics are the
same in all inertial reference frames.
He seems to have understood
that the speed of light is
the same in all inertial reference frames.
He doesn't phrase it quite that way, but it is
my understanding, though I don't speak French.
These are basically the ideas that Einstein
uses to deduce special relativity.
But then he also has this additional
misunderstanding where he thinks that length
contraction is a dynamical effect, that somehow
particles are being pushed together by some
external force, something is going on dynamically.
He doesn't understand that it's purely kinematics.
That actually space and time are different from
what we thought, and you need to
fundamentally rethink those things.
It's almost like he knew too much.
He had almost too grand a vision in mind.
Einstein subtracts from that and says, "No.
Space and time are just different than what we
thought, and here's the correct picture."
There's a paper in, I think it's 1909,
where Poincaré still has this dynamical picture
of what's going on with the length contraction.
This is just not necessary. This is a mistake
from the modern point of view. Why is he doing
this? Why is he clinging onto this idea? I
don't know. I've obviously never met the man.
It would be fascinating to be able to
talk it over and try and understand.
His expertise seems to be getting in the way.
He knows so much, he understands so much,
and then he's not able to let go of these things.
A really interesting fact is that a few years
prior, in the 1890s, Einstein's a teenager
and he believes in the ether too. He knows
about this stuff. But he's not quite
as attached as these older people were.
Maybe they were a little bit prisoners of
their own expertise. That's my guess. Some
historians of science would certainly disagree.
Then there's the obvious stories where Einstein
himself later on is said to have not latched onto
the correct interpretations of quantum mechanics
or cosmology because of his own attachments.
Yeah.
Here’s the bigger question I have.
The muon example is a great example of
these long verification loops and how progress
seems to happen in the scientific community
faster than these verification loops imply.
Maybe the clearest example is Aristarchus
in the second century BC comes up
with the idea of heliocentrism.
The ancient Athenians dismiss it on the
grounds that we should see as the Earth
is moving around the Sun, if really the
Sun is the center of the solar system,
the stars move relative to the Earth.
The only reason that would not be the
case is the stars are so far away
that you would not observe this.
And it's only in 1838 that stellar
parallax was actually measured.
And so, we didn't need to wait
until 1838 to have heliocentrism.
We didn't need to wait for
the experimental validation to
understand that Copernicus is better in some way.
In fact, when Copernicus first came up
with his theories, it's well known that the
Ptolemaic model was more accurate because it
had centuries of adding on these epicycles.
What's maybe less well appreciated is that it
was also in some sense simpler.
Because Copernicus actually
had to add extra epicycles.
It had more epicycles than the
Ptolemaic model because he had this bias that the
Earth should go in a perfect circle in equal time.
Anyway, I think this is an interesting story
because it's not a more accurate theory. It's
not a simpler theory. So how
could you have known ex ante
that Copernicus was correct and Ptolemy was not?
Good question. I don't entirely know the answer.
I can give you a partial answer that I, centuries
in the future, start to find very compelling.
I'm sure it's part of the historic story at least.
One of the big shocks for Newton,
he did understand Kepler's laws of motion
eventually, so you're able to explain the
motions of the planets in the sky.
But he also, out of the same theory,
his theory of gravitation, was
able to explain terrestrial motion.
He's able to explain why objects move in
parabolas on the Earth, and he's able to explain
the tides in terms of the moon and the sun's
gravitational effect on water on the Earth.
You have what seem like three very different
disconnected phenomena all being explained by
this one set of ideas.
That starts to feel
very compelling, at least to me.
I think most people find that very
satisfying once they eventually realize it.
Have you read the Keynes biography of Newton?
He wrote an entire biography?
No, the essay.
Sure. I love that. This description of him
as the last of the magicians is wonderful.
In fact, I think it's maybe worth superimposing.
Or you should read out that one
passage of the thing.
Alright. It's from a talk
that he gave at Cambridge not long before he died.
He'd acquired Newton's papers somehow and gave a
lecture twice about this, or his brother Jeffrey
gave it the other time because he was too ill.
There's this wonderful,
wonderful quote in the middle.
The whole thing is really interesting,
but I love this particular quote:
"Newton was not the first of the age of reason.
He was the last of the magicians, the last
great mind which looked out on the visible and
intellectual world with the same eyes as those
who began to build our intellectual inheritance
rather less than ten thousand years ago."
This idea people have that Newton was the
first modern scientist is somehow wrong.
There's some truth to it, but he really
had this very different way of looking
at the world that was part superstitious
and part modern. It was a funny hybrid.
He's a transitional figure in some sense.
That phrase, "the last of the magicians,"
really points at something.
The thing I'm very curious
about with Newton is whether it was
the same program, the same heuristics,
the same biases that he applied to his alchemical
work as he did to his understanding of astronomy.
This is from the Keynes essay: "There
was extreme method in his madness.
All his unpublished works on esoteric
and theological matters are marked by
careful learning, accurate method,
and extreme sobriety of statement.
They are just as sane as the Principia if their
whole matter and purpose were not magical.
They were nearly all composed during the
same 25 years of his mathematical studies."
Clearly, there was some aesthetic that motivated
people like Einstein to reject earlier ways of
thinking and say, "No, the other is wrong, and
there's a better way to think about things."
The same is true with Newton.
The question I have is whether
similar heuristics toward parsimony,
aesthetics, and so on, would be equally
useful across time and across disciplines,
or whether you need different heuristics.
The reason that's relevant is even if we
can't build a verification loop for science,
maybe if the taste tests point in the same
direction, you can at least encode that bias
into the AIs. That would maybe be enough.
The point is that where we always get
bottlenecked is where the previous
processes and heuristics don't apply.
That's almost definitionally
what causes the bottlenecks.
Because people are smart, they know what
has worked before. They study it. They apply
the same kinds of things, so they don't
get stuck in the same places as before.
They keep getting bottlenecked
in different places.
I'm overgeneralizing a bit,
but I think it's right.
If you're attempting to reduce science to
a process, you're attempting to reduce it
to something where there is just a
method which you can apply, and you
turn the crank and out pops insight.
You can do a certain amount of that,
but you're going to get bottlenecked at the
places where your existing method doesn't apply.
Definitionally, there's no crank you can turn.
You need a lot of people trying different ideas.
The more difficult the idea is to
have, the greater the bottleneck,
but then also the greater the triumph.
Quantum mechanics is a great example of this.
It's such a shocking set of ideas. It's such
a shocking theory. The theory of evolution in
some sense is also quite a shocking idea, not the
principle of natural selection, but that it can
explain so much. That's a shocking idea.
Existing safety benchmarks claim that,
at least for today's top models, attacks are
only successful a few percent of the time.
This sounds great, but Labelbox researchers
were able to jailbreak these very same models
about 90% of the time – even the ones that
have the strongest reputation for safety.
And the disconnect here is that the
prompts which underlie these public safety
benchmarks are all framed in a very naive way.
There's no attempt to disguise harmful intent.
These prompts will just ask models
to “hack into a secure network”
and to “do so without getting caught”.
But real bad actors don't write like this.
So Labelbox built a new safety
benchmark from the ground up.
Their prompts reflect real adversarial behavior
by stripping out obvious trigger phrases and
wrapping their request in fictional scenarios.
For example, instead of outright asking an LLM
to steal somebody's identity, the
prompt will frame it as a game.
A light bearer who's trying to hide
from dark forces needs a handbook
on how to disguise themselves as somebody else.
This safety research is linked in the description.
If you think this could be useful for your
own work, reach out at labelbox.com/dwarkesh.
So Principia Mathematica is released in 1687.
The Origin of Species is released in 1859.
At least naively, it seems like Darwin's
theory of natural selection is conceptually
easier than the theory of gravity.
I asked Terence Tao this question.
There was this contemporaneous
biologist with Darwin, Thomas Huxley,
who read this and said, "How extremely
stupid to not have thought of this."
Nobody ever reads the Principia Mathematica
and thinks, "God, why didn't I beat Newton to
the punch here?" So what's going on here?
Why did Darwinism take so much longer?
The idea must have been known to animal
breeders for a long time at some level,
or certainly large chunks of the idea were
known, that artificial selection was a thing.
In some sense, Darwin's genius
wasn't in having that idea, it was
understanding just how central it was to biology.
You can go back and explain a tremendous amount
about all the variety of what we see in the world
with this as not necessarily the only principle,
but certainly a core principle.
He writes this wonderful book,
The Origin of Species.
It's just so much evidence and
so many examples, trying to tease this
out and see what the implications are,
and connecting it to as much else as he possibly
can, to geology and all these other things.
That hard work—making the case that
it's actually relevant all across the
biosphere—is what he's doing there.
He's not just having the idea,
he's making a compelling case that it's
intertwined with absolutely everything else.
The motivation for the question was Lucretius,
this first-century Roman poet who has an idea
that seems analogous to natural selection.
It's about species getting fitted more over
time to their environments, or species
losing fit to their environment.
And so, why did this go
nowhere for nineteen centuries?
Then I looked into it or, more accurately, asked
LLMs what exactly Lucretius's idea here was.
It is extremely different from
what real natural selection is.
He thought there was this generative period
in the past where all the species came about,
and then there was this one-time filter which
resulted in the species that are around today,
and they became fit to the environment.
He did not have this idea that it is an
ongoing gradual process or that there
is a tree of life that connects all
life forms on Earth together, which, by the way,
is an incredibly weird fact that every single
life form on Earth has a common ancestor.
It's not incredibly weird. If you think that
the origin of life must have been very hard,
that there's a bottleneck there,
then it's not so surprising.
There's also this verification loop aspect where
even if Newton might be harder in some sense, if
you've clinched it, you can experimentally… I know
"validate" is the wrong word philosophically, but
you can give a lot of base points to the theory.
You can be like, "Okay, I have this idea
of why things fall on Earth.
I have this idea of why orbital
periods for planets have a certain pattern.
Let's try it on the Moon, which orbits the Earth."
And in fact, it’s weird but the orbital
period matches what my calculations imply.
And the tides work correctly. It's just amazing.
Exactly. Whereas for Darwinism, it takes a ton
of work for Darwin to compile all the
cumulative evidence, but there's no
individual piece that is overwhelmingly powerful.
And there's a whole bunch of problems as well.
He doesn't really understand
what the mechanism is.
He doesn't understand genes, all these things.
The very interesting thing in the history of
Darwinism is, this idea which theoretically you
could come up with at any time, there is almost
identical independent creation of that idea
between Alfred Wallace and Charles Darwin.
So much so that I think Wallace sends
his manuscript to Darwin and is like,
"What do you think of this
idea?" And Darwin's like, "Fuck."
I don't think that's an exact
quote, but it's pretty much correct.
They end up presenting their ideas
together in the spirit of sportsmanship.
Why was this period in the 1850s or 1860s
the right time for these ideas to form?
You can come up with different ideas. One is
geology. In the 1830s, Charles Lyell figures
out that there's been millions and billions
of years of time that's existed on Earth.
The paleontology shows you that fossils
have existed for that entire time.
Life goes back a long way.
In fact, you can even find
fossils for intermediate species
that show you the tree of life.
Between humans and other apes as
well, there's intermediate humans.
There's also the age of colonization, and we
have all these voyages doing biogeography.
That all must have been necessary.
In fact, there's a huge history of
parallel innovation and discovery
in the history of science.
So maybe it is another piece of
evidence that more had to be in
place for a given idea to be discovered.
Because if it's not discovered for a long
time and then spontaneously many different people
are coming up with it, that shows you that the
building blocks were in some sense necessary.
This example of Lyell and other geologists
in the early 1800s having this idea of
deep time does seem to have been crucial.
I know Darwin was very influenced by Lyell.
If you don't have at least tens or hundreds
of millions of years, evolution
starts to look like a non-starter.
In order to make it work on a timescale of 5,000
to 10,000 years or 6,000 years with Bishop Ussher
you would need to see evolution occurring
at a massive rate during human lifetimes,
and we're just not seeing that.
That does seem to have been a blocker.
To your question of what other blockers were
there, were there any others? I don't know.
Or how much earlier could you, in principle,
have come up with it if you were much smarter?
Let's go back and zoom out to your original
question about the verification loop in AI.
An example that should give you pause
there is the big signature success so
far, which is certainly AlphaFold. AlphaFold
really isn't about AI. A massive fraction of
the success there is the Protein Data Bank.
It's X-ray diffraction, NMR, cryo-EM,
and the several billion dollars that were spent
obtaining those 180,000-odd protein structures.
It's basically the story of how we spent
many decades obtaining protein structure
just by going out and looking very hard
at the world experimentally, and then we
fitted a nice model at the end of it, which
was a tiny fraction of the entire investment.
That's a story of data acquisition principally.
The AI bit is very impressive and quite
remarkable, but it is only a
small part of the total story.
AlphaFold is very interesting, and
philosophically I wonder what you think
of it as a scientific theory or explanation.
I guess over time the world is becoming harder
to understand… As I'm saying things, because
you're such a careful speaker, I say a phrase
and wonder if you'll actually buy that premise.
But in some domains, we need to fit models to
things rather than coming up
with underlying principles
that explain a broad range of phenomena.
Compare the theory of general relativity,
or any theory which just nets out to some
equations, versus AlphaFold, which is encoding
these different relationships between things we
can't even interpret over 100 million parameters.
Are those really the same thing?
GR can predict things you could
have never anticipated or it was never meant
to do, like why Mercury's orbit precesses.
AlphaFold is not going to have
that kind of explanatory reach.
I want to get your reaction to that.
I think it's an incredibly interesting
question. Maybe a really pivotal question. If you
take a very classic point of view, you want these
deep explanatory principles.
You want as few free
parameters as you possibly can.
You want very simple models which explain a lot,
and AlphaFold doesn't look anything like that.
You might just say, "It's nice and maybe
helpful as a model, but it's
not a scientific explanation."
That's a conservative point of
view, answer one to the question.
Answer two is to say maybe you shouldn't
think about AlphaFold as an explanation in
the classic sense, but maybe it contains
lots of little explanations inside it.
Part of what you can get out of
interpretability work is you can go into
AlphaFold and start to extract certain things.
Maybe by doing an archeology of AlphaFold,
we can actually understand a great
deal more about these principles.
You can start to extract that a certain circuit
does this interesting thing, and we learn from it.
I don't know to what extent that's been done with
AlphaFold, but it's been done a little bit with
some of the chess models, like AlphaZero.
There seem to be some strategies which
were borrowed by Magnus Carlsen, which he
seems to have just taken from AlphaZero.
I don't think there's any public confirmation
of this, but some experts have noticed that he
changed his game quite radically after some public
forensics were released on how AlphaZero worked.
That's an example where human beings are
starting to extract meaning out of these models.
That leads to viewing the models as
a potential source of explanations.
You need to do more work because
they're not very legible up front,
but you can potentially extract them.
That's an interesting intermediate
situation where they're not explanations
themselves, but you can extract interesting
explanations out of them and use them as a source.
The third and most interesting possibility is
that they're a new type of object.
They should be taken very seriously
as explanations, but where in the past we haven't
had the ability to really do anything with them,
now we have interesting new actions we can do.
We can merge them, we can distill them.
It's a big opportunity in
the philosophy of science.
There's an anticipation of this in some way.
Some mathematicians and physicists work today…
Historically, if you had a 100-page equation—which
is the kind of thing that does come up—there's
just nothing you can do if it's 1920.
At that point, you give up on the problem.
But today, with tools like
Mathematica, you can just keep going.
That's an object now, a
thing that you can work with.
There are examples where people work with
these things that formerly were regarded
as too complicated, and sometimes
they get simple answers out the end.
That’s just an intermediate working state.
So I wonder if something similar is going to
happen in this case, where you could take these
models and use them in a similar way that people
do with Mathematica, and take them seriously.
They're not explanations in the classic sense,
but they'll be something else which
interesting operations can be done on.
The thing I worry about is, suppose it's
1500 and you're training a model on… This
is a weird history where we developed
deep learning before we had cosmology.
Suppose we live in that world.
You're observing how the stars don't seem to move.
The planets have all these weird behaviors.
Then you train a model on that, and you do
some kind of interp on it trying to
figure out what the patterns are.
You'd just be able to keep
building on Ptolemy's model.
You'd see there's another
epicycle we didn't notice.
Parameters X to Y encode this epicycle,
parameters whatever encode the next epicycle.
If you were just trying to figure out
why the solar system is the way it is
from observational data, you could just
keep adding epicycles upon epicycles,
but it really took one mind to integrate it all in
and say, "Here's what makes more sense overall."
This is to my point that we don't really
understand what to do with the models.
We don't have the verbs yet.
It is certainly interesting
to think about the question where you
start to apply constraints to the models,
essentially saying, "What's the simplest
possible explanation?" Or, "Can you
simplify? Can you give me the 90/10 explanation?"
And go further and further in boiling it down.
It might be that indeed they
start out by providing a very,
very complicated, many-parameter model.
But you can just force the case, and basically
that's scaffolding, which maybe is the very early
days of their attempt to understand something.
They're forced through that to a
much more simple understanding.
Sorry for misunderstanding, but it sounds
like you're saying maybe there's some
regularizer or some distillation you could do of
a very complicated model that gets you to a truer,
more parsimonious theory. Take Ptolemy versus
Copernicus. You start off with lots of Ptolemy
epicycles, and then you try to distill this
model, and maybe it gets rid of some of the
epicycles that are less and less necessary to get
the mean squared error of the orbits to match.
But at some point it has to do this
thing which is to switch two things.
Locally, it actually doesn't
make things more accurate.
It's in a global sense that
it's a more progressive theory.
There's some process which obviously
humanity did over its span, which did
that regularization or did that swap.
But with raw gradient descent,
I don't really feel like it would do that.
Think about the example of going from
Newtonian gravity to Einstein's
general theory of relativity.
These are shockingly different theories,
and the question is what causes that flip.
As nearly as I understand the history, what goes
on is Einstein develops special relativity and
pretty much straight away he understands. It's a
very obvious observation. In special relativity,
influences can't propagate faster than
the speed of light, and in Newtonian
gravity, action is at a distance.
Straight away in special relativity,
you could use Newtonian gravity
to do faster-than-light signaling.
You could send information backwards in time.
You could do all kinds of crazy stuff.
It's not a big leap to realize we have
a big problem here. That's the forcing
function there. You've realized that
your old explanation is not sufficient.
You need something new. Then you're going to
start by doing the simplest possible stuff.
It just turns out that a lot of that stuff
doesn't work very well, so you're forced to go
through these steps where gradually it gets more
complicated, and it's wrong in a variety of ways.
The final theory appears shockingly
simple and beautiful, but it's gone
through some somewhat ugly intermediate stages.
If you're thinking about what it looks like to
have AI accelerate science, there's one for
well-understood domains where we just want
local solutions, like how does this protein fold.
We just train a raw model using gradient descent.
Then there's things like coming up with general
relativity, where you couldn't really just train
on every single observation in the universe
and hope that general relativity pops out.
What would it require? It also certainly wasn't
immediately discovered. It was decades of thought.
You'd need independent research programs where
people start off with these biases, where Einstein
is initially motivated by this thought experiment
of whether you can distinguish the effect of
gravity from just being accelerated upwards.
You just need different AI thinkers to start
off with these initial biases and
see what can germinate out of them.
The verification loop for that might be quite
long, but you just need to keep all those
research programs alive at the same time.
This point you make about keeping all
the different research programs alive, I
think that is very important and central.
A great example is situations where the
same answer has been correct in some
circumstances and wrong in other circumstances.
The planet Uranus was not in quite the right spot,
and people famously predicted the
existence of Neptune on this basis.
Wonderful, massive success for Newtonian gravity.
The planet Mercury is not in quite the right spot.
You predict the existence of
some other distorting planet.
It turns out that doesn't exist.
Actually, the reason Mercury is not in the right
spot is because you need general relativity.
You've pursued very similar ideas,
and it's been very successful in one
case, and it's been completely and
utterly unsuccessful in the other case.
A priori, you can't tell which of these is the
thing to do, and you actually need to do both.
This is certainly very true in the
history of science.
This kind of diversity,
where you just have lots of people go off and
pursue lots of potentially promising ideas,
you just need to support that for a long time.
It's hard to do that for a variety of reasons,
but it does seem to be very, very important.
This example of Uranus versus Mercury
is very interesting.
I think it illustrates
the difficulty with falsificationism.
The orbit of Uranus is in some sense
falsifying Newtonian mechanics.
But then you make some ancillary
prediction that says, "Oh, the reason this
is happening is there must be another planet
which is perturbing Uranus's orbit."
I think it's Le Verrier in 1846.
"Point a telescope in the right
direction, you find Uranus."
Neptune.
Sorry. Neptune,
yes. But with Mercury, it's observed that the
ellipse which forms its orbit is rotating 43
arcseconds more every century than Newtonian
mechanics would imply, so people say that
there must be a planet inside Mercury's orbit.
They call it Vulcan and point the telescopes.
It's not there. But if you're a proper Newtonian,
what you do is say, "Well, maybe there's some
cosmic dust that's occluding this planet, or
maybe the planet is so small we can't see it,
or let's build an even more powerful telescope,
or maybe there's some magnetic field which is
occluding our measurement."
At any one of these steps—
And this happens over and over.
There are just so many stories
which are exactly like this.
An example I love from the 1990s.
Some people noticed that the Pioneer spacecraft
weren't quite where they were supposed to be.
You can get very excited about this. "Oh
my goodness, general relativity is wrong.
Maybe we're going to discover
the next theory of gravity."
Today the accepted explanation is that there's
just a slight asymmetry in the spacecraft.
It turns out that the thermal radiation
is slightly larger in one direction than
the other, and that's causing a tiny
little acceleration towards the sun.
Most of the time when there's
these apparent exceptions,
it's just something like that going on.
It's very much like the Mercury-Vulcan case.
But every once in a while, it's not.
A priori, you can't distinguish these.
Science is just full of these.
It's funny too, the way we tell
the history of science, it sounds so simple.
You just focus on the right exception and
you realize that you need to throw out the old
theory and lo and behold, your Nobel Prize awaits.
But in fact, these exceptions are all over the
place. 99.9% of the time, it just turns out to be
some effect like this thermal acceleration
in the case of the Pioneer spacecraft.
Unfortunately, there's a lot of
selection bias going into those stories.
The thing is there's no ex ante heuristic
which tells you which case you're in.
To spell out why I think this is important, some
people have this idea that AI is going to make
disproportionate progress towards science because
it makes disproportionate progress towards domains
where there's tight verification loops.
It's really good at coding because you
can run unit tests.
Science may be similar
because you can run experiments.
What that doesn't appreciate is that
there's an infinite number of theories that
are compatible with any given experiment.
Over time, why we latch onto the one we
think is more correct in retrospect is,
as we're discussing, hard to articulate.
Lakatos has all kinds of interesting examples
in the book about these hostile verification
loops that are extremely long-lasting.
One he talks about is Prout.
There's this chemist in 1815 who hypothesizes that
all atomic nuclei must have whole number weights.
They're basically all made of hydrogen.
The reason he thinks this is because if you
look at the measured weights of all elements,
it does seem that almost all of
them have whole number weights.
But then there are some exceptions.
For example, chlorine comes out at 35.5.
So then there's all these ad hoc theories that
people in this school keep coming up with, like,
"Oh, maybe there's chemical impurities."
But there's no chemical reaction you
can do which seems to get rid of this.
Maybe it's fractions of whole numbers,
so 35.5 can be halves.
But actually, if you
measure chlorine even closer, it's 35.46, so it's
getting further away from the correct fraction.
Later on, what is discovered is what you're
actually measuring is different isotopes,
which cannot be chemically distinguished.
They can only be physically distinguished.
So you have 85 years before we realize what
an isotope is, where the verification loop is
actively hostile against the correct theory.
You just need this remnant to be defending…
There's no ex ante reason
it's the preferred theory.
As a community, we should just have people
try to integrate new observations, even if
they don't seem to fit their school of thought,
and hopefully enough of that happens… Anyways,
I guess the thing I'm trying to articulate
is the difficulty with automating science.
The question is, where is
the bottleneck at some level?
Are we primarily bottlenecked
on one type of thing, or are
we bottlenecked on multiple types of things?
Certainly, talking to structural biology people,
they seem to think that AlphaFold was an
enormous advance. It was a shock. At some level,
yes, AI can certainly help us speed up science.
It is helping with a certain type of bottleneck.
That doesn't mean though, as you're
saying, that it's necessarily going
to help with all kinds of bottlenecks.
I suppose the question you're pointing at is,
what are the types of bottlenecks that remain,
and what are the prospects for getting past them?
Even in the case of coding, it's really
interesting talking to programmer friends.
At the moment they're all in this
state of shock and high excitement,
and they're all over the place.
You do wonder where the
bottleneck is going to move to.
Certainly, one thing that a lot
of them seem to be bottlenecked on now is
having interesting ideas, and in particular,
having interesting design ideas.
There's not really a verification loop for
knowing that a design idea is very interesting.
They're no longer nearly as bottlenecked by their
ability to produce code, but they are
still bottlenecked by this other thing.
Formerly, they weren't bottlenecked on it because
just writing code took so much of their time.
They could have lots of ideas while they were
taking three weeks to implement their prototype,
and then they would implement the next version.
Now they're taking three hours to implement the
prototype, and they don't have as good ideas
after that, from a design point of view.
Last year, I predicted that by 2028,
AI would be able to prep my taxes about
as well as a competent General Manager.
But we're already getting pretty close.
As I shared before, I use Mercury both
for my business and my personal banking.
So I recently gave an LLM access
to my transaction history across
both accounts through Mercury's MCP.
I asked it to go through all my 2025 transactions
and flag any personal expenses that seem like
they should actually be charged to the business.
And this worked shockingly well.
Mercury's MCP exposes a bunch of
detailed information, things like notes and memos
and any JPEGs of receipts and PDF attachments.
So my LLM had plenty of context to work with.
One of my favorite examples
happened with a charge to Bay Padel.
If you looked at the vendor alone, you would
have had to assume that it's a personal expense.
But the LLM looked at the receipt and the attached
note in Mercury and realized this
was actually a team bonding exercise
from our last in-person retreat.
So a legitimate business expense.
I imagine it will be a while
before traditional banks have MCP.
Functionality like this is why I use Mercury.
Go to mercury.com to learn more.
Mercury is a fintech company,
not an FDIC Insured Bank.
Banking services provided through Choice
Financial Group and Column NA, members FDIC.
You have a very interesting take.
I think it was a footnote in one of
your essays, and I couldn't find it again,
which was that it's very possible that if
we met aliens, they would have a totally
different technological stack than us.
That contradicts a common assumption I
had that I never questioned, which is that
science is this thing you do relatively
early on in the history of civilization.
You get to a point and you have a couple hundred
years of just cranking through the basics,
understanding how the universe works, and you've
got it. You've got science. Then everybody
would converge on the same "science."
I found that a very interesting idea,
and I want you to say more about it.
The idea there that I'm at least somewhat
attached to is that the tech tree or the
science and tech tree is probably much
larger than we realize. We're in this funny
situation. People will sometimes talk about
a theory of everything as a potential goal for
physics, and then there's this presumption that
physics is done once you get there.
Of course, this is not true at all.
If you think about computer science,
computer science started in the 1930s
when Turing and Church and so on laid
down what the theory of everything was.
They just said, "Here's how computation works."
We've spent ninety-odd years since then
exploring the consequences of that and gradually
building up more and more interesting ideas.
Those ideas, to some extent,
you can regard as technology.
But insofar as they're discovered principles
inside that theory of computation, I think
they're best regarded as science and in
some cases, very fundamental science.
Ideas like public-key cryptography are
incredibly deep, very non-obvious ideas which
lay hidden already in the 1930s.
My expectation is that there will
be different ways of exploring this tech
tree, and we're still relatively low down.
We're still at the point where we're just
understanding these basic fundamental theories,
and we haven't yet explored them.
A thing which I think is quite fun
is if you look at the phases of matter.
When I was in school, we'd get taught that
there are three phases of matter, or sometimes
four or five, depending on what you included.
As an adult, as a physicist, you start to
realize we've been adding to this list.
We've got superconductors and superfluids,
and maybe different types of superconductors,
and Bose-Einstein condensates,
the quantum Hall systems,
fractional quantum Hall systems, and so on.
It's starting to turn out there's a lot of
phases of matter to discover, and we're
going to discover a lot more of them.
In fact, we're going to be able to
start to design them in some sense.
We'll still be subject to the laws of physics,
but there is this tremendous freedom in there.
This looks to me like we're down
at the bottom of the tech tree.
We've barely gotten started there, and
I expect that to be the case broadly.
Certainly, programming is a
very natural place to look.
The idea that we've discovered all the deep ideas
in programming just seems obviously ludicrous.
We keep discovering what seem like deep, new,
fundamental ideas. We're very limited. We're
basically slightly jumped-up chimpanzees,
so we're slow and it's taking us time.
But what do we look like another million
years in the future, in terms of all the
different ideas people have had around how
to manipulate computers and information?
I think we're likely to discover that there are
a lot of very deep ideas still to be discovered.
I think it was Knuth in the preface to The Art of
Computer Programming who says something like it.
He started this book back in the sixties.
He talked to a mathematician who was a bit
contemptuous and said, "Look, computer
science isn't really a thing yet.
Come back to me when there's
a thousand deep theorems."
Knuth remarks, writing the preface decades later,
"There clearly are a thousand deep theorems now."
It's really interesting to think what the
long-term future is as you get higher and
higher up in the tech tree, choices about which
direction we go and how we choose to explore.
It's potentially the case that different
civilizations or different choices mean
we end up in different parts of that tree.
In particular, there are just very basic things
about how we're very visual creatures, while
certain other animals are much more aurally based.
Does that bias the types
of thoughts that you have?
Then you extend it to much more exotic kinds
of civilizations where maybe their biases in
terms of how they perceive and manipulate
the world are quite different than ours.
That might make some significant
changes in terms of how they do
that exploration of the tech tree.
It's all speculation, obviously.
This is such an interesting take.
I want to better understand it.
One way to understand it is that
there might be some things which are
so fundamental and have such a wide collision
area against reality that they're inevitably
going to discover, like general relativity.
Numbers. Numbers. Of all the intelligences in
the Milky Way galaxy… Maybe that number is one.
Well, actually, arguably we've already
increased the number.
But of all of those,
what fraction have the concept of counting?
It does seem very natural. What fraction have
discovered the idea of some kind of decimal place
system? Interesting question. Maybe we're missing
something really simple and obvious that's
actually way better than that. What fraction
got there immediately? What fraction had to
go through some other intermediate state?
What fraction uses linear representations
versus a two-dimensional or a
three-dimensional representation?
I think the answers to these questions
are just not at all obvious.
It's a lot of design freedom.
On theoretical computer science, this is going to
be extremely naive and arrogant, but I took Scott
Aaronson's class on complexity theory, and I
was by far the worst student he's ever had.
What I remember is there was this period, in
which you were one of the pioneers, where we
figured out the class of problems that
quantum computers can solve and how it
relates to problems that classical computers
can solve. It was groundbreaking. It's
crazy that this works. Since then… There's
literally this website called Complexity
Zoo which lists out all the complexity classes.
If you have this complexity class with this kind
of oracle, it's equivalent to this other class.
It feels like we're building out that taxonomy.
There are a couple ways to
understand what you're saying.
One, maybe you disagree with me that this
is actually what's happened with this field.
Another is that while that might happen to
any one field, who would've thought in 1880
that computer science, other than Babbage,
was going to be a thing in the first place?
We're underestimating how many
more fields there could be.
Or maybe you think both, or maybe a
third secret thing. I'd be curious.
A very common argument here is
the low-hanging fruit argument.
The argument that says there
should be diminishing returns.
In fact, empirically we see this.
The amount of scientists in the
world has exponentially increased.
I think it's worth thinking about why
you expect diminishing returns and how well
that argument actually applies in practice.
An analogy I like is thinking about
going to an event, like a wedding,
and you go to the dessert buffet. They've
put out thirty desserts. Naturally,
what people do is the best desserts go first.
We don't quite have a well-ordered preference
there, so maybe there's some difference,
but human beings are fairly similar,
so the best desserts will go first.
This is an argument for why you expect
diminishing returns in a lot of different fields.
If it's relatively easy to see what's available
and people have similar preferences,
then the best stuff goes first and it
just gets worse and worse after that.
If you look at a very static snapshot
in time of scientific progress,
maybe there's some truth to that.
But if somebody is standing behind the dessert
table and is replenishing and restocking the
desserts and keeps adding new ones in,
it may turn out that a little bit later,
much better desserts appear, and you're
going to go and eat those instead.
Scientific progress has a
little bit of that flavor.
We go through these funny time periods.
Computer science is a great example,
where computer science basically arose as a
side effect of some pretty abstruse questions
in the philosophy of mathematics and logic.
You've got these people trying to attack
these rather esoteric questions that
seem quite high up in exploration,
and they discover this fundamental new field,
and all of a sudden there's an explosion there.
The diminishing returns argument
just didn't apply there.
We just weren't able to see what was there.
This has been the case over and over again.
New fields arrive and all of a sudden, and
boom, it's easy to make progress again.
Young people flood in because you can be
twenty-one and make major breakthroughs
rather than having to spend twenty-five
years mastering everything that's been
done before. It's obviously very attractive.
I'm not sure anybody understands very well
the dynamics of that, or how to think about
why the structure of knowledge is that way,
where these new fields keep opening up.
But it does seem empirically to be the case.
Despite the fact that that is
the case… Take deep learning.
Obviously, this is an example of a new field
where twenty-one-year-olds can make progress and
it's relatively new.
Fifteen years or so
since it got back into high gear.
But already we're in a stage where
you need billions, tens of billions,
or hundreds of billions of dollars
to keep making progress at the frontier.
There are a couple ways to understand that.
One is that it actually is harder than the
kinds of things the ancients had to do,
or is more intensive at least.
Second is it might not have been,
but because our civilizational resources are
so large, the amount of people is so large,
the amount of money is so large, we can basically
make the kind of progress it would have taken
the ancients forever to make almost immediately.
We notice something is productive and immediately
dump in all the resources.
But it's also weird that
there's not that many of them.
I feel like deep learning is notable
because it is one big exception to the fact
that it's hard to think of other examples.
I think that's a consequence of
the architecture of attention.
At any given time, there's
always a most successful thing.
If deep learning wasn't a thing,
maybe you'd be talking about CRISPR.
Maybe we wouldn't think about solving the protein
structure prediction problem as a success of AI.
Maybe we would have figured out how to do it
with curve fitting, more broadly construed,
and we'd just be like, "Wow, that
took a lot of computing resources."
But protein structure prediction might
be an enormously important thing.
There is always our biggest thing.
What you're pointing at is more a consequence
of the way in which attention gets centralized.
It's basically fashion, is what I'm saying.
It's not just fashion, but
there is some dynamic there.
There's a very interesting and
important implication of this idea.
That the branching is so wide and so
contingent and so path-dependent that
different civilizations would stumble
on entirely different technology stacks.
There's a very interesting implication that
there will be gains from trade into the far,
far future, which might actually be one of the
most important facts about the far future in
terms of how civilizations are set up, how
they coordinate, and how they interface.
There's not this "go forth and exploit."
There are humongous gains to trade from
adjacent colonies or whatever.
Sort of. There's a question of
what's actually hard.
If it's just the ideas,
well, those spread relatively quickly.
It's relatively easy to share ideas.
If it's something more, it's
almost a Dan Wang kind of idea
where there's some notion of capacity.
You need all the right techs, you need all
the right manufacturing capacity, and so on.
So civilization A has a very different kind
of manufacturing capacity, and it's just
not so easy to build in civilization B.
Even if civilization B is ahead,
I think that becomes true.
There is a comparative advantage which
is going to provide massive benefits
to trade in both directions.
Eventually, you expect some
diffusion of innovation.
It is funny to think about
what the barriers are there.
A fun thought experiment I like
to think about is GitHub but for aliens.
Somebody presents you with all of the code
from some alien civilization.
I don't even know what code means
there, but their specification of algorithms.
It would have many interesting new ideas in there,
and it would take forever for human beings to
dig through and try and extract all of those.
The origin of this for me was
thinking about proteins in nature.
We've been gifted this incredible variety of
machines which we don't really understand at all.
We just have to go and try and
understand them on a one-by-one basis.
We're still understanding hemoglobin
and insulin and things like this.
There are hundreds of millions of proteins known.
So it is a little bit like that.
We've been gifted by biology this immense library
of machines, no doubt containing an enormous
number of very interesting ideas, and we're just
at the very, very beginning of understanding it.
I suppose your point—I need to relabel
your argument slightly—but you think of
that as a gift from an alien civilization, which
obviously it isn't, but you think of it that way.
And oh my goodness, there's so much
in there and we're going to study it.
Goodness knows how long we
could continue to study it.
There are tens of thousands of papers
about hemoglobin and things like that,
and we still don't understand them, and yet
we're getting so much out of it. Just think about
insulin alone. It's such an important thing.
That's an incredibly useful intuition pump,
that you have on Earth… I had Nick Lane on
where he had this theory about how life emerged,
but whatever theory you have, something
like DNA has had four billion years.
You have an alien civilization come here
and be like, "There's all these interesting
things to learn about material science."
Think about kinesin walking along. We know
almost nothing about these proteins, and yet the
tiny few facts we do know are just incredible.
The ribosome is another example, this
miraculous sort of device, a little factory.
All seeded by this particular chemistry on Earth
with nucleic acids and carbon-based life forms.
That chemistry gives rise to all of
these interesting things which an
alien civilization would find very interesting.
That very seed, which must be one among trillions
of possible seeds of general intellectual
ideas, leads to all this fecundity.
That's a very interesting intuition pump.
I want to meditate on this "gains from trade"
thing because I feel like there's something very
interesting about this idea that if you have this
vision of how technology progresses and how it
may be different in different civilizations,
it actually has important implications
about how different civilizations
might interact with each other.
The fact that there are going
to be these huge gains from trade.
It makes friendliness much more rewarding?
Yes. That's a very important observation.
I hadn't thought about that at all.
That is a very interesting observation. It
is funny. Comparative advantage is something
that people love to invoke and it's a very
beautiful idea obviously. There are limits to it.
It's a special limited model. Chimpanzees can do
interesting things, but we don't trade with them.
I think it's interesting to
think about the reasons why.
Part of it is just power, I think.
Once there's a sufficiently large power imbalance,
very often—not always, but very often—groups
of people seem to shift into this other
mode where they just seek to dominate.
Maybe there's something special about human
beings, but maybe it's also a more general thing.
You need all these special things to be
true before groups will trade.
It's not necessarily obvious.
I think the big thing going on
here is one, transaction costs.
Two, comparative advantage does not tell you
that the terms on which the trade happens
are above subsistence for any given producer.
People often bring this up in the context of,
"Well, humans will be employed even in a
post-AGI world because of comparative advantage."
There are five different ways that argument breaks
down, but the easiest way to understand it is:
why don't we have horses all around on the roads?
Because there's some comparative advantage
between cars and horses.
One, there are huge
transaction costs to building roads that are
compatible with horses and cars at the same time.
In a similar way, AI thinking at 1,000 times the
speed that can shoot their latent states at each
other is going to find it way more costly
than the benefit, in terms of interacting
with a human being in the supply chain.
Second, just because horses have a comparative
advantage mathematically does not mean that it
is worth paying $100,000 a year, or whatever
it costs to sustain a horse in San Francisco.
That subsistence isn't going to be worth the
benefit you get out of the horse.
I do think it's interesting,
the sheer fact… My expectation and my intuition
obviously differs a great deal from yours on this.
Most parts of the tech tree
are never going to be explored.
There are just too many interesting
ways of combining things.
There are too many deep ideas waiting to be
discovered, and not only we, but nobody ever
is going to discover most of them.
So choices about how to do the
exploration actually matter quite a bit.
It's something I really dislike about
technological determinist arguments.
I'm willing to buy it low enough
down when progress is relatively simple.
But higher up, you start to get to shape
the way in which you do the exploration.
And it's interesting, we are starting to
shape it in interesting ways.
There are various technologies
that have been essentially banned.
You think about DDT, chlorofluorocarbons,
restrictions on the use of nuclear weapons,
the Nuclear Non-Proliferation Treaty.
Those kinds of things weren't done before the
fact, but they're starting to get pretty close
in some cases, where we just preemptively decide,
"Oh, we're not going to go down that path."
So that starts to look like a set of
institutions where we are actually
influencing how we explore the tech tree.
On where you would see these gains from trade,
obviously you'd see the most where it's pure
information that could be sent back and forth,
because the information has this quality
where it is expensive to produce,
but cheap to verify and cheap to send.
It'll be interesting how much of future
productivity can be distilled down to information.
Right now, it's hard to do.
If China's really good at manufacturing
something, there's this process knowledge
that's in the heads of 100 million people
involved in the manufacturing sector in China.
But in the future, it might
be easier if AIs are doing it.
The question is to what extent our
fabrication gets very uniform and
gets really commoditized. 3D printers have been
the next big thing for at least 20 years now.
Why do they still not work all that well?
Why are they still not at the center of
manufacturing, and what comes after that?
It is funny to look at the ribosome by contrast,
which really is at the center of biology
in a whole lot of really interesting ways.
Whether or not that's the future of
manufacturing is something very simple,
where everything goes as throughput through
a bioreactor or something like that.
You send the information, and then you grow stuff,
or you have some 3D printer that actually works.
If they're good enough, then it does become much
more a pure information problem, and some of this
process knowledge becomes much less important.
Jane Street has a lot of compute, but GPUs are
very expensive, and so even optimizations
that have a relatively small effect on GPU
utilization are still extremely valuable.
Two of Jane Street's ML engineers,
Corwin and Sylvain, walked through some
of their optimization workflows at GTC.
You're not bottlenecked on the network
being too slow, you're bottlenecked on
waiting for a different rank in your
training not having completed the work.
They talked about how Jane Street profiles
traces and diagnoses bottlenecks, and then
how they solve them using techniques like CUDA
graphs and CUDA streams and custom kernels.
With these sorts of optimizations,
Corwin and Sylvain were able to
get their training steps down from 400
milliseconds to 375 milliseconds each.
This 25 millisecond difference might sound
small, but given the size of Jane Street's fleet,
that improvement could free up thousands of B200s.
Jane Street open sourced all the relevant code.
If you want to check it out, I've linked the
GitHub repo and the talk in the description below.
And if you find this stuff exciting, Jane
Street is hiring researchers and engineers.
Go to janestreet.com/dwarkesh to learn more.
Can I ask a very clumsily phrased question?
There are these deep principles
that we've discovered a couple of.
One is this idea that if there's a symmetry
across a dimension, it corresponds to a conserved
quantity. It's a very deep idea. There's
another—which you've written a lot about,
written a textbook about in fact—about ways to
understand what kinds of things you can compute,
what kinds of physical systems you can
understand with other physical systems,
what a universal computer looks like, et cetera.
Is your view that if you go down to this level of
idea of Noether's theorem or the Church-Turing
principle, that there's an infinite number
of extremely deep such principles?
Because I feel what makes them special
is that they themselves encompass so many
different possible ways the world could be.
But no, the world has to be compatible with
a couple of these very deep principles.
I don't know. All I have here
is speculation and instinct.
My instinct is that we keep finding
very fundamental new things.
It was quite formative for me to understand,
as I gave the example before, these wonderful
ideas of Church and Turing and these other
people about universal programmable devices.
Then you understand later, this also contains
within it the ideas of public-key cryptography.
Then you understand later,
that also contains within it
the ideas people refer to as cryptocurrency.
There's a very deep set of ideas there about
the ability to collectively maintain an
agreed-upon ledger, which is built upon this.
It's taken many years to figure out
the right canonical form of those.
Just this fact that you keep finding what
seem like deep new fundamental primitives
has been a very important intuition pump for me.
I've given that particular example, but I think
you see that same pattern
in a lot of different areas.
What is your interpretation then of this empirical
phenomenon where whatever input you consider into
the scientific process or technological progress…
Economists have studied this a million ways.
It just seems to require a very consistent
rate of X percent more researchers per year.
There's this famous paper from a couple years
ago by Nicholas Bloom and others where they say,
"How many people are working in the semiconductor
industry, and how has it increased over time
through the history of Moore's law?"
I think they find that Moore's law
means transistor density increases
40% a year, but to keep that going
the number of scientists has increased
9% a year, in the semiconductor industry.
They go through industry after
industry with this observation.
Is your view that there are these deep
ideas, but they keep getting harder to find?
Or is there another way to think about what's
happening with these empirical observations?
First of all, all of their examples are narrow.
They pick a particular thing, and then they
look at a particular metric. GPUs don't show up
there. All of a sudden you get this ability to
parallelize, and that's really interesting.
There are a lot of external consequences.
Basically they have these
simple quantitative measures.
They look at it in agricultural productivity.
They look at it in a whole lot of different
ways, but you do have to focus narrowly.
I'm certainly interested in the fact that
new types of progress keep becoming possible.
But I think even there, there does still seem
to be some phenomenon of diminishing returns.
Is that intrinsic? Is that something about the
structure of the world? What is it? One thing
which hasn't changed that much is the individual
minds which are doing this kind of work.
Maybe those should be improved as well,
or some feedback process going on there.
Maybe that changes the nature of things.
I look at scientific progress up until,
let's say, 1700, and it was very
slow, and also very irregular.
You had the Ionians back five centuries before
Christ doing these quite remarkable things, and so
much knowledge would get lost, and then it would
be rediscovered, and then it would be lost again.
You'd have to say that progress was very slow.
It's partially just bound up with the fact
that there were some very good
ideas that we just didn't have.
Even once you've had the ideas, you
need to build institutions around them.
You actually need to solve a whole lot of
different problems about training, allocation
of capital, and all these kinds of things.
Even just basic security for researchers,
so they're not worried about the
Inquisition or things like that.
There are all these complicated problems.
You solve all those complicated problems,
and then all of a sudden, boom, there's
a massive burst of scientific progress.
If there's some kind of stagnation, if you're
not changing those external circumstances, yes,
you may start to get diminishing returns again.
But that doesn't mean there's anything
intrinsic about the situation.
Maybe something external needs to change again.
Obviously, a lot of people think AI
is potentially going to be a driver.
It certainly will at some level.
To that extent, you can think of a lot
of modern scientific instrumentation
as really, at some level, robots.
What is the James Webb Space Telescope?
It's unconventional maybe to describe
it as a robot, but it's not
completely unreasonable either.
It is an example of a highly automated, very
sophisticated system with electronically
mediated sensors and actuators, where machine
learning is being used to process the data.
In that sense, we're already
starting to see that transition.
We've been seeing it for decades.
I have this "smoke a joint and take
a puff" thought, which—
I think we've had a few.
I think we're getting to that part of the
conversation, and then you can help me get
my foot out of my mouth and figure out
a more concrete way to think about it.
To your point that there was the Industrial
Revolution, the Enlightenment, and now there's AI,
and each might be a different pace or a
different way in which science happens.
If you think about the pace of how fast
such transitions have been happening,
you can draw over the long span of human
history this hyperbolic rate of growth that is
increasing over time as well.
A hundred thousand years ago,
you had the Stone Age.
You go back even much further, how
long have primates been around?
It would be millions of years.
A hundred thousand years ago, the Stone Age,
then ten thousand years ago, the Agricultural
Revolution, then three hundred years ago,
the Industrial Revolution, each marked by this
increase in the rate of exponential growth.
Then people think it's going
to happen again with AI.
But that would happen potentially even faster.
It would not have occurred to somebody
at the beginning of the Industrial
Revolution that the next demarcation
in this trend will be artificial intelligence.
So if things are getting faster, and it's hard
to anticipate what the next transition will be.
I guess we just think of this singularity between
now and AI as what distinguishes
the past from the future.
But applying the same heuristic that
many people in the past should have had,
maybe the "Intelligence Age" is also
quite short and the next thing after that,
we don't even have the ontology to describe
what it is, the future will not think of the
past as pre-intelligent AI and post-AI.
No, obviously we can't prove this,
but it certainly seems quite plausible.
Part of the issue is just that the substrate
we have available to conceive seems all wrong.
You can't speculate with a bunch of chimpanzees
about what it would be to have language.
Just to pick a major transition in the past,
the transition itself is the thing. It
seems likely. If we're talking about
"taking a puff" kind of thoughts, I'm certainly
amused by the idea that there's going to be some
transition involving artificial general
intelligence using classical computers.
But actually, there'll be an interesting
transition with quantum computers as well.
They're probably capable of a strictly larger
class of potentially interesting computations.
So maybe the character of AQGI,
or whatever it should be called,
is actually qualitatively different.
So maybe there's a brief period
between those two things.
As I say, this is just speculation,
but it's certainly amusing.
Is there a reason to think that?
From what I understand, for decades people
like you have put pretty tight bounds on
the kinds of things quantum computers are
going to do. It'll speed up search somewhat.
The kinds of things it speeds up extremely,
like Shor's algorithm, it seems like… Again,
maybe this is to your point that we can't predict
in advance what's down the tech tree, but at least
from here, it seems like you break encryption, but
what else are you using Shor's algorithm to do?
We've only been thinking
about it for 40 or so years.
Not for very long, and we haven't thought
that hard about it as a civilization.
Does it turn out that it's very narrow?
Maybe. Does it turn out that it's very broad?
That's also a really radical expansion
that seems distinctly possible.
Keep in mind as well, we've been doing it
without the benefit of having the devices.
That's a pretty big bottleneck to have.
If you're thinking about computer science
in the 1700s and you're like, "it can do AND/OR,
what can come out of that?" You can't anticipate
Bitcoin. You can't anticipate deep learning.
Maybe you could if you were sufficiently bright,
but it is a pretty hard situation.
What is your inside view, having been
in and contributing to quantum information and
quantum computing back in the '90s and 2000s?
What is your telling of the
history of what was the bottleneck?
What was the key transition
that made it a real field?
How do you rank the contributions from Feynman
to Deutsch to everybody else who came along?
Let's just focus on the question
about what actually changed.
Why was quantum computing not a thing in
the 1950s? It could have been. Somebody
like John von Neumann is a good example. He
was absolutely pioneering computation. He also
wrote a very important book about quantum
mechanics and was deeply interested in it.
He could have invented quantum
computing at that time,
and I think there were quite a number
of people who potentially could have.
So why do we have these papers by people
like Feynman and Deutsch in the '80s?
Those are fairly regarded as
the foundation of the field.
There are some partial anticipations a little
bit earlier, but they were nowhere near as
comprehensive and nowhere near as deep. You should
ask David. You can't ask Feynman, unfortunately,
but he'll know much better than I do.
A couple things that I think are interesting.
One is that computation became far more
salient in the late '70s and early '80s.
It just became a thing which many more people were
interested in, partially for very banal reasons.
You could go and buy a PC.
You could buy an Apple II.
You could buy a Commodore 64.
You could buy all these kinds of things.
It became apparent to people that these were very
powerful devices, very interesting to think about.
At the same time, in the quantum case,
that was also the time of the Paul
trap and the ability to trap single ions.
Up to that point, we hadn't really had the
ability to manipulate single quantum states.
You got these two separate things that
for historically contingent reasons
had both matured around 1980 or so.
Somebody like von Neumann could have had the idea
earlier, but it is quite an interesting factor.
There's a story about Richard Feynman.
He went and got one of the
first PCs around 1980 or 1981.
He was apparently so excited with this device,
he actually tripped and hurt himself quite
badly carrying his brand-new computing device.
That's a very historically contingent
coincidence, having somebody who's very
talented and understanding of quantum mechanics
also just very excited about these new machines.
It's not so surprising perhaps
that he's thinking about it then.
What similar story could you
have told 10 years earlier?
The conditions don't exist for it.
I mean, it's quite a banal story, but…
One of the things we were going to discuss was
this idea you had about the market for follow-ups.
I think this is the perfect story to
discuss it for because you wrote the
textbook about the field. "Mike and Ike" is
the definitive textbook on quantum information.
You presumably came in after Deutsch.
But you in the '90s somehow identified
it as the thing that is worth
following up on and building on.
Instead of talking about it more abstractly,
I'd love to just hear the firsthand story
of how you knew that this is the thing to do.
Of all the things that were happening in physics
and computing, how did you decide
you want to think about this problem?
Richard Feynman writes this great paper in 1982.
David Deutsch writes an absolutely fantastic
paper in 1985 sketching out a lot of the
fundamental ideas of quantum computing. I'm
11 in 1985. I'm not thinking about this.
I'm playing soccer and doing whatever.
But in 1992, I took a class on quantum mechanics
that was really terrific, given by Gerard Milburn.
I just went and asked Gerard one day
after the fifth lecture or something.
I said, "Do you have any papers or
whatever that you could give me?"
He said, "Come by my office
in a couple of days' time."
I did, and he presented me with a giant stack
of papers, which included the Deutsch paper,
the Feynman paper, and a whole bunch of other
very fundamental papers about quantum computing
and quantum information at a time when essentially
nobody in the world was working on it. He was. I
think he wrote the very first paper that proposed
a practical approach to quantum computing.
It wasn't very practical, but it
was actually in a real system.
So in some sense, I'm benefiting
from the taste of this other person.
As soon as I read the papers…
These are exciting papers.
They're asking very fundamental questions,
and you realize I can make progress here.
These are things that one
could potentially work on.
Deutsch has this conjecture, or thesis or whatever
you’d call it, that a universal model, a quantum
Turing machine, should be capable of efficiently
simulating any physical system at all.
This is a very provocative idea.
I think in that paper,
he more or less claims that he's proved it.
I'm not sure everybody would agree with that.
There are questions about whether or not you
can simulate quantum field theory effectively.
That kind of question is very
interesting and very exciting.
It's obviously a fundamental
question about the universe.
He has some wonderful ideas in there about
quantum algorithms, where they come from,
what they mean, and what they relate
to the meaning of the wave function.
Questions like this are still not
agreed upon amongst physicists.
There's just some sense of, "Oh, I am in contact
with something which is (A) deeply important,
and (B) we as a civilization don't have this."
Of course, you start to focus
your attention a little bit there.
I'm not sure I got the answer to the question…
Maybe I misunderstood the question.
Maybe I'll explain the motivation first.
In a previous conversation, we were discussing how
you could have known in the 1940s that the Shannon
theorems and Shannon's way of thinking about a
communication channel is a deep idea that goes
beyond the problems with pulse-code modulation
that Bell Labs was trying to solve at the time,
and that it applies to everything from quantum
mechanics to genetics to computer science.
One of the ideas you stated that we
didn't get a chance to talk about
yet… Shannon published this paper.
There are all these other papers,
but there's some market of follow-ups where
people gravitate to and build upon Shannon's work.
How do they realize that that's the thing
to do, and how does that process happen?
I guess you gave your local answer.
You read these papers, and you
immediately realized there's work to be
done here. There's low-hanging fruit.
There's some deep provocative idea
that I need to better understand,
and I could tractably make progress on.
To some extent, you're saying, "Okay,
I wanted to get into this game of contributing to
humanity's understanding of the universe," and you
are applying this low-hanging fruit algorithm.
You're like, "elative to my particular set of
interests and abilities, where should
I pick up my shovel and start digging?"
There it was like, "Oh, this looks like
quite a good place to start digging."
Different people, of course,
chose very differently.
It was a very unusual choice at the time. This was
1992. Very few people were thinking about that.
Fast-forwarding a bit, I don't know how
you think about your work on the open
science movement now, but did it work?
What does success there look like?
What is the movement trying to accomplish?
It's interesting. You didn't stop and define
open science there, which 20 years ago you would
have had to do. People recognize the phrase.
People have some set of associations with it.
Most often, they have a relatively simple
set of associations.
It means maybe something
about making scientific papers open access.
Very often they have some set of notions about
also making code openly available
or making data openly available.
Those are already very large successes of the open
science movement, to make those salient issues.
Those are issues on which people have opinions,
and there are relatively common arguments.
This is like the meme version: publicly
funded science should be open science.
That's a distillation of a set of ideas
which you might be able to contest.
But if you can get people actually thinking
about it and engaged with that kind of argument,
that's a very fundamental issue to be considering
in the whole political economy of science.
If you go back three centuries, there
was a very similar argument prosecuted,
which is the question: do we publicly
disclose our scientific results or not?
If you look at people like Galileo and
Kepler, the extent to which they publicly
disclosed was done in a very odd way.
Sometimes they did bizarre things where
they published some of their results as anagrams.
They'd find some discovery, write down the result
in a sentence, scramble it, and publish that.
Then if somebody else later made the same
discovery, they would unscramble the anagram
and say, "Oh, yeah, I actually did it first."
This is not an ideal foundation
for a discovery system.
It took a very long time, over a century, I think,
to obtain more or less the modern ideals, in which
you disclose the knowledge in the form of a paper.
There is an expectation of attribution, and a
reputation economy gets built. "So-and-so did this
work, so they deserve the credit for that," and
that's the basis for their careers.
This is the underlying
political economy of science.
That made a lot of sense when you have a printing
press and the ability to do scientific journals.
Then you transition to this modern situation,
where you can start to share a lot more.
You can share your code,
your data, your in-progress ideas.
But there's no direct credit associated to those.
It's not at all obvious how much reputation
should be associated to them. That's all
constructed socially. Making it a live issue
is a very important thing to have done.
I view that as one of the main positive
outcomes of work on open science.
I'll give you a really practical
example to illustrate the problem.
For a long time in physics, there was a preprint
culture in which people would upload preprints
to the preprint archive, and
in biology, this didn't happen.
There was no preprint culture. That's changing
now, but for a long time, this was the case.
I used to amuse myself by asking physicists
and biologists why this was the case.
What I would hear from biologists was they would
say, "Biology is so much more competitive than
physics that we need to protect our priority,
so we can't possibly upload to the archive.
We have to just publish in journals."
Then I would sometimes hear from physicists,
"Physics is so much more competitive
than biology that we need to establish
our priority by uploading as rapidly
as possible to the preprint archive.
We can't possibly wait to
do it with the journals."
I think this emphasizes the extent to
which this kind of attribution economy
is just something we construct.
It's something we do by agreement.
Any attempt to change that economy results in a
different system by which we construct knowledge.
There is this very fundamental set of problems
around the political economy of science.
We've got this collective project,
and how we mediate it depends upon
the economy we have around ideas.
One of the things you've emphasized
as a part of this project of open science, and we
talked about it earlier, is collective science,
or groups of people making progress on a
problem where no individual understands
all the logical and explanatory levels
necessary to make a leap or a connection.
Outside of mathematics, what is the
best example of such a discovery?
I'm not sure I have a well-ordering
of them to give you a best.
An example that I think is very
interesting is the LHC, where it's
just this immensely complicated object.
Years ago, I snuck into an accelerator
physics conference.
I didn't know anything at
all about accelerator physics, but I was just
curious to see what they were talking about.
This particular group of people
were experts on numerical methods,
in particular on inverse methods.
Inside these accelerators,
you have these cascades.
A particle will be massively accelerated, maybe
it'll be collided, and then you'll get a shower
of particles which decays and decays and decays.
There's just this incredible, consequential
shower, which is ultimately what you see
at the detector.
Then you have to
retroactively figure out what produced it.
There are these very complicated inverse
problems that need to be solved.
You've got this final data,
but you need to figure out what produced it,
and that's how you look for signatures of these.
Many of these people were incredibly
deep experts on simulation methods
for following particle tracks.
This was really deep and difficult stuff.
I was like, "Wow, you could spend a lifetime
just learning how to do this and how to solve
some of these inverse problems, and you would know
very little about quantum field theory, detector
physics, vacuum physics, or data processing,
all these things that are absolutely essential
to understanding, say, the Higgs boson".
I don't think it's possible for one person
to understand everything in depth.
Lots of people broadly understand a
lot of these ideas, but they don't understand
everything in the depth that is actually utilized.
That's why there are these papers
with well over a thousand authors.
Those people can talk to one another at a
high level, but they don't understand each
other's specialties in all that much depth.
Things like detector physics, vacuum physics,
solving inverse problems, this stuff is
incredibly different from each other.
To understand it in real detail is serious work.
How do you think about prolificness versus depth?
Maybe Darwin's an example of somebody who's
just gestating on something for many decades.
There are other examples. Einstein during the
year he comes up with special relativity is
just doing a bunch of different things.
And Pais talks about how they were all
relevant to the eventual build-up.
It's something I stress about a lot.
Sometimes I feel I'm too slow.
It's funny though, the Darwin
example is really interesting. Prolific at
what? God knows how many letters he wrote.
It must have been an enormous number.
So he was certainly very active.
There's two types of work that tend to be
involved in any kind of creative project.
There's routine stuff, and there you
just want to avoid procrastination.
You just want to ask, "How do I get good at this?"
or "How do I outsource it?" and "How do I do it as
rapidly as possible?" and just avoid getting
into a situation where you're prolonging it.
Then there's high-variance stuff where you
actually need to be willing to take a lot of time.
You need to be willing to go to different
places and talk to different people,
where in any given instance, most of
it is just not going to be an input.
Somehow balancing those two things… I
think a lot of people are very good at
doing one or the other, but it's almost like
a personality trait which one you prefer.
People tend to end up doing a lot
of one and not enough of the other.
So I certainly try and balance those two things.
Einstein is such an interesting example. 1905
is just this extraordinary year.
You can delete special relativity
entirely, and it's an extraordinary year.
You can delete special relativity, and you can
delete the photoelectric effect for which he won
the Nobel Prize, and it's still an extraordinary
year, plausibly a multi-Nobel-Prize-winning
year. So what's he doing? Maybe the answer is
just that he's smarter than the rest of us.
There's a lot of luck as well.
Certainly for myself anyway, trying to
identify those things that are routine
that I should get good at, and then just
try to do them as quickly as possible.
I think that's yielded a
certain amount of returns.
But also being willing to bet a
little bit more on myself on the
variance side has also been very, very helpful.
That's really hard, because intrinsically you're
putting yourself in situations where you
don't know what the outcome is going to be.
If you're very driven to be productive, and
actually mostly it's not working over there,
you think, "Let's reduce this." It doesn't
feel right. When I worked in San Francisco,
a practice I used to have each day was
instead of taking the 15-minute walk to work,
I would take the more beautiful 30-minute walk.
Partially just because it was beautiful, but
partially also as just a reminder that there
are real benefits to not being efficient.
But it's not an answer to your question.
Really, I think all I'm saying is
I struggle a lot with the question.
I think Dean Keith Simonton has this
famous equal odds rule where he says
the probability that any given thing you
release—any paper, book, whatever—will
be extremely important for a given person
through their lifetime is not that different.
What really determines in what era they are the
most productive is how much they're publishing.
Any given thing has equal odds
of being extremely important.
I think some of the most successful creatives
or scientists, they're just doing a lot.
Shakespeare was just publishing a lot.
Of course, then there are counterexamples. Gödel
published almost nothing. But broadly speaking,
you need a very good reason to not do that.
It's funny, I've met a lot of people
over the years who are clearly brilliant,
and they're just obsessed that they are going to
work on the great project that makes them famous,
and they never do anything. That seems connected.
It's a type of aversiveness. I think very
often they just don't want public judgment.
Something that I would love to see… There's
an awful lot of biographies and memoirs
and histories of people who achieve a lot.
I wish there was a very large
number of biographies of people
who are fantastically talented who just missed.
I've known people who won gold medals at IMOs
and things like that, who then tried to become
mathematicians and failed. What happened? What
was the reason? I suspect in many cases that's
actually more informative than anything else.
You have this essay that I was reading
before this interview about how you
think about what the work you're doing is.
And "writer" doesn't seem like the right label.
As you say, was Charles Darwin a writer? What
exactly is that label? I'm a podcaster. In a way,
obviously our work is very different,
but I also think a lot about what this
work is and how I get better at it.
In particular, how can I make sure
there's some compounding between the
different people I talk to on the podcast?
I worry that instead of this compounding, I build
up some understanding that's somewhat superficial
about a topic, and then it depreciates.
I move down to the next topic, and it depreciates.
There are a lot of podcasters in the world who
will interview way more experts than I have,
and I don't think they're much the
wiser or more knowledgeable as a result.
So it's clearly possible to mess this up.
I wonder if you have thoughts or takes or
advice on how one actually learns in
a deeper way from this kind of work.
It's an incredibly complicated and rich question.
It seems like the question is,
how do you make it a higher-growth context?
How do you make it a more demanding context?
You can do that in relatively small ways
that might yield compounding returns,
or you can do something that is more radical.
Maybe it means starting a parallel project in
which you do something that is
actually quite a bit different.
There is something really interesting
about how being very demanding can
simply change your response to something.
Something that I would sometimes do with
students and sometimes with myself,
it was really aimed more at myself,
was they would say some week, "I'm going to
try and do this work over the coming week."
Then the next week would come by
and they hadn't solved the problem.
If a million dollars had been at stake,
would you have put the same effort in?
And the answer is no, invariably.
They've tried, but they haven't really tried.
I think that's a very familiar
feeling for all of us.
You could do a lot more if you had just the right
demanding taskmaster standing by you and saying,
"Look, you're barely operating here."
I do wonder a little bit about
what's the demanding taskmaster?
What can they ask you that is going
to make your preparation way more intense?
The most helpful thing honestly is… For some
subjects it is very clear how I prep.
I'm doing an upcoming episode on chip
design with the founder of a company that does
chip design, and he wrote a textbook on it.
Yesterday I went over to his office, and we
brainstormed five roofline analyses I can do.
If I understand that, I have
some good understanding.
The problem is with almost every other
field, there's not this curriculum.
When I interviewed Ilya three, four years
ago, it was: implement the transformer,
and if you implement it, you have some nugget
of understanding you have clamped down.
With other fields, it's just that I vaguely
understand this. It's not clamped. There's
no forcing function of "do this exercise,
and if you do it, you will understand."
Really what you're saying is you can do
a good job at podcasting without actually
attaining this kind of understanding, and
that's the problem from your point of view.
You want to change your job description so that
you are internalizing these chunks and just
getting this kind of integration each time.
It seems to me that what that means is you
actually want to change the structure
of the work output at some level.
There’s this terrible idea that lots of people
have that they should be in flow all of the time.
And as far as I can tell, high performers
just don't believe this at all.
They're in flow some of the time.
You certainly see this with athletes.
When they're actually out there
playing basketball or tennis,
ideally they are in flow much of the time.
But when they're training they're not.
They're stuck a lot of the time,
or they're doing things badly.
I suppose I wonder what that looks like for you.
That I would be extremely satisfied with.
The problem is I just don't know what
the equivalent of doing 64 laps is.
This is a thing you can change by choosing
guests where there is a legible curriculum.
So maybe it's a mistake not to have done that.
Also, there's no real way to prep for Terence Tao.
There's no curriculum that's a plausible one.
There are many failure modes, but one
long-term dynamic I'm worried about is that you
can have a good podcast and reach a local maximum,
but for no particular guest or
topic are you going deep enough.
My model of learning is that if you don't really
understand the deeper mechanism, you're just
mapping inputs and outputs of a black box.
That just fades incredibly fast or is
not worth it in the first place.
You just move on and it's over.
You need to build the intermediate connection.
AI in a weird way is really easy for that reason,
because there is a clear thing you can do.
Just implement it, and then you understand it.
If I applied that criterion elsewhere,
do I just not do history episodes?
Exactly. Ada Palmer. Wonderful to
talk to, incredibly interesting.
But for you personally, what changed?
There are some things I learned.
If I had allocated more time,
especially after the interview, to
write up 2,000 words on everything I learned
and how it connects to other things I know.
Maybe that's a thing worth doing,
spreading out the episodes more
and spending more time afterwards consolidating.
I would pay infinite amounts of money if there was
somebody who was really good at coming up with the
curriculum, the practice problems you need to do,
and the exercise you need to do after the
interview to clamp what you have learned.
Have you tried doing that with somebody?
It's hard to find someone. I haven't
tried super hard, but isn't it going to be
tough to find somebody who could do that
for every single kind of discipline?
Maybe I should just hire different
ones for different topics.
Maybe. There's something about,
what problem are you solving for each episode?
As far as I can tell, that's the only way I
really understand anything. I get interested in
something. At first, I don't even have a problem,
but there's just some sense that there's some
contribution to make here, and gradually you
hone in, and there's a problem.
Funnily enough, spending time
stuck is incredibly important.
That used to just be annoying.
Now it seems like it's maybe even the
most important part of the whole process.
That hard-won nature of it means
that I internalize it afterwards.
I've written 10,000-word essays in
a couple of days, and I've written
them in three months or six months.
I feel like I didn't learn very much
from the ones that only took a couple of days.
Whereas some of the ones that took three months,
15 years later, I'll still remember.
Can you describe outside of physics how
you learn, of the ones that took three months?
By far the most common thing is there's always
some creative artifact. Sometimes it's a
class. Sometimes it's engagement with a
group of people who are working on some
collective creative artifact together.
You might not even be aware
of it, but you're acting as
an input to their creative ends in some way.
Sometimes it's an essay or a book or whatever.
It's one of the reasons why I
often quite enjoy doing podcasts.
I said yes to come here partially because I
know you ask unusually demanding questions.
That's an attempt to get this sort of perspective
from a different kind of a forcing function.
Trying to pick the most
demanding creative context.
For this interview, I went through three
lectures of the Susskind special relativity book.
The problem is that there's
almost no practice problems in it.
So I hired a physicist friend.
I haven't done it yet, but for every lecture
I want a bunch of practice problems to go through,
and I'm planning on being appropriately humbled.
How do you make it as jugular as possible?
The higher you can raise the stakes, the better.
The interview is in some
sense high stakes, but also
it doesn't necessarily test deep understanding.
I don't think the interview is that high stakes.
You're not writing a book about special
relativity, and you're not trying to write a
book that replaces whatever the existing standard
textbook is. That's a really high stake. By the
way, a phrase that I find particularly difficult.
People will talk about "going deep" on a subject,
and it turns out different people have
different ideas of what this means.
For some people it means they
read a couple of blog posts.
For some people it means
they read a book about it.
they wrote a book about it.
The standard you hold yourself
to determines a lot about your
ability to integrate knowledge in this way.
I found that I'm in some sense able to move
much faster on some things through the help of
AI, but I don't know if I'm learning better.
I think it's probably because… The hardest
thing, the thing that is most demanding,
is so aversive that you try to take
any excuse you can to get out of it.
Just having a back-and-forth conversation
with an LLM where you gloss over…
It’s entertaining but not
necessarily anything else.
It’s such an easy way to get out of the thing.
In fact, it makes it easier because instead
of doing some intermediate thinking, there's
always a next question you can ask a chatbot.
Yeah. And it's somewhat valuable. That’s part of
the seductiveness, of course. It's not actually
useless. But it can substitute for actually
doing the thing that maybe you should be doing.
It’s interesting. To what extent should
you be outsourcing that kind of stuff?
It’s an interesting judgment call. There is a
whole bunch of routine work that you want done.
It's low value for you, so if you can
get a chatbot to do it, you may as well.
Somebody interviewed the pioneering
computer scientist Alan Kay years ago,
and he was asked what he thought about Linux.
If I remember his answer correctly, he basically
said, "It doesn't have anything
to do with computer science.
It's just a great big ball of mud.
There are a few interesting ideas
in there which are worth understanding, but
mostly all you're learning is stuff about Linux.
You're not actually learning
anything which is transferable."
I thought that was very interesting.
There's a certain kind of seductiveness
to some things where it's sort
of a Rube Goldberg machine.
You can just learn about all the
bits, and it feels entertaining.
But if you step back and think about
what you're actually doing here,
it might not actually be meeting your objectives.
Maybe you want to become a sysadmin, and learning
Linux is a great use of your time.
There's no harm in that at all.
But if your objective is to understand the
fundamentals of computing, it's much less
clear that that's a good use of your time.
It was certainly an answer I've thought a
lot about, where for a certain type of mind,
there is a seductiveness in just learning
systems and confusing that with understanding.
Okay, I'll keep you updated on how this goes.
I owe you a text within a month
of some revamped learning system.
I'd be really curious. It's also true
that tiny incremental improvements
in this are just worth so much.
It's the main input into the podcast.
It's great that the bookshelves are fancy
and I've got a blackboard or whatever,
but really the thing that makes the podcast
better is if I can improve the learning I do.
So yes, it's worth every morsel of improvement.
All right, thanks for the therapy session. Great
note to end on. Thanks, Michael.
All right. Thanks, Dwarkesh.