Today, I'm chatting with Terence
Tao, who needs no introduction.
Terence, I want to begin by having you retell
the story of how Kepler discovered the laws of
planetary motion because I think this will be a
great jumping off point to talk about AI for math.
I've always had an amateur interest in astronomy.
I've loved stories of how the early astronomers
worked out the nature of the universe.
Kepler was building on the work of Copernicus, who
was himself building on the work of Aristarchus.
Copernicus very famously proposed the
heliocentric model, that instead of the
planets and the Sun going around the Earth, the
Sun was at the center of the solar system and the
other planets were going around the Sun.
Copernicus proposed that the orbits of
the planets were perfect circles.
His theory fit the observations
that the Greeks, the Arabs, and the
Indians had worked out over centuries.
Kepler learned about these theories in his
studies, and he made this observation that the
ratios of the size of the orbits that Copernicus
predicted seemed to have some geometric meaning.
He started proposing that if you take the orbit
of the Earth and you enclose it in a cube,
the outer sphere that encloses the cube almost
perfectly matched the orbit of Mars, and so forth.
There were six planets known at the time and five
gaps between them, and there were five perfect
Platonic solids: the cube, the tetrahedron,
icosahedron, octahedron, and dodecahedron.
So he had this theory, which he
thought was absolutely beautiful,
that you could inscribe these Platonic
solids between the spheres of the planets.
It seemed to fit, and it seemed to him that
God's design of the planets was matching this
mathematical perfection of the Platonic solids.
He needed data to confirm this theory.
At the time, there was only one really
high-quality dataset in existence.
Tycho Brahe, this very wealthy,
eccentric Danish astronomer,
had managed to convince the Danish government
to fund this extremely expensive observatory.
In fact, it was an entire island where he had
taken decades of observations of all the planets,
like Mars and Jupiter, at least every night for
which the weather was clear, with the naked eye.
He was the last of the naked-eye astronomers.
He had all this data which Kepler
could use to confirm his theory.
Kepler started working with Tycho,
but Tycho was very jealous of the data.
He only gave him little bits of it at a time.
Kepler eventually just stole the data.
He copied it and had to have a fight with
Brahe's descendants.
He did get the data,
and then he worked out, to his disappointment,
that his beautiful theory didn't quite work.
The data was off from his Platonic
solid theory by 10% or something.
He tried all kinds of fudges, moving the
circles around, and it didn't quite work.
But he worked on this problem for years and years,
and eventually, he figured out how to use the data
to work out the actual orbits of the planets.
That was an incredibly clever,
genius amount of data analysis.
And then he worked out that the
orbits were actually ellipses, not
circles, which was shocking for him.
So he worked out the two laws of planetary
motion: the ellipses, and also that equal
areas sweep out equal times.
Then ten years later, after
collecting a lot of data—the furthest planets
like Saturn and Jupiter were the hardest for
him to work out—he finally worked out this
third law, that the time it takes for a
planet to complete its orbit was proportional
to some power of the distance to the Sun.
These are the three famous
Kepler's laws of motion.
He had no explanation for them.
It was all driven by experiment,
and it took Newton a century later to give a
theory that explained all three laws at once.
The take I want to try on you is that
Kepler was a high-temperature LLM.
Newton comes up with this explanation of why
the three laws of planetary motion must be true.
Of course, the way that Kepler discovers
the laws of planetary motion, or figures
out the relative orbits of the different
planets, is as you say a work of genius.
But through his career, he's
just trying random relationships.
In fact, in the book in which he writes
down the third law of planetary motion,
it's an aside on The Harmonics of the World,
which is just a book about how all these different
planets have these different harmonies.
And the reason there's so much famine
and misery on Earth is because the Earth
is mi-fa-mi, that's the note of Earth.
It's all this random astrology, but
in there is the cube-square law,
which tells you what relationship the period
has to a planet's distance from the Sun.
As you were detailing, if you add that to
Newton's F=ma and the equation for centripetal
acceleration, you get the inverse-square law.
And so Newton works that out.
But the reason I think this is an interesting
story is that I feel LLMs can do the kind of
thing of trying random relationships for
twenty years, some of which make no sense,
as long as there's a verifiable data bank like
Brahe's dataset. "Ok, I'm going to try out random
things about musical notes, Platonic objects,
or different geometries, I have this bias that
there's some important thing about the geometry
of these orbits." Then one thing works. As long
as you can verify it, these empirical regularities
can then drive actual deep scientific progress.
Traditionally, when we talk about the
history of science, idea generation has
always been the prestige part of science.
A scientific problem comes with many steps.
You have to identify a problem, and then you have
to identify a good, fruitful problem to work on.
Then you need to collect data,
figure out a strategy to analyze
the data, and make a hypothesis.
At this point, you need to propose a
good hypothesis, and then you need to validate.
Then you need to write things up and explain.
There are a dozen different components.
The ones we celebrate are these eureka
genius moments of idea generation.
Kepler certainly had to cycle through
many ideas, several of which didn't work.
I bet there were many that he didn't even
publish at all because they just didn't fit.
That's an important part of the process,
trying all kinds of random
things and seeing if they worked.
But as you say, it has to be matched by an equal
amount of verification, otherwise it's slop.
We celebrate Kepler, but we should also
celebrate Brahe for his assiduous data
collection, which was ten times more
precise than any previous observation.
That extra decimal point of accuracy was
essential for Kepler to get his results.
He was using Euclidean geometry and the
most advanced mathematics he could use at
the time to match his models with the data.
All aspects had to be in play: the data,
the theory, and the hypothesis generation.
I'm not sure nowadays that hypothesis
generation is the bottleneck anymore.
Science has changed in the century since.
Classically, the two big paradigms for
science were theory and experiment.
Then in the 20th century, numerical
simulation came along, so you can do
computer simulations to test theories.
Finally, in the late 20th century,
we had big data.
We had the era of data analysis.
A lot of new progress is actually driven
now by analyzing massive datasets first.
You collect large datasets and then draw
patterns from them to deduce thoughts.
This is a little bit different from how
science used to work, where you make a
few observations or have one out-of-the-blue
idea, and then collect data to test your idea.
That's the classic scientific method. Now it's
almost reversed. You collect big data first,
and then you try to get hypotheses from it.
Kepler was maybe one of the first early
data scientists, but even he didn't start
with Tycho's dataset and then analyze it.
He had some preconceived theories first.
It seems like this is less and less the
way we make progress, just because the
data is so much more massive and useful.
Oh, interesting. I feel like the 20th-century
science that you're describing actually very
well describes what happened with Kepler.
He did have these ideas—1595 and '96 is where
he comes up with the polygons and then the
Platonic objects theory—but they were wrong.
Then a few years later, he gets Brahe's data,
and it's only after twenty years of trying random
things that he gets this empirical regularity.
It actually feels a bit closer to Brahe's data
being analogous to some massive data bank of
simulations, and now that you've got the data,
you can keep trying random things.
If it wasn't for that, Kepler would be
out there just writing books about harmonics
and Platonic objects, and there would be
nothing to actually verify against.
The data was extremely important. The
distinction I was trying to make was that
traditionally, you make a hypothesis and
then you test it against data.
But now with machine learning,
data analysis, and statistics, you can
start with data and through statistics
work out laws that were not present before.
Kepler's third law is a little bit like this,
except that instead of having the thousand data
points that Brahe had, Kepler had six data points.
For every planet, he knew the length of
the orbit and the distance to the Sun.
There were five or six data points, and
he did what we would now call regression.
He fit a curve to these six data points and
got a square-cube law, which was amazing.
But he was quite lucky that these six
data points gave him the right conclusion.
That's not enough data to be really reliable.
There was a later astronomer, Johann Bode,
who took the same data—the distances
to the planets—and inspired by Kepler,
he had a prediction that the distances to the
planets formed a shifted geometric progression.
He also fit a curve, except
there was one point missing.
There was a big gap between Mars and Jupiter.
His law predicted that there was a missing planet.
It was kind of a crank theory, except
when Uranus was discovered by Herschel,
the distance to Uranus fit exactly this pattern.
Then Ceres was discovered in the asteroid belt,
and it also fit the pattern.
People got really excited that Bode had
discovered this amazing new law of nature.
But then Neptune was discovered,
and it was way off.
Basically it was just a numerical fluke.
There were six data points. Maybe one reason
why Kepler didn't highlight his third law as
much as the first two laws is that instinctively,
even though he didn't have modern statistics,
he kind of knew that with six data points, he had
to be somewhat tentative with the conclusions.
To ask the question about the analogy more
explicitly, does this analogy make sense if
in the future we have smarter and smarter AIs?
We'll have millions of them, and they can go out
and hunt for all these empirical irregularities.
It sounds like you don't think the bottleneck
in science is finding more things that
are the equivalent of the third law of
planetary motion for each given field,
so that later on somebody can say, "Oh,
we need a way to explain this. Let's work out the
math. Here's the inverse-square law of gravity."
I think AI has driven the cost of
idea generation down to almost zero,
in a very similar way to how the internet drove
the cost of communication down to almost zero.
It’s an amazing thing, but it doesn't create
abundance by itself. Now the bottleneck is
different. We're now in a situation where
suddenly people can generate thousands of
theories for a given scientific problem.
Now we have to verify them, evaluate them.
This is something which we have to change our
structures of science to actually sort this
out. Traditionally, we build walls. In the past,
before we had AI slop, we had amateur scientists
have their own theories of the universe,
many of which were of very little value.
We built these peer review publication
systems to filter out and try to isolate
the high signal ideas to test.
But now that we can generate these
possible explanations at massive scale, and
some of them are good and a lot are terrible,
human reviewers are already being overwhelmed.
Many journals are reporting that AI-generated
submissions are just flooding their submissions.
It's great that we can generate all kinds of
things now with AI, but it means that the rest
of the aspects of science have to catch up:
verification, validation, and assessing
what ideas actually move the subject forward
and which ones are dead ends or red herrings.
That's not something we know how to do at scale.
For each individual paper, we can
have a debate among scientists
and get to a consensus in a few years.
But when we're generating a thousand of
these every day, this doesn't work.
There's this incredibly interesting
question. If you have billions of AI
scientists, not only how do you gauge
which ones are real progress, but how do you...
This is actually a question that human science
has had to face and we've solved somehow,
and I’m actually not sure how we solved this.
Let's say in the 1940s, if you're at Bell Labs
and there are these new technologies coming out.
Pulse-code modulation, how do you transfer
signals? How do you digitize signals?
How do you transfer them over analog wires?
There are all these papers about the engineering
constraints and the details, and then there's one
which comes up with the idea of the bit, which has
implications across many different fields.
You need some system which can then look
at that and say, "Okay, we need
to apply this to probability.
We need to apply this to
computer science," et cetera.
In the future, the AIs are coming up with
the next version of this unifying concept.
How would you identify it among millions of papers
that might actually constitute progress, but which
have much less in terms of general unifying ideas?
A lot of it's the test of time.
Many great ideas didn't actually get a great
reception at the time they were first proposed.
It was only after some other scientists
realized that they could take it further
and apply them to their own...
Deep learning itself was a
niche area of AI for a long time.
The idea of getting answers entirely
through training on data and not through first
principles reasoning was very controversial,
and it just took a long time before it started
bearing fruit. You mentioned the bit. There were
other proposals for computer architectures
than the zero-one that is universal today.
I think there were trits, three-valued logic.
In an alternate universe,
maybe a different paradigm would have shown up.
The transformer, for example, is the foundation of
all modern large language models, and it was the
first deep learning architecture that really was
sophisticated enough to capture language.
But it didn't have to be that way.
There could've been some other architecture that
was the first to do it and once that was adopted,
it would become the standard.
One reason why it's hard to
assess whether a given idea is going to be
fruitful is that it depends on the future.
It depends also on the culture and society,
which ones get adopted, which ones don't.
The base ten numeral system in mathematics
is extremely useful, much better than
the Roman numeral system, for instance.
But again, there's nothing special about ten.
It's a system that is useful for us
because everyone else uses it. We've
standardized it. We've built all our
computers and our number representation
systems around it, so we're stuck with it now.
Some people occasionally push for other systems
than decimal, but there's just too much inertia.
It's not something where you can look at any given
scientific achievement purely in isolation and
give it an objective grade without being aware
of the context both in the past and the future.
So it may never be something that you can
just reinforcement learn the same way that
you can for much more localized problems.
Often in the history of science when a new theory
comes up that in retrospect we realize is correct,
it seems to make implications that either
make no sense because they're wrong, and we
realize later on why they're wrong, or they're
correct but seem wildly implausible at the time.
As you talked about, Aristarchus had
heliocentrism in the third century BC.
The ancient Athenians were like, "This can't be
because if the earth is going around the sun,
we should see the relative position of the stars
change as we're going around the sun, and the only
way that wouldn't be the case is if they're so
far away that you don't notice any parallax,"
which is actually the correct implication.
But there's times when the implication is
incorrect and we just need to graduate
to a better level of understanding.
Leibniz would chide Newton and disagree with
Newton's theory of gravity on the basis that
it implied action at a distance, and they
didn't know the mechanism, and Newton himself
was sort of stunned that inertial mass and
gravitational mass were the same quantity.
All these things later were resolved by
Einstein. But it was still progress. So
the question for a system of peer review for
AI would be: even if you can falsify a theory,
how would you notice that it still constitutes
progress relative to the thing before?
Often, the ultimately correct theory
initially is worse in many ways.
Copernicus's theory of the planets was
less accurate than Ptolemy's theory.
Geocentrism had been developed for a
millennium by that point, and they had
made many tweaks and increasingly complicated
ad hoc fixes to make it more and more accurate.
Copernicus's theory was a lot
simpler but much less accurate.
It was only Kepler that made it
more accurate than Ptolemy's theory.
Science is always a work in progress.
When you only get part of the solution,
it looks worse than a theory which is incorrect
but somehow has been completed to the point
where it kind of answers all the questions.
As you say, Newton's theory had big mysteries.
They had the equivalence of mass
and action at a distance, which
were only resolved with a very conceptually
different approach centuries afterwards.
Often progress has to be made not by
adding more theories, but by deleting
some assumptions that you have in your mind.
One reason why geocentrism held on for so long
is we had this idea that objects
naturally want to stay at rest.
This is the Aristotelian notion of physics,
and so the idea that the Earth was moving…
How come we weren't all falling over?
Once you have Newton's laws of motion—an
object in motion remains in motion
and so forth—then it makes sense.
Conceptually, it's a very big leap to
realize that the Earth is in motion.
It doesn't feel like it's in motion.
The biggest advances, like Darwin's
theory of evolution, is the idea
that species are not static.
This is not obvious because you
don't see evolution in your lifetime.
Well, now we actually can, but
it seems permanent and static.
Right now we're going through a cognitive version
of the Copernican revolution, where we used to
think that human intelligence is the center of
the universe, and now we're seeing that there are
very different types of intelligence out there
with very different strengths and weaknesses.
Our assessment of which tasks require
intelligence, which ones don't,
has to be reordered quite a bit.
Trying to fit AI into our theories
of scientific progress and what is hard and
what is easy, we're struggling quite a lot.
We have to ask questions that we've
never really had to ask before.
Or maybe the philosophers had, but
now we all have to deal with it.
This brings up a topic I've
been very curious about.
You mentioned Darwin's theory of evolution.
There's this book, The Clockwork Universe
by Edward Dolnick, which covers a lot of
this era of history we're talking about.
He has this interesting observation in there.
The Origin of Species was published in 1859.
Principia Mathematica was published in 1687.
So The Origin of Species comes out two centuries
after Principia.
Conceptually,
it seems like Darwin's theory is simpler.
There's a contemporaneous biologist to Darwin,
Thomas Huxley, who reads The Origin of Species and
he says, "How stupid not to have thought of that."
Nobody ever says that about
Principia, chiding themselves
for not having beaten Newton to gravity.
So there's a question of why did it take longer?
It seems like a big part of the
reason is what you were saying.
The evidence for natural selection is overwhelming
in a certain sense, but it's cumulative and
retrospective, whereas Newton can
just say, "Here are my equations.
Let me see the moon's orbital
period and its distance,
and if it lines up, then we've made progress."
Lucretius actually had this idea that species
adapted to their environment in the first
century BC but nobody really talks about it
until Darwin because Lucretius couldn't run some
experiment and force people to pay attention.
I wonder if we'll in retrospect end up seeing
much more progress in domains which have this
kind of tight data loop where you can
verify them quite easily, even though
they're conceptually much more difficult.
I think one aspect of science is that it's not
just creating a new theory and validating
it, but communicating it to others.
Darwin was an amazing science communicator.
He wrote in English, in natural language. I'm
speaking like a—
No Lean.
I have to get out of my technical mindset.
He spoke in plain English, didn't use equations,
and he synthesized a lot of disparate facts.
Little pieces of evolution had been worked out in
the past, but he had this very compelling vision.
Again, he was still missing things.
He didn't know the mechanism for
heredity, he didn't have DNA.
But his writing style was persuasive, and
that helped a lot. Newton wrote in Latin.
He had invented entire new areas of
mathematics just to explain what he was doing.
He was also from an era where scientists
were much more secretive and competitive.
Academia is still competitive, but it
was even worse back in Newton's day.
He held back some of his best insights because
he didn't want his rivals to get any advantage.
He was also a somewhat unpleasant
person from what I gather.
It was only a couple of decades after Newton
when other scientists explained his work in
much simpler terms that they became widespread.
The art of exposition and making a case and
creating a narrative is also a
very important part of science.
If you have the data, it helps, but people need
to be convinced, otherwise they will not push
it further or take the initial investment
to learn your theory and really explore it.
That's another thing which is really
hard to reinforcement learn on.
How can you score how persuasive you are?
Well, there are entire marketing
departments trying to do this.
Maybe it's good that AI is not
yet optimized to be persuasive.
There's a social aspect to science.
Even though we pride ourselves on having an
objective side to it, where there's data and
experiment and validation, we still have
to tell stories and convince our fellow
scientists. That's a soft, squishy thing. It's
a combination of data and painting a narrative,
and it's a narrative of gaps.
Even with Darwin, as I said, there
were pieces of his theory he could not explain.
But he could still make a case that in the future,
people would find transitional
forms, that they would find the
mechanism of inheritance, and they did.
I don't know how you can quantify that
in such a precise way that you can
start doing reinforcement learning.
Maybe that will be forever
the human side of science.
One takeaway I had from reading and watching your
stuff on the cosmic distance ladder… By the way,
I highly recommend people watch your series
with 3Blue1Brown on the cosmic distance ladder.
One takeaway was that the deductive
overhang in many fields could be
so much bigger than people realize.
If you just had the right insight about
how to study a problem, you might be surprised
at how much more you could learn about the world.
I wonder if you think that's a product
of astronomy at the particular times
in history that you're studying.
Or is it just that based on the data
that is incident on the Earth right now, we could
actually divine a lot more than we happen to know?
Astronomy was one of the first sciences to
really embrace data analysis and squeezing
every last possible drop of information out
of the information they had because data was
the bottleneck. It still is the bottleneck.
It's really hard to collect astronomical data.
Astronomers are world-class in
extracting all kinds of conclusions
from little traces of data, almost like Sherlock.
I hear that for a lot of quant hedge funds, their
preferred hire is an astronomy PhD, actually.
They are also very interested for other reasons
in extracting signals from
various random bits of data.
Okay, speaking of clever ideas,
one of my listeners, Shawn,
solved the puzzle that Jane Street made for my
audience and posted a great walkthrough on X.
For context, Jane Street trained a ResNet,
shuffled all 96 layers, and then challenged
people to put them back in the right order using
only the model's outputs and training data.
You can't brute force this – there's more
possible orderings than atoms in the universe.
So Shawn broke the problem
into two different parts.
First, pair the layers into 48 different blocks.
And second, put those blocks in the right order.
For pairing, Shawn realized that in
a well-trained ResNet, the product of
two weight matrices in a residual block should
have a distinctive negative diagonal pattern.
This arises as a way for the model to keep the
residual stream from growing out of control.
From this insight, he was able
to recover the right pairings.
For ordering, Shawn noticed that the model
seemed to improve if he sorted the blocks by
the size of their residual contributions.
Starting with that rough approximation,
he combined a clever ranking heuristic with
local swaps to recover the exact right order.
His full walkthrough is linked in the description.
Don't worry if you didn't get
to this puzzle in time, though.
There's still one up about backdoored LLMs that
even Jane Street doesn't know how to solve.
You can find it at janestreet.com/dwarkesh.
Alright, back to Terence!
We do under-explore how to extract
extra information from various signals.
Just to pick one random study, I remember reading
once that people were trying to measure how often
scientists actually read the papers
that they cite. How do you measure
this? You could try to survey different
scientists, but they had a clever trick.
Many citations have little typos, like a
number is wrong or punctuation is almost wrong.
They measured how often a typo got copied
from one reference to the next, and they
could infer whether an author was just copying and
pasting a reference without actually checking it.
From that, they were able to infer some measure
of how much attention people were paying.
So there are some clever tricks to extract…
These questions you posed earlier of how
we can assess whether a scientific development
is fruitful, interesting, or represents real
progress… Maybe there are really useful metrics
or footprints of this phenomenon in data.
We can examine citations and how often
something is mentioned in a conference.
Maybe there's a lot of sociology of science
research to be done that could actually
detect these things.
Maybe we should get
some astronomers on the case, actually.
That brings us nicely to the progress that, from
the outside, it seems like AI for math is making.
You had a post recently where you pointed out
that over the last few months,
AI programs have solved fifty
out of the eleven hundred odd Erdős problems.
I don’t know if it’s still correct, but as of
a month ago you said that there had been a pause
because the low-hanging fruit had been picked.
First of all, I'm curious if that is still the
case, that we have picked the low-hanging fruit
and now we're at this plateau currently.
It does seem so. Fifty-odd problems have
been solved with AI assistance, which is
great, but there's like six hundred to go.
People are still chipping away
at one or two of these right now.
We're seeing a lot fewer pure AI solutions
now where the AI just one-shots the problem.
There was a month where that happened and
that has stopped, not for lack of trying.
I know of three separate attempts to get
frontier model AIs to just attack every
single one of the problems simultaneously.
They pick out some minor observations,
or maybe they find that some problem was already
solved in the literature, but there hasn't been
any further purely AI-powered solution yet.
People are using AI a lot currently.
Someone might use AI to generate a possible
proof strategy, and then another person will
use a separate AI tool to critique it, rewrite
it, generate some numerical data for it,
or do a literature survey.
Some problems have been solved
by an ongoing conversation between
lots of humans and lots of AI tools.
But it does seem like it was this one-off thing.
Maybe one analogy for these problems is
that you're in some sort of mountain
range with all kinds of cliffs and walls.
Maybe there's a little wall which is three
feet high, and one that's six feet high,
and then there's fifteen feet high, and
then there are some mile-high cliffs.
You're trying to climb as many of these
cliffs as possible, but it's in the dark.
We don't know which ones are
tall, which ones are short.
So we try to light some candles
and make some maps, and slowly we
figure out some of them are climbable.
Some of them we can identify a partial
track in the wall that you can reach first.
These AI tools, they're like jumping
machines that can jump two meters
in the air, higher than any human.
Sometimes they jump in the wrong
direction, and sometimes they crash,
but sometimes they can reach the tops of the
lowest walls that we couldn't reach before.
We've just set them loose in this
mountain range, hopping around.
There was this exciting period where they could
actually find all the low ones and reach them.
Maybe the next time there's a big
advance in the models, they will
try it again, and a few more will be breached.
But it's a different style of doing mathematics.
Normally we would hill climb, make little
markers, and try to identify partial things.
These tools either succeed or they fail.
They've been really bad at creating partial
progress or identifying intermediate
stages that you should focus on first.
Going back to this previous discussion, we
don't have a way of evaluating partial progress
the same way we can evaluate a one-shot
success or failure of solving a problem.
There's two different ways to think
through what you've just said.
One of them is more bearish on AI
progress, and one of them is more bullish.
The bearish one being, "Oh, they're only
getting to a certain height of wall,
which is not as high as humans are reaching."
The second is that they have this powerful
property that once they achieve a certain
waterline, they can fill every single problem
that is available at that waterline,
which we simply can't do with humans.
We can't make a million copies of you
and give each of them a million dollars
of inference compute and have you do a hundred
years of subjective time research on a million
different problems at the same time.
But once AIs reach Terence Tao-level,
they could do that.
Once they reach intermediate levels,
they could do the intermediate version of that.
The same reason that we should be bearish now is
the reason we should be especially bullish.
Not even when they achieve superhuman
intelligence, but just when they
achieve human-level intelligence,
because their human-level intelligence
is qualitatively wider and more powerful
than our human-level intelligence.
I agree. They excel at breadth,
and humans excel at depth, human experts at
least. I think they're very complementary.
But our current way of doing math and science
is focused on depth because that's where human
expertise is, because humans can't do breadth.
We have to redesign the way we do science to take
full advantage of this breadth
capability that we now have.
We should have a lot more effort in creating
very broad classes of problems to work on rather
than one or two really deep, important problems.
We should still have the deep, important problems,
and humans should still be working on them.
But now we have this other way of doing science.
We can explore entirely new fields of
science by first getting these broad,
moderately competent AIs to map it out
and make all the easy observations.
And then identify certain islands of difficulty,
which human experts can then come and work on.
I see very much a future of
very complementary science.
Eventually, you would hope to get both breadth
and depth and somehow get the best of both worlds.
But we need practice with the breadth side.
It's too new. We don't even have the paradigms
to really take full advantage of it.
But we will, and then science will be
unrecognizable after that, I think.
To this point about complementarity,
programmers have noticed that they're way
more productive as a result of these AI tools.
I don't know if you as a mathematician
feel the same way, but it does seem
like one big difference between vibe coding
and vibe researching is that with software,
the whole point is to have some
effect on the world through your work.
If it leads to you better understanding
a problem or coming up with some clean
abstraction to embody in your code,
that is instrumental to the end goal.
Whereas with research, the reason we care
about solving the Millennium Prize Problems
is that presumably that in the process of
solving them, we discover new mathematical
objects or new techniques that advance our
civilization's understanding of mathematics.
So the proof is instrumental
to the intermediate work.
I don't know if you agree with that dichotomy
or if that in any way will explain the relative
uplift we'll see in software versus research.
Certainly in math, the process is often more
important than the problem itself.
The problem is kind of a proxy
for measuring progress.
I think even in software,
there are different types of software tasks.
If you just create a webpage that does the same
thing that a thousand other webpages
do, there's no skill to be learned.
Well, there is still some skill maybe that
the individual programmer could pick up.
But for boilerplate-type code, it's something
that you should definitely offload to AI.
Sometimes once you make the code,
you still have to maintain it.
There are issues with upgrading it and
making it compatible with other things.
I've heard programmers report that even
if an AI can create the first prototype
of a tool, making it mesh with everything
else and making it interact with the real
world in the way they want is an ongoing process.
If you don't have the skills that you pick up from
writing the code, that may impact your
ability to maintain it down the road.
So yes, certainly mathematicians, we've used
problems to build intuition and to train people
to have a good idea of what's true, what to
expect, what is provable, and what is difficult.
Just getting the answers right away
may actually inhibit that process.
I made a distinction between
theory and experiment before.
In most sciences, there's an equal
division between the theoretical side
and the experimental side.
Math has been unique in
that it's almost entirely theoretical.
We place a premium on trying to have coherent,
clean theories of why things are true and false.
We haven't done many experiments as to,
if we have two different ways to solve
a problem, which is more effective.
We have some intuition, but we haven't done
large-scale studies where we take a thousand
problems and just test them.
But we can do that now.
I think AI-type tools will actually
revolutionize the experimental side of math,
where you don't care so much about individual
problems and the process of solving them,
but you want to gather large-scale data
about what things work and what things don't.
The same way that if you're a software
company and you want to roll out a thousand
pieces of software, you don't really want to
handcraft each one and learn lessons from each.
You just want to find what
workflows let you scale.
The idea of doing mathematics
at scale is at its infancy.
But that's where AI is really
going to revolutionize the subject.
I feel like a big crux in these conversations
about how good AI will be for science is,
I think you said this, that they're using
existing techniques and modifying them.
It would be interesting to
understand how much progress one
can make simply from using existing techniques.
If I looked at the top math journals, how many of
the papers are coming up with a new technique,
whatever that means, versus using existing
techniques on new problems? What is the overhang?
If you just applied every known technique to every
open problem, would that constitute a humongous
uplift in our civilization's knowledge, or would
that not be that impressive and useful?
This is a great question, and we don't
have the data to fully answer it yet.
Certainly, a lot of work that human
mathematicians do… When you take a new problem,
one of the first things we do is we look at all
the standard things that have worked on similar
problems in the past, and we try them one by one.
Sometimes that works, and that's still worth
publishing because the question was important.
Sometimes they almost work,
and you have to add one more
wrinkle to it, and that's also interesting.
But the papers that go into the top journals
are usually ones where the existing methods
can kind of solve 80% of the problem, but then
there is this 20% which is resistant and a new
technique has to be invented to fill in the gaps.
It's very rare now that a problem gets
solved with no reliance on past literature,
where all the ideas come out of nowhere.
That was more common in the past,
but math is so mature now that it's just so much
of a handicap to not use the literature first.
AI tools are getting really good at the
first part of that, just trying all the
standard techniques on a problem, often making
fewer mistakes in applying them than humans.
They still make mistakes, but I've tested
these tools on little tasks that I can do,
and sometimes they pick up errors that I make.
Sometimes I pick up errors that they make.
It's about a tie right now.
But I haven't yet seen them take the next step.
When there are holes in the argument where none
of the things are working, then what do you do?
They can suggest random things, but often
I find that trying to chase them down to
make them work, and finding they don't
work, wastes more time than it saves.
I think some fraction of problems that
we currently think are hard will fall
from this method, especially the ones
that haven't received enough attention.
With the Erdős problems, almost all of the 50
problems that were solved by AIs were ones for
which there was basically no literature.
Erdős posed the problem once or twice.
Maybe some people tried it casually and couldn't
do it, but they never wrote up anything.
But it turned out that there was a solution,
and it was just combining this one obscure
technique that not many people know about
with some other result in the literature.
That's the median level of what AI can
accomplish, and that's really great.
It clears out 50 of these problems.
So I think you will see some isolated successes.
But what we found… Some people have done
large-scale sweeps of these Erdős problems.
If you only focus on the success
stories, the ones that get broadcast
on social media, it looks amazing.
All these problems that haven't been
solved for decades, now they're falling.
But whenever we do a systematic study,
on any given problem an AI tool has
a success rate of maybe 1% or 2%.
It's just that they can buy scale, and you
just pick the winners. It looks great. I
think there'll be a similar thing happening
with the hundreds of really prestigious,
difficult math problems out there.
Some AI may get lucky and actually solve them,
and there will be some backdoor to solve
the problem that everyone else missed.
That will get a lot of publicity.
But then people will try these fancy
tools on their own favorite problem, and they
will again experience the 1% to 2% success rate.
There'll be a lot of noise amongst the signal
of when they're working and when they're not.
It will be increasingly important to
collect these really standardized datasets.
There are efforts now to create a standard set of
challenge problems for AIs to solve, and not just
rely on the AI companies to only publish their
wins and not disclose their negative results.
That will maybe give more clarity
as to where we're actually at.
Although I think it's worth emphasizing how
much progress in AI it constitutes already,
to have models that are capable of applying
some technique that nobody had written down
as applicable to this particular problem.
The progress is simultaneously amazing
and disappointing.
It is a very strange
feeling to see these tools in action.
But people also acclimatize really quickly.
I remember when Google's web
search came out 20 years ago.
It just blew all the other
searches out of the water.
You're getting relevant hits on the
front page, exactly what you wanted.
It was amazing, and then after
a few years, you just took for
granted that you could Google anything.
2026-level AI would be stunning in 2021.
A lot of it—face recognition, natural speech,
doing college-level math problems—we just
take for granted now.
Speaking of 2026 AI,
you made a prediction in 2023 that by 2026
it would be like a colleague in mathematics?
A trustworthy co-author if used correctly.
Which is looking pretty good in retrospect.
Yeah, I'm pretty pleased.
So let's see if you can continue this streak.
You personally are 2x more
productive as a result of AI.
What year would you say that?
Productivity, I think,
is not quite a one-dimensional quantity.
I'm definitely noticing that the style
in which I do mathematics is changing
quite a bit, and the type of things I do.
For example, my papers now have a
lot more code, a lot more pictures,
because it's so easy to generate these things now.
Some plot which would have taken me hours to do,
now I can do in minutes.
But in the past, I just wouldn't have
put the plot in my paper in the first place.
I would just talk about it in words.
So it's hard to measure what 2x means.
On the one hand, I think the type of
papers that I would write today, if I
had to do them without AI assistance,
would definitely take five times longer.
But I would not write my papers that way.
5x?
Yeah, but these are auxiliary tasks.
Things like doing a much deeper literature
search or supplying a lot more numerics.
They enrich the paper. The core of what I do,
actually solving the most difficult part of a
math problem, hasn't changed too much.
I still use pen and paper for that.
But there's lots of silly things.
I use an AI agent now to reformat.
Sometimes if all my parentheses are not quite
the right size, I used to manually change them
by hand, and now I can get an AI agent to
do all that quite nicely in the background.
They've really sped up lots of secondary tasks.
They haven't yet sped up the core thing that I do,
but it's allowed me to add
more things to my papers.
By the same token, if I were to write a paper
I wrote in 2020 again—and not add all these
extra features, but just have something of
the same level of functionality—it actually
hasn't saved that much time, to be honest.
It's made the papers richer and broader,
but not necessarily deeper.
You made this distinction between
artificial cleverness and artificial intelligence.
I would like to better understand those concepts.
What is an example of intelligence
that is not just cleverness?
Intelligence is famously hard to define.
It's one of these things that
you know when you see it.
But when I talk to someone and we're trying to
collaboratively solve a math problem together,
there's this conversation where neither of
us knows how to solve the problem initially.
One of us has some idea and it looks promising,
so then we have some sort of prototype strategy.
We test it, and it doesn't
work, but then we modify it.
There's adaptivity and continual
improvement of the idea over time.
Eventually, we've systematically mapped
out what doesn't work and what does work,
and we can see a path forward, but
it's evolving with our discussion.
This isn't quite what the AIs do.
The AIs can mimic this a little bit.
To go back to this analogy of these jumping
robots, they can jump and fail, and jump and fail.
But what they can't do is jump a little bit, reach
some handhold, stay there, pull other people up,
and then try to jump from there.
There isn't this cumulative process
which is built up interactively.
It seems to be a lot more trial and
error and just repetition: brute force.
It scales, and it can work amazingly
well in certain contexts.
But this idea of building
up cumulatively from partial progress
is what's still not quite there yet.
Interesting. You're saying if Gemini 3 or
Claude 4.5, whatever, solves a problem,
it is not the case that its own
understanding of math has progressed.
No.
Or even if it works
on a problem without solving it, it's not that
its own understanding of math has progressed.
Yeah. You run a new session and
it's forgotten what it just did.
It has no new skills to build on related problems.
Maybe what you just did is 0.001% of the
training data for the next generation.
So maybe eventually some of it gets absorbed.
So Terence talks about the importance
of decomposing particularly gnarly
problems into a series of easier chunks.
Even if this doesn't result in the full solution,
approaching problems in this way helps you build
up the intuitions and practice the techniques
that you'll need to keep making progress.
But models today tend to struggle with these
kinds of problem-solving techniques.
That's where Labelbox comes in.
Labelbox helps you train models not just to get
the right answer, but to think the right way.
They've operationalized these reasoning behaviors
into rubrics, giving you the ability to evaluate
every important dimension of a model's output.
These rubrics go beyond simple correctness.
Did the model reach for the right tools?
Did it check its own work and
explore alternative paths?
How clear was its response?
These skills are useful across domains:
math, physics, finance, psychology, and more.
And they're becoming increasingly important
as models take on harder, open-ended problems,
some of which have multiple solutions and some
of which we don't even know the solutions to.
Labelbox can get you rubrics tailored to
your domain, helping you systematically
measure and shape how your models think.
Learn more at labelbox.com/dwarkesh.
One big question I have is how plausible is it
that if we just keep training AIs—they get better
and better at solving problems in Lean—that they
will continue to solve more and more impressive
problems, and then we will be surprised at how
little insight we got from some Lean solution
to proving the Riemann hypothesis or something.
Or do you think it is a necessary condition of
solving the Riemann hypothesis, even by
an AI that is doing it entirely in Lean,
that the constructions and definitions
created in the Lean program have to
advance our understanding of mathematics?
Or could it just be assembly code gobbledygook?
We don't know. Some problems have been
basically solved by pure brute force.
The four color theorem is a famous example.
We have still not found a conceptually elegant
proof of this theorem, and maybe we never will.
Some problems may only be solvable by splitting
into an enormous number of
cases and doing brute force,
uninsightful computer analysis on each case.
Part of the reason we prize problems like
the Riemann hypothesis is that we're
pretty sure a new type of mathematics
has to be created, or a new connection between
two previously unconnected areas of mathematics
has to be discovered to make this work.
We don't even know what the shape of the solution
is, but it doesn't feel like a problem that will
be solved just by exhaustively checking cases.
Or it could be false actually.
Okay, there is an unlikely scenario
that the hypothesis is false, and you
can just compute a zero off the line,
and a massive computer calculation verifies
it. That would be very disappointing. I do
feel that fully autonomous, one-shot approaches
are not the right approach for these problems.
You'll get a lot more mileage out of the interplay
of humans collaborating with these tools.
I can see one of these problems
being solved by smart humans
assisted by extremely powerful AI tools.
But the exact dynamic may be very different
from what we envision right now.
It could be a collaboration of
a type that just doesn't exist yet.
There may be a way to generate a million variants
of the Riemann zeta function and do AI-assisted
data analysis to discover some pattern connecting
them that we didn't know about before.
This lets you transform the problem
into a different area of mathematics.
There could be all kinds of scenarios.
Suppose the AI figures it out, and latent in
the Lean is some brand-new construction which,
if we realized its significance, we would be
able to apply in all these different situations.
How would we even recognize it?
Again, a very naive question, but if you come
up with the equivalent of Descartes' idea that
you can have a coordinate system unifying algebra
and geometry, in Lean code it would just look
like R→R, and it wouldn't look that significant.
I'm sure there are other constructions
which have this kind of property.
The beauty of formalizing a proof in
something like Lean is that you can take
any piece of it and study it atomically.
When I read a paper which solves some
difficult problem, there's often a
big sequence of lemmas and theorems.
Ideally, the author will talk their way
through what's important and what's not.
But sometimes they don't reveal what steps
were the important ones and which ones
were just boilerplate, standard steps.
You can study each lemma in isolation.
Some of them I can see look fairly standard
and resemble something I'm familiar with.
I'm pretty sure there's nothing
interesting going on there.
But this other lemma, that's something I haven't
seen before, and I can see why having this result
would really help prove the main result.
You can assess whether a step is really key
to your argument or not, and
Lean really facilitates that.
The individual steps are
identified really precisely.
I think in the future, there will be entire
professions of mathematicians who might take
a giant Lean-generated proof and do some
ablation on it, trying to remove parts of
it and find more elegant ways.
They might get other AIs to do
some reinforcement learning to make the proof
more elegant, and maybe other AIs will grade
whether this proof looks better or not.
One thing that will change quite a bit
in the near future is how we write papers.
Until recently, writing papers was the most
time-consuming and expensive part of the job.
So you did it very rarely.
You only wrote up your results once all the other
parts of your argument were checked out, because
rewriting and refactoring was just a total pain.
That's become a lot easier now
with modern AI tools.
You don't have to have just
one version of your paper.
Once you have one,
people can generate hundreds more.
One giant messy Lean proof may not be very
meaningful or understandable on
its own, but other people can
refactor it and do all kinds of things with it.
We've seen this with the Erdős problem website.
An AI will generate a proof, and here are
3,000 lines of code that verify the proof.
Then people got other AIs to summarize
the proof, and people write their own
proofs. There's actually post-processing.
Once you have one proof, we have a lot of
tools now to deconstruct and interpret it.
It's a very nascent area of mathematics,
but I'm not as worried about it.
Some people are concerned about what happens if
the Riemann hypothesis is proven with
a completely incomprehensible proof.
I think once you have the artifact of a
proof, we can do a lot of analysis on it.
You posted recently that it would be
helpful to have a formal or semi-formal
language for mathematical strategies
as opposed to just mathematical proofs,
which is what Lean specializes in.
I would love to learn more about
what that would involve or look like.
We don't really know. We've been very
lucky in mathematics that we have worked
out the laws of logic and mathematics,
but this is a fairly recent accomplishment.
It was started by Euclid two millennia ago,
but only in the early 20th century did we
finally list out the axioms of mathematics,
the standard axioms of what we call ZFC, the
axioms of first-order logic, and what a proof is.
This we've managed to automate
and have a formal language for.
There could be some way to assess plausibility.
You have a conjecture that something is true,
you test a few examples, and it works out.
How does this increase your
confidence that the conjecture is true?
We have a few sort of mathematical ways to model
this, like Bayesian probability, for example.
But you often have to set certain base
assumptions, and there's a lot of
subjectivity still in these tasks.
This is more of a wish than a plan to develop
these languages, but just seeing how successful
having a formal framework in place, like Lean, has
made deductive proofs so much easier to automate
and train AI on… The bottleneck for using AI to
create strategies and make conjectures is we have
to rely on human experts and the test of time to
validate whether something is plausible or not.
If there was some semi-formal framework
where this could be done semi-automatically
in a way that isn't easily hackable...
It's really important with these formal
proof assistants that there are no backdoors
or exploits you can use to somehow get your
certified proof without actually proving
it, because reinforcement learning is
just so good at finding these backdoors.
If there's some framework that mimics how
scientists talk to each other in a
semi-formal way, using data and argument,
but also constructing narratives...
There's some subjective aspect of
science that we don't know how to capture in a way
that we can insert AI into it in any useful way.
This is a future problem. There are research
efforts to try to create automated conjectures,
and maybe there are ways to benchmark these and
simulate this, but it's all very new science.
Can you help me get some intuition? I have two
sub-questions. One, it would be very helpful
to have a specific example of what something
like this would look like, the way scientists
communicate that we can't formalize yet.
Two, it seems almost definitionally paradoxical
to say you're building up some narrative or
natural language explanation and then also having
something which you could have formalized.
I'm sure there's some intuition behind
where that overlap is, and I'd
love to understand that better.
An example of a conjecture: Gauss was
interested in the prime numbers and
created one of the first mathematical datasets.
He just computed the first 100,000 prime numbers
or so, hoping to find patterns.
He did find a pattern,
but maybe not the pattern he was expecting.
He found a statistical pattern in the primes
that if you count how many primes there are
up to 100, 1,000, one million, and so forth,
they get sparser and sparser, but the drop-off
in the density was inversely proportional to
the natural logarithm of the range of numbers.
So he conjectured what we now call the prime
number theorem: the number of primes up
to X is X divided by the natural log of X.
He had no way to prove this. It was
data-driven. This was a conjecture.
It was revolutionary for its time because it
was maybe the first really important conjecture
of math that was statistical in nature.
Normally you're talking about a pattern,
like maybe the spacing between the
primes has a certain regularity.
But this didn't tell you exactly how many
primes there were in any given range.
It just gave you an approximation that got better
and better as you went further and further out.
It started the field of what
we call analytic number theory.
It was the first in many conjectures
like this, many of which got proved,
which started consolidating the idea that the
prime numbers didn't really have a pattern,
that they behaved like random sets
of numbers with a certain density.
They had some patterns,
like they're almost all odd.
They're also not actually random,
they're what's called pseudo-random.
There's no random number generation
involved in creating the prime numbers.
But over time, it became more and more
productive to think of the primes as
if they were just generated by some god rolling
dice all the time and creating this random set.
This allowed us to make all
these other predictions.
There's a still-open conjecture in number
theory called the twin prime conjecture, that
there should be infinitely many pairs of primes
that are twins just two apart, like 11 and 13.
We can't prove that, and there are
good reasons why we can't prove it.
But because of this statistical random model of
the primes, we are absolutely convinced it's true.
We know that if the primes were generated by
flipping coins, we would just—by random chance
like infinite monkeys at a typewriter—see
twin primes appear over and over again.
We have over time developed this very accurate
conceptual model of what the primes should behave
like based on statistics and probability.
It's mostly heuristic and non-rigorous,
but extremely accurate.
The few times when we actually
can prove things about the primes, it has
matched up with the predictions of what we
call the random model of the primes.
We have this conjectural concept
framework for understanding the
primes that everyone believes in.
It's the same reason why we believe the
Riemann hypothesis is true, and why we
believe that cryptography based on
the primes is mathematically secure.
It's all part of this belief.
In fact, one reason why we care
about the Riemann hypothesis is that
if the Riemann hypothesis failed,
if we knew it was false, it would
be a serious blow to this model.
It would mean there's a secret pattern
to the primes that we were not aware of.
I think we would very rapidly abandon
any cryptography based on the primes,
because if there was one pattern that we didn't
know about, there are probably more, and these
patterns can lead to exploits in crypto.
It would be a big shock.
So we really want to make
sure that doesn't happen.
We've been convinced of things like
the Riemann hypothesis over time.
Some of it is experimental evidence, and some
is that the few times we've been able to make
theoretical results, they've always aligned.
It is possible that the consensus is wrong and
we've all just missed something very basic.
There have been paradigm shifts in
the past in scientific history.
But we don't really have a way of
measuring this, partly because we don't have
enough data on how math or science develops.
We have one timeline of history, and we have
maybe 100 stories of turning points in history.
If we had access to a million alien
civilizations, each with a different
development of history and science in different
orders, then maybe we'd actually have a decent
shot at understanding how we measure what
progress is and what is a good strategy.
We could maybe start formalizing
it and actually having a framework.
Maybe what we need to do is start creating
lots of mini-universes or simulations of AI
solving very basic problems in arithmetic
or whatever, but coming up with their
own strategies for doing these things and
having these little laboratories to test.
There are people who investigate what's
the smallest neural network that can do
10-digit multiplication and things like that.
I think we could learn a lot just from evolving
small AIs on simple problems.
I was super excited when Mercury
reached out about sponsoring the podcast
because I've been banking with them for years.
I think I opened my first
account with them in 2023.
Something I've come to appreciate over the
last few years is that Mercury is constantly
updating things and adding new features.
Take their newest feature, Insights.
Insights summarizes your money in and out,
showing you your biggest transactions and calling
out anything that deserves extra attention.
Like maybe your revenue from a particular partner
has gone down, or you've got a big uncategorized
purchase that needs to be investigated.
It's a super low-friction way for me to keep
tabs on my business and make quick decisions.
For example, I try to invest any cash that I
don't need on hand to keep running the business.
With Insights, with just a couple of clicks,
I was able to see exactly how much money I
spent in each month of 2025 and that lets
me know exactly how much cash I'll need for
the next year or so of operations.
And then I can go invest the rest.
Mercury just keeps adding new features like this.
Go to mercury.com to check it out.
Mercury is a fintech company,
not an FDIC Insured Bank.
Banking services provided through Choice
Financial Group and Column NA, members FDIC.
You have to learn about new fields not
only very rapidly, but deeply enough
to contribute to the frontier.
So in some sense, you're also
one of the world's greatest autodidacts.
What is your process of learning about a new
subfield in math? What does that look like?
We talked about depth and breadth before.
It's not a purely human-AI distinction.
Humans also, I think it was Berlin who
split them into hedgehogs and foxes.
The hedgehog knows one thing very well,
and a fox knows a little bit about everything.
I definitely think of myself as a fox.
I work with hedgehogs a lot, and
sometimes I can be a hedgehog if need be.
I've always had a little
bit of an obsessive streak.
If there's something I read about which I
feel like I have the capability to understand,
but I don't understand why it works and
there's some magic in it… Someone was able
to use a type of mathematics I'm not familiar
with and get a result I would like to prove.
I can't do it myself, but they
could do it by their method,
and I want to find out what their trick was.
It bugs me that someone else can do something
I think I can do, but I can't.
I've always had that obsessive,
completionist streak.
I've had to wean myself off
computer games because if I start a game, I want
to play it to completion, through all the levels.
That's one way I learn new fields.
I collaborate with a lot of people
who have taught me other types of mathematics.
I just make friends with another mathematician
working on another area of mathematics.
I find their problems interesting,
but they have to teach me some of the basic
tricks, what's known, and what's not known.
I learn a lot from that.
I found that writing about
what I've learned helps.
I have a blog where I sometimes
record things I've learned.
In the past when I was younger,
I would learn something, do this cool trick,
and say, "Okay, I'm going to remember this."
Then six months later, I'd forgotten it.
I remember remembering it,
but I can't reconstruct my arguments.
The first few times, it was so frustrating
to have understood something and then lost it.
I resolved I should always write down
anything cool that I've learned.
That's part of how this blog came about.
How long does it take you to write a blog post?
It's something I often do when I don't want
to do other work.
There's some referee
report or something that feels slightly
unpleasant for me to do at the time.
Writing a blog feels creative and fun.
It's something I do for myself.
Depending on the topic, it could be a
quick half an hour or several hours.
Because it's something I do voluntarily,
time flies when I write these things down, as
opposed to doing something I have to do for
administrative reasons that is just drudgery.
Those are tasks, by the way, that
AI is really helping with nowadays.
If civilization could from first principles
decide how to use Terry Tao's time, as a
limited resource, what is the biggest difference?
What if the veil of ignorance got to decide how to
use Terry Tao's time versus what it does
now? This podcast wouldn't be happening.
As much as I complain about certain tasks that
I don't want to do, but have to do… As you get
more senior in academia, you get more and more
responsibilities, more committees, and whatever.
I have also found that a lot of events
I reluctantly went to because I was
obliged to for one reason or another…
Because it's outside my comfort zone,
it often results in interactions with people I
wouldn't normally talk to, like you for instance.
I would learn interesting things
and have interesting experiences.
I would have opportunities to then network with
other people that I never would have before.
So I do believe a lot in serendipity.
I do optimize portions of my day
where I schedule very carefully.
But I am willing to leave some portions just
to do something that is not my usual thing.
Maybe it'll be a waste of my time,
but maybe I will learn something.
More often than not, I get a positive
experience that I wouldn't have planned for.
So I believe a lot in serendipity.
Maybe there's a danger in modern
societies, not just with AI, that we've
become really good at optimizing everything.
We’re not optimizing our own optimization.
With COVID, for example, we switched a lot to
remote meetings, so everything was scheduled.
We kept busy in academia. We met almost
the same number of people we met in person,
but everything had to be planned in advance.
What we lost out on was the casual knocking
on a hallway door, just meeting
someone while getting a coffee.
Those serendipitous interactions may not seem
optimal, but they are actually really important.
When I was a grad student, I would go to
the library to look for a journal article.
You had to physically check out
the journal and read the article.
You could browse through and sometimes
the next article was also interesting.
Sometimes it wasn’t, but you could
accidentally find interesting things.
That has basically been lost now.
If you want to access an article,
you just type it into a search engine or an AI,
and you get exactly what you want instantly.
But you don't get the accidental things you might
have found if you'd done it more inefficiently.
I spent a year once at the Institute
for Advanced Study, which is
a great place with no distractions.
You're there just to do research.
The first few weeks you're there, it's great.
You're getting all these papers written up that
you've been wanting to do for a long time.
You think about problems for
blocks of hours at a time.
But I find if I stay there for more
than several months, I run out of inspiration.
I get bored. I surf the internet a lot more.
You actually do need a certain
level of distraction in your life.
It adds enough randomness and high temperature.
I don't know the optimal way to schedule
my life. It just seems to work.
I'm very curious when you expect AIs
that can actually do frontier math at least
as well as the best human mathematicians.
In some ways, they're already doing frontier math
that is super intelligent that humans can't do,
but it's a different frontier
from what we're used to.
You could argue that calculators were doing
frontier math that humans could not accomplish,
but it was number crunching.
But replacing Terry Tao completely.
I mean, what do you want me for?
You'll just go on all the podcasts after.
It might not be the right question to ask.
I think within a decade, a lot of things that
math students currently do—what we spend the
bulk of our time doing and a lot of stuff we
put in our papers today—can be done by AI.
But we will find that that actually wasn't
the most important part of what we do.
A hundred years ago, a lot of mathematicians
were just solving differential equations.
Physicists needed some exact solution to
some system, and they hired a mathematician to
laboriously go through the calculus and work out
the solution to this fluid equation, whatever.
A lot of what a 19th-century mathematician would
do, you could make a call to Mathematica, Wolfram
Alpha, a computer algebra package, or now more
recently to an AI, and it would just solve the
problem in a few minutes. But we moved on. We
worked on different types of problems after that.
Once computers came along—computers
used to be human.
People used to laboriously
create log tables and work out primes as
Gauss did, and that has all been outsourced
to computers. But we moved on. In genetics,
to sequence the genome of a single organism,
that was an entire PhD of a geneticist, carefully
separating all the chromosomes and whatever.
Now you can just spend $1,000 and send
it to a sequencer and get it done.
But genetics is not dead as a subject.
You move to a different scale.
Maybe you study whole ecosystems
rather than individuals.
I take your point but when is most
mathematical progress, or almost
all mathematical progress, happening by AI?
If you find out this year a Millennium Prize
Problem has been solved, you would put
95% odds that an AI did it autonomously.
Surely there will be such a year.
I guess I do believe that hybrid
human plus AIs will dominate mathematics for
a lot longer. It will depend. It will require
some additional breakthroughs beyond what we
already have, so it's going to be stochastic.
I think AIs currently are very good at
certain things, but really terrible at others.
While you can add more and more frameworks on top
to reduce the error rates and make them work with
each other a bit more, it feels like we don't
have all the ingredients to really have a truly
satisfactory replacement for all intellectual
tasks. It is complementary currently. It's not
a replacement. Because current level AIs
will accelerate science in so many ways,
hopefully new discoveries and new
breakthroughs will happen more quickly.
It's also possible that by destroying serendipity
we actually inhibit certain types of progress.
Anything is possible at this point.
I think the world is very,
very unpredictable at this point in time.
What is your advice to somebody who would
consider a career in math or is early in a career
in math, especially in light of AI progress?
How should they be thinking about
their career differently, if at all,
as a result of AI progress?
We live in a time of change.
As I said, we live in a
particularly unpredictable era.
Things that we've taken for granted
for centuries may not hold anymore.
The way we do everything, and not
just mathematics, will change.
In many ways, I would prefer the much more
boring, quiet era where things are much the
same as they were 10 years ago, 20 years ago.
But I think one just has to embrace that
there's going to be a lot of change.
The things that you study, some of them
may become obsolete or revolutionized,
but some things will be retained.
You always have to keep an eye on opportunities
for things that you wouldn't be able to do before.
In math, you previously had to go through
years and years of education and be a math
PhD before you could contribute
to the frontier of math research.
But now it's quite possible at the
high school level, or whatever,
that you could get involved in a math project and
actually make a real contribution because of all
these AI tools, Lean, and everything else.
There will be a lot of non-traditional
opportunities to learn, so you
need a very adaptable mindset.
There will be room for pursuing things
just for curiosity and for playing around.
You still need to get your credentials.
For a while it will still be important to
go through traditional education and learn
math and science the old-fashioned way.
But you should also be open to very different ways
of doing science, some of which don't exist yet.
It's a scary time, but also very exciting.
That's a great note to close on. Terence,
thanks so much.
Pleasure.