Most of our knowledge from antiquity is
not lost at the burning of the library
of Alexandria. It's lost between 400 and
600 AD when the papyrie are falling
apart. And here you are with a library
of a thousand books and you can only
afford to make 100 new books. So you
have to choose which hundred of these
thousand do we save because there
literally is not enough industry on your
continent to make enough leather to copy
down all this text. You have to pick.
And so the majority of what we lost from
antiquity we lost then we lost when the
papyrie were falling apart. And this is
also what distorted what survived
because most of the copying out was done
by monks. And when you have a thousand
books and you can only save a hundred of
them and you're a monk you're like what
will I save? I know St. Augustine. I
love St. Augustine. This is why we have
more surviving work by St. Augustine
than the entirety of all pagan classical
Latin because the subjective tastes of
the people in power at the moment the
papyrie were falling apart ended up
being an unintentional moment of
censorship that biased what survives
from antiquity.