You've probably seen lots of graphs of
history with the hockey stick graph
structure, right? Where it's sort of
flat for a long time and then up and
they'll put that after the invention of
the scientific method. And it depends on
what we're graphing and also depends on
how much you zoom in or zoom out because
it's true we do 150 years after bacon
get to inventions that result in
enormous increases in population. Would
we have anyway even if it hadn't been
systematized? Probably a bit later and
we would have a slightly flatter hockey
stick. But we would still have hockey
stick, right? In the same way that when
you put mice on an island without mice,
they breed and they breed and they breed
and they breed and they hockey stick.
Humans would also have hockey stick. But
would we have hockey stick later? Would
we have hockey stick with more pain?
Right? When mice hockey stick, they also
starve to death and eat each other. We
haven't done that yet. Go us. Was that
science? Probably. So, is it true that
everything accelerated after 1620? In
one sense, yes. In another sense, it's a
continuation of a curve that was already
curving.