The printing press comes in in 1450 and
it isn't done shaping the world
instantly. It takes 40 years to even be
economically sustainable. It's not until
the 1490s that printers are making
money. And then in the 15s, it's time
for pamphlets and pamphlet distribution.
And now there's news and news is
suddenly done by print. A revolution on
the same scale as the difference between
computers and cell phones. Then we get
the newspaper, another new application
of the same technology that follows like
social media. So it's one information
revolution having multiple successive
revolutionary applications as it
disseminates and eventually saturates.
And it moves on a time scale quite
similar to the time scale in which the
digital one is happening as well. So
that print keeps hitting Europe with
successive revolutions for 150 years.
And every couple decades there will be a
new bang. Or sometimes every decade
there will be a new suddenly it's
possible to get a printed pamphlet from
Vittenberg to London in 17 days. Oh my
god, we can coordinate our resistance
movement against the Catholics. Boom.
That wasn't possible even a decade
earlier when it took months to get a
pamphlet from one end of Europe to the