Makia is an absolutely dedicated patriot
and he only works for Florence. The
prince is dedicated to the heir and
ruler of Florence. So this is a point
late in Mchavel's life in which he was
part of the resistance regime that ruled
while the Medachi were in exile. They
were in power. They were kicked out.
When they returned, they viewed him as
an enemy. He is arrested, tortured,
exiled. and in exile writes the prince
but dedicates it to the very family that
exiled him because they now control
Florence and Flor he will only work for
Florence. He doesn't want his manual of
here are the great secrets of statecraft
to be in the hands of anybody but his
homeland so that it will defend his
homeland. The prince he kept in very
close private circles circulating it
only with trusted intimate friends and
then the copy that he sends in to
Florence and yes it's a job application.
Please bring me back. I will work for
you. I will be loyal. I support my
country more than any particular regime
or group that might be in power.
Whatever is in power in my city, I will
be faithful to it. And when in the
prince he says you can do and should do
all of these different ruthless things
to keep power, we have to remember that
the end justifies the means when the end
is the survival of your country.
Makavelli feels very strongly that
regime changes bring civil violence.
Civil violence sheds blood. And he has
seen the streets of his city run with
blood before. He thinks that even life
under a tyrant is better than life in a
civil war, which is usually not life at
all. So he says, "Don't push for a
regime change. Even if the regime is
tyrannical, more people will survive by
sticking with the tyrant than by
changing the regime.