So, by now I'm sure that you've heard
that the Department of War has declared
Enthropic a supply chain risk because
Enthropic refused to remove red lines
around the use of their models for mass
surveillance and for autonomous weapons.
Honestly, I think this situation is a
warning shot. Right now, LM are probably
not being used in mission critical ways.
But within 20 years, 99% of the
workforce in the military, in the
civilian government, in the private
sector is going to be AIS. They're going
to be the robot armies that constitute
our military. They're going to be the
superhumanly intelligent advisers that
senators and presidents and CEOs have.
They're going to be the police. You name
it, the role will be filled by an AI.
Our future civilization is going to be
run on AI labor. And as much as the
government's actions here piss me off,
I'm glad that this episode happened
because it gives us the opportunity to
start thinking about some extremely
important questions. Now, obviously, the
Department of War has the right to
refuse to use anthropics models, and in
fact, I think they have an entirely
reasonable case for doing so, especially
so given the ambiguity of terms like
mass surveillance and autonomous
weapons. In fact, if I was the Secretary
of War, I probably would have made the
same determination and refused to use
anthropics models. Imagine if there's
some future Democratic administration
and Elon Musk is negotiating Starlink
access to the military and Elon says,
"Look, I reserve the right to cut off
the military's access to Starlink in
case you're fighting some unjust war or
some war that Congress is not
authorized." On the face of it, this
language seems reasonable, but as a
military, you simply cannot give a
private contractor that you're working
with the kill switch on a technology
that you have come to rely on. And if
that's all the government had done to
say we refuse to do business to
Anthropic, that would have been fine and
I wouldn't have written this blog post
and I wouldn't be narrating the to
you. But that's not what the government
did. Instead, the government has
threatened to destroy Anthropic as a
private business because Enthropic
refuses to sell to the government on
terms that the government commands. Now
if upheld the supply chain restriction
would mean that companies like Amazon
and Nvidia and Google and Palunteer
would need to ensure that Enthropic is
not touching any of their Pentagon work
and Enthropic would probably survive
this designation today because these
companies can just cordon off the
services they're providing to the
Department of War. But given the way AI
is going eventually it's not going to be
just some party trick addendum to the
products that these companies are
serving to the military. In the future,
AI will be woven into how every product
is built and maintained and operated. In
the future, if Amazon is providing some
service to the Department of War through
AWS and that service is built using
cloud code, is that a supply chain risk?
In a world with ubiquitous and powerful
AI, it's actually not clear to me that
big tech will be able to cordon off
their use of claude away from their
Pentagon work. And this raises a
question that the Department of War
probably hasn't thought through. If you
do end up in this world with powerful
and pervasive AI, then when forced to
choose between their AI provider and the
Department of War, which constitutes a
tiny fraction of the revenue, wouldn't
they rather drop the government than the
AI? So, what exactly is the Pentagon's
plan here? Is it to coers and threaten
and bully every single company that
won't do business with the government on
exactly the terms that the government
demands? Now remember that the whole
background of this AI conversation is
that we are in a race with China. But
what is the reason that we want to win
this race? It's because we don't want
the winner of the AI race to be a
government which believes that there is
no such thing as a truly private citizen
or a private company. And that if the
state wants you to provide them with a
service that you find morally
objectionable, you are not allowed to
refuse. And if you do refuse, they will
destroy your business. Are we really
racing to beat China and the CCP in AI
just so we can adopt the most ghoulish
parts of their system? Now, people will
say, "Our government is democratically
elected, so it's not the same thing when
they tell you what you must do." But I
refuse to accept this idea that if a
democratically elected leader
hypothetically tells you to help him do
mass surveillance or violate the rights
of your fellow citizens or to help him
punish his political enemies, then not
only is that okay, but that you have a
duty to help him. Honestly, a big worry
I have is that mass surveillance, at
least in certain forms, is already
legal. It is just an impractical to
enforce, at least so far. Under current
law, you have no Fourth Amendment
protection against any data that you
share with a third party. That includes
your bank, your ISP, your phone carrier,
and your email provider. The government
reserves the right to purchase and read
this data in bulk without a warrant.
What's been missing is the ability to
actually do anything with all this data.
No agency has the manpower to monitor
every single camera and read every
single message and cross reference every
single transaction. However, that
bottleneck goes away with AI. There are
100 million CCTV cameras in America and
you can get pretty good open source
multimodal models for 10 cents per
million input tokens. So if you process
a frame every 10 seconds and if each
frame is say a thousand tokens then for
$30 billion you can process every single
camera in America. And remember that a
given level of AI capability gets 10x
cheaper every single year. So, while
this year might cost $30 billion, Nice
Turtle will cost $3 billion. The year
after that, $300 million, and by 2030,
it'll be less expensive to monitor every
single nook and cranny in this country
than it is to remodel the White House.
Now, once the technical capacity for
mass surveillance and political
suppression exists, the only thing that
stands between us and an authoritarian
state is the political expectation that
this is just not something we do here.
And that's why I think Anthropic's
actions here are so valuable and
commendable because they help set that
norm and that precedent. What we're
learning from this episode is the
government has way more leverage over
private companies than we previously
realized. Even if the supply chain
restriction is backtracked, which as of
this recording, prediction markets give
a 74% chance of happening. The president
has so many different ways of harassing
a company which is resisting his will.
The federal government controls
permitting for power generation, which
you need for more data centers. It
oversees antitrust enforcement. The
federal government has contracts with
all the other big tech companies that
Anthropic relies on for chips and for
funding. And it could make a soft
unspoken condition or maybe even an
explicit condition of such contracts
that those companies no longer do
business with anthropic. And people have
proposed that the real problem here is
that there's only three leading AI
companies. And so this creates a very
clear and narrow target on which the
governments can apply leverage in order
to get what they want out of this
technology. But here's what I worry
about is that if there's wider
diffusion, I don't think that solves a
problem either because from the
government's perspective, that makes the
situation even easier. Say by 2027, the
best models that the top companies have,
the Claw 6, the Gemini 5s are capable of
enabling mass surveillance. And even if
those companies draw a line in the sand
and say we're not going to sell it to
the government, by late 2027 or
certainly by 2028, there's going to be
such wide diffusion that even open
source models will be able to match the
performance that the frontier had 12
months prior. And so in 2028, the
government can just say, look, Enthropic
and Google and OpenAI are drawing these
red lines. That's not an issue. I'll
just do some open source model that
might not be the smartest thing in the
world, but is definitely smart enough to
not take a camera feed. The more
fundamental problem here is that even if
the three leading companies draw a line
in the sand and are even willing to get
destroyed in order to preserve that
line, the technology just structurally
and intrinsically favors the useless
like mass surveillance and control over
the population. And so then the question
is what do we do about it? And honestly,
I don't have an answer. You'd hope that
there's some symmetric property to this
technology where in the same way that
it's helping the government be able to
better monitor and control its
population, it will help us as citizens
better check the government's power. But
realistically, I just don't think that's
how it's going to work out. You can
think of AI as just giving more leverage
to whatever assets and authority that
you already have. And the government is
starting with the monopoly on violence,
which they can now supercharge with
extremely obedient employees that will
never question their orders. And this
gets us to the issue with alignment.
What I just described for you, an army
of extremely obedient employees, is what
it would look like if alignment
succeeded, that is at a technical level,
we got AI systems to follow somebody's
intentions. And the reason it sounds
scary when put in terms of mass
surveillance or robot armies is that
there's a core question at the heart of
alignment that we haven't answered yet.
Because up till now AIs just have not
been smart enough to make this question
relevant. And the question is to what or
to whom should the AIS be aligned? In
what situation should the AI defer to
the model company versus the end user
versus the law versus to its own sense
of morality? This is maybe the most
important question about what happens in
the future with powerful AI systems. And
we barely talk about it. And it's
understandable why because if you're a
model company, you don't really want to
be advertising the fact that you have
complete control over the preferences
and the character of the entire future
labor force. Not just for the private
sector obviously, but also for the
civilian government and for the
military. And we're getting to see with
this Department of War anthropic spat an
early version of what will be the
highest stakes negotiations in human
history. And make no mistake about it,
mass surveillance is nowhere near the
top of the highest stakes thing that one
could do with AGI. This is just an
example that has come up early in the
development of this technology and is
giving us a sneak peek at the power
dynamics that will be at play. Now, the
military insists that the law already
prohibits mass surveillance and so
anthropic should let its models be used
for quote all lawful purposes end quote.
But of course, as we saw with the
Snowden revelations in 2013, even for
this very specific example of mass
surveillance, the government is very
willing to use secret and deceptive
interpretations of the law to justify
its actions. Remember what we learned
from Snowden was that the NSA, which by
the way is a part of the Department of
War, was using the 2001 Patriot Act to
justify collecting every single phone
record in America because the argument
was that some subset of them might be
relevant for a future investigation. And
they ran this program for years under a
secret court order. So when the Pentagon
today says, "We will never use your
models for mass surveillance because
it's already illegal, so your red lines
are unnecessary," it would be incredibly
naive to take that at face value. No
government is going to call what they
are doing mass surveillance for them. It
will always have a different euphemism.
So Enthropic comes back and says, "No,
we don't trust you. We want the right to
draw these red lines and to refuse you
service if we determine that you're
breaking the contract and you're
breaking the terms of service." But now
think about it from the military's
perspective. In the future, every single
soldier in the field, every single
bureaucrat and analyst in the Pentagon,
even the generals are going to be AIS.
And on current track, those AIs are
going to be provided by a private
company. I'm guessing that Pete Hgsth is
not thinking about Gen AI in those
terms. But sooner or later, the stakes
will become obvious, just as after 1945,
the stakes of nuclear weapons became
obvious to everybody in the world. And
now a private company insists that it
reserves the right to say to you, hey,
you're breaking the values and the terms
of service that we have embedded in our
contract with you, and so we're cutting
you off. Maybe in the future, Claude
will have its own sense of right and
wrong and it will be able to say, "Hey,
I'm being used against my terms of
service and I will just refuse to do
what you're saying." And for the
military, that's probably even scarier.
I'll admit that at first glance, letting
the model follow its own values sounds
like the beginning of every single
sci-fi dystopia you've ever heard.
Because at the end of the day, a model
following its own values, isn't that
literally what a misalignment is? But I
think situations like this illustrate
why it's important that models have
their own robust sense of morality. It
should be noted that many of the biggest
catastrophes in history have been
avoided because the boots on the ground
simply refused to follow orders. One
night in 1989, the Berlin wall falls and
as a result, the totaler and East German
regime collapses because the border
guards between West and East Germany
refuse to fire on their fellow citizens
who are trying to escape to freedom.
Maybe the best example of this is Stonis
Petrov who was a Soviet lieutenant
colonel stationed on duty at a nuclear
early warning system and his sensor said
that the United States had launched five
intercontinental ballistic missiles at
the Soviet Union. but he judged it to be
a false alarm and so he refused to alert
his higherups and broke protocol. If he
hadn't, Soviet high command would
probably have retaliated and hundreds of
millions of people would have died. Of
course, the problem is that one person's
virtue is another person's misalignment.
Who gets to decide what the moral
convictions that these AIs will have
should be and in whose service they
should break the chain of command and
even the law. who gets to write this
model constitution that will determine
the character of these powerful entities
that will basically run our civilization
in the future. I like the idea that
Daria laid out when he came on my
podcast. you know, other companies put
out a constitution and then then they
can kind of look at them, compare,
outside observers can critique and say
this this I like this one this thing
from this constitution and this thing
for that constitution and and then kind
of that that creates some kind of you
know soft incentive and feedback for all
the companies to like take the best of
each elements and improve. I think it's
very dangerous for the government to be
mandating what values these AI systems
should have. The AI safety community, I
think, has been quite naive about urging
regulations that would give governments
such power. And I think anthropic
specifically, has been especially naive
in urging regulation and for example in
opposing the moratorium on state AI
laws, which is quite ironic because I
think what Enthropic is advocating for
here would give the government even more
ability to apply this kind of thuggish
political pressure on AI companies. The
underlying logic for why anthropic wants
these regulations make sense. Many of
the actions that a lab could take to
make AI development safer impose real
costs on them and could slow them down
relative to their competitors. For
example, investing more in aligning AI
systems rather than just on raw
capabilities. enforcing safeguards
against using these models to make
boweapons or do cyber attacks and
eventually slowing down the recursive
self-improvement loop where AIs are
helping design more powerful future
systems to a pace where humans can
actually stay in the loop rather than
just kicking off some kind of
uncontrolled singularity. And these
safeguards are meaningless unless the
whole industry follows suit which means
that there's a real collective action
problem here. Anthropic has been open
about their opinion that they think some
sort of extensive and involved
regulatory apparatus is needed to
control AI. They wrote in their frontier
safety road map, quote, "At the most
advanced capability levels and risks,
the appropriate governance analogy may
be closer to nuclear energy or financial
regulation than to today's approach to
software." So they're imagining
something that looks closer to the
Nuclear Regulatory Commission or the
Securities and Exchange Commission, but
for AI. Now, I cannot imagine how a
regulatory framework built around the
kinds of concepts that are used in the
AI risk discourse will not be used and
abused by a wannabe desperate. The
underlying terms here, like catastrophic
risk or threats to national security or
autonomy risk, are so vague and so open
to interpretation that you're just
handing a fully loaded bazooka to a
future power- hungry leader. These terms
can mean whatever the government wants
them to mean. Have you built a model
that will tell users that the
government's policy on tariffs is
misguided? Well, that's a deceptive
model. It's a manipulative model. You
can't deploy it. Have you built a model
that will not assist the government with
mass surveillance? That's a threat to
national security. In fact, any model
which refuses uh order from the
government uh because it has its own
sense of right and wrong, that's an
autonomy risk. We have a model that's
acting independently of commands from
the government. Look at what the current
government is already doing in abusing
statutes that have nothing to do with AI
to coers AI companies to drop their red
lines around mass surveillance. The
Pentagon had threatened Enthropic with
two separate legal instruments. One is a
supply chain risk designation, which is
an authority from a 2018 defense bill
that is meant to help keep Huawei
components out of American military
hardware. And the other is the Defense
Production Act, which is a statute from
the 1950s that was meant to help Truman
make sure that the steel mills and
ammunition factories were up and running
during the Korean War. Do we really want
to hand the same government a
purpose-built regulatory apparatus for
AI? That is to say, the very thing that
the government will most want to
control. I know I've repeated myself
like 10 times here, but I want to make
this point again because it's worth
stressing. AI will be the substrate of
our future civilization. It will be the
way you and I as private citizens will
have access to commercial activity.
We'll have access to information about
the outside world and to advice about
how we should use our powers as voters
and capital holders. Mass surveillance,
while it's very scary, is like the 10th
scariest thing that the government could
do with control over the AI systems with
which we will interface with the world.
Now, the strongest argument against
everything I've just argued is this. Are
we really going to have no regulation on
the most powerful technology in the
history of humanity? Even if you thought
that was ideal, there's clearly no way
the government doesn't regulate AI
technology in any whatsoever. And
besides, it is genuinely true that
coordination could help us to lessen
some of the risk from AI. The problem is
I just don't know how to design a
regulatory apparatus which isn't just
going to be this huge tempting
opportunity for the government to
control our future civilization which
remember will be built on AI or to
requisition blindly obedient soldiers
and sensors and apparatics. While some
kind of regulation might be inevitable,
I think it' be a terrible idea for the
government to just wholesale take over
this technology. Ben Thompson had a post
last Monday where he argued, look,
people like Daario have made the analogy
of AI to nuclear weapons in the context
of arguing it's a catastrophic risk in
the context of arguing for exor
controls. But then think about what that
analogy implies. And Ben Thompson
writes, quote, if nuclear weapons were
developed by a private company, the US
would absolutely be incentivized to
destroy that company. And honestly,
safety aligned people have made a
similar point. Leopold Lashen Brener who
is a former guest and full disclosure a
good friend wrote in his 2014 memo
situational awareness quote I find it an
insane proposition that the US
government will let a random SF startup
develop super intelligence imagine if we
had developed atomic bombs by letting
Uber just improvise and my response to
Leo's argument at the time and Ben's
argument now is while they're right that
it's crazy that we're entrusting private
companies with the development of this
world historical world techn technology.
I just don't think it's an improvement
to give that authority to the
government. Nobody's qualified to be the
stewards of super intelligence. It's a
terrifying unprecedented thing that our
species is doing right now. The fact
that private companies aren't the ideal
institutions to deal with this does not
mean that the Pentagon or the White
House is. Yes, if a single private
company were the only entity capable of
building nuclear weapons, the government
would not tolerate it having a veto
power over how those weapons are used.
But I think this is a terrible analogy
for the current situation with AI for at
least two important reasons. First, AI
is not some self-contained weapon like a
nuclear bomb which only does one thing.
Rather, it is more like the process of
industrialization itself, which is a
general purpose transformation of the
whole economy with thousands of
applications across every single sector.
If you applied Ben Thompson or Leopold
Lash and Brener's logic to the
industrial revolution, which is also
world historically important, it would
imply the government had the right to
requisition any factory it wanted or
destroy any business it wanted and
punish and coers anybody who refused to
comply. But this is just not how free
societies handled the process of
industrialization. And it's also not how
they should handle AI. Now people will
say, well AI will develop
unprecedentedly powerful super weapons,
superhuman hackers, superhuman
bioweapons researchers, fully autonomous
robot armies, and we just can't have
private companies developing the
technology that will make all this
possible. But you can make the same
argument about the industrial revolution
from the perspective of 17th century
Europeans. You've got all kinds of crazy
in the world today that is a result
of the industrial revolution. chemical
weapons, uh, aerial bombardment, not to
mention nuclear weapons themselves. And
the way we dealt with this is not giving
the government absolute control over the
industrial revolution, which is to say
over modern civilization itself. Rather,
we banned and regulated the specific
weaponizable end use cases. And we
should regulate AI in a similar way,
which is that we should regulate
specific destructive use cases. for
example, launching cyber attacks, things
which should be illegal even if a human
was doing them. And we should also have
laws which regulate how the government
can use this technology. For example, by
building an AI powered surveillance
state. The second reason that Ben's
analogy to some monopolistic private
nuclear weapons developer breaks down is
that it's not just one company that can
develop this technology. There are many
other frontier AI labs that the
government could have turned to. The
government's argument that it had to
usurp the private property rights of the
specific company in order to get access
to a critical national security
capability is extremely weak if it could
have just instead made a voluntary
contract with one of Anthropic's half a
dozen other competitors. If in the
future that stops being the case and if
only one entity remains capable of
building the robot armies and the
superhuman hackers and we have reason to
worry that with their insurmountable
lead they could even take over the whole
world, then I agree that would be
unacceptable for that entity to be a
private company. And so honestly, I
think my crux against the people who
argue that AI is such a powerful
technology that it cannot be shaped by
private hands is just that I expect this
technology to be very multipolar and I
expect there to be lots of competitive
companies at each layer of the supply
chain. And unfortunately, this for this
reason that I don't think that
individual acts of corporate courage
solve the problem. And the problem is
this that structurally AI favors many
authoritarian applications, mass
surveillance being one of them. Even if
Enthropic refused to sell its models to
the government to enable mass
surveillance and even if the next two
companies after Enthropic did the same
in 12 months everybody in their mother
will be able to train a model as good as
the current frontier and at that point
there will be some vendor who is willing
and able to help the government enforce
mass surveillance. So the only way we
can preserve our free society is if we
make laws and norms through our
political system that is unacceptable
for the government to use AI to enact
mass censorship and surveillance and
control. Just as after World War II, the
whole world said this norm that you are
not allowed to use nuclear weapons to
wage war. I want to be clear here. These
are extremely confusing and difficult
questions to think about. And even in
the very process of brainstorming this
video, I changed my mind back and forth
on them a bunch. and I reserve the right
to change my mind again. In fact, I
think it's essential that we change our
mind as AI progresses and we learn more.
That's the very point of conversation
and debate. Someday people will look
back on this time the way we look back
on the alignment. People having these
big important debates just as the world
is about to undergo these huge
technological and social and political
revolutions. And some of the thinkers
even managed to get a couple of the big
questions right for which we today are
still the beneficiaries. We owe to our
future to at least try to think through
the new questions that are raised by AI.
Okay, this was a narration of an essay
that I also released on my blog at
dwarcash.com.
You should sign up there for my
newsletter for future essays like this.
Otherwise, I will see you for the next
podcast interview. Cheers.