The idea that China won't be able to
have AI chips is completely nonsense.
The amount of energy they have is
incredible, isn't that right? AI is a
parallel computing problem, isn't it?
Why can't they just put four, 10 times
as much chips together? Because energy
is free. They have so much energy. They
have data centers that are sitting
completely empty, fully powered. You
know, they have ghost cities, they have
ghost ghost data centers. They have so
much capacity of infrastructure, and
their capacity of building chips is one
of the largest in the world. Now, of
course, if you ask me, would the United
States be further ahead if if the entire
world had no computer at all? Well,
that's just not an outcome, that's not a
scenario that's true. They have plenty
of computer already. The amount of
threshold they need for the concern
you're worried about, they've already
reached that threshold and beyond. When
you have abundant of energy, it makes up
for chips. If you have abundance of of
chips, it makes up for energy. For
example, United States is scarce on
energy, which is the reason why Nvidia
has to keep advancing our architecture
and do this extreme code design, so that
with the few chips that we ship, because
the amount of energy is so limited, our
throughput per watt is off the charts.
But if your amount of watts is
completely abundant, it's free,
what do you care about performance per
watt for? But then there's a question
of, okay, well, can they actually
manufacture enough chips? But they do.
Huawei just had the largest single year
in the history of the company. How many
chips did they ship? A ton. Millions.
Millions is way more than Entropic has.
Right, but as you know, the bottleneck
often in trading and doing inference on
these models is the amount of bandwidth.
So, if you HBM2, I don't I don't know
the numbers off hand, but like versus
the newest thing you have, you can be
almost an order of magnitude difference
in memory bandwidth, which is huge.
>> Huawei's a networking company. But that
doesn't change the fact that you need to
EUV for the most advanced HBM.
>> Not true. Not at all true.
You could gang them together, just like
we gang them together with MBLink 72.
They've already demonstrated silicon
photonics connecting all of these
computer together into one giant
supercomputer. Your premise is just
wrong.