There's a really cool building that I
love in Florence. It's, if you've been
there, there's the famous bridge, the
Ponttovecia, which has the little
jeweler shops all along it. And when you
get to the end of it, there's this funny
over-the- head corridor, the Vasari
corridor, as we call it, which was built
by the Dukes of Florence to connect the
old city palace to their new palace
across the river, which was much bigger.
And because they're so terrified of
being assassinated by their own people,
they built this overhead walkway so that
they could walk in safety without being
assassinated. This is a sign of a weak
Duke. But also, when he was building it,
it's going across the roofs and
sometimes blasting off the second
stories of different people's houses.
And most people when his grace, the
Duke, says, "I'm going to blast the top
story off your house," would say, "Yes,
your grace. Please continue." But they
get to this one point where there's an
old tower, a 500-year-old tower, and
this belongs to I think it's the
Minnelli family who are descended from
peers of Julius Caesar and can trace
their genealogy all the way back to an
old Roman gent. And when the Duke says,
"We want to top knock the top off your
tower," they say, "No, this is our
tower. This tower has been ours since
before the Meduche existed as a named
family. You may not knock the top off."
and the Duke does not knock the top off
and the corridor goes around in this
awkward square. These are monarchs who
know that they are weak and are
therefore careful and therefore more
rights like property rights exist.
Meanwhile, across the river in Ferrara
being a place where dukes worked very
very hard to gain power. Uh, Duke
Alphonsa Estee of Ferrara used to wander
around Ferrara buck naked with a sword
in one hand and his dick in the other to
show off that nobody would ever possibly
try to harm a duke to estate.