All of these republics except Florence
are modeled on ancient Rome. So you have
a small slice of the population that are
fully infranchised members of the
republic who rule over the commoner
majority. Florence was like that for
quite a while. But when republics fell,
they usually fell to noble families. And
after one particular near miss in which
the city was nearly taken over, they
decided to get rid of the nobility of
Florence and they massacred most of them
and cut their heads off and put them on
pikes and burned their houses down and
raked sold into the earth and had a
party on their graves the way you do in
the period when you're getting rid of a
class of people. And they set up a
commoner republic. What that meant was
the Senate consisted of members of
merchant guilds, not the guy who sits at
the loom weaving, but the guy who owns
the warehouse full of looms where the
workers are working. And they've set up
a really weird republic in which a bunch
of merchants are trying to share power.
Their names go in a bag. You choose nine
guys at random. They are put in a palace
where they rule the city from that
tower. They're actually locked in the
tower for the duration of their time in
office because if they left the tower,
they could be bribed or kidnapped. and
they ruled the city for 2 months or 3
months and then at the end they are
thanked for their service and escorted
out and different nine guys share power
for the next 3 months. From the
perspective of every other polity in the
world, the rulers of Florence are the
rank of their valet. There is no
nobility left in the