People are like Goodberg was an inventor
and invented a thing and then it had an
impact. No, he was living in the middle
of a library building boom in which
there was a huge demand for books that
spiked. He invented the invention in
response to that cultural change. It
isn't by [music] chance that we got the
printing press in 1450. There was a huge
boom of library building starting in the
1410s and inventors were trying to
figure out ways to make books cheaper.
They were making smaller books. They
were [music] using paper more. They were
trying to do this paper surges before
the Gutenberg move type printing press.
So Gutenberg isn't a random genius out
of nowhere. It's at this point it was
the moment that people needed more
books. We were gonna get the invention.