So one thing when we read Mchavel he
talks a lot about the po which we
translate as the people and he talks
about how important it is that the po
are respected and the po have a voice
and that the po are armed and the
government shows respect for the people
by allowing the people to be armed. We
read this and we're like yeah this feels
really familiar. This feels like
documents of the founding of the US
where we're respecting and arming and
and trusting the people. Popp meant the
top 4% economically of the population
the members of the merch merchant
guilds. That's the po. We didn't realize
that in the 19th century when we were
excitedly translating the prince and
reading it as quasi democratic. So the
po is the 5% and then he's talking about
quarrels between them and theati the
best which are the 0.01%.
>> I see. Okay. Cuz there's a big part of
the prince where he says it's in many
situations better to piss off the quote
unquote nobles instead of the people
because there's so many fewer nobles and
you can just replace the nobles with the
people. And if you piss off the people,
it's like it's it's a much tougher
situation. What he means is it's better
to piss off the the Jeff Bezos instead
of the city millionaire.
>> Want the millionaires to be on your side
and it's fine to piss off the
billionaires. That's really what he's
saying. I see.