From the perspective of every other
polity in the world, the rulers of
Florence are the rank of their valet.
There is no nobility left in the city.
In fact, Florence can't run its own
armies or head its own police because
you're not going to surrender if you're
told to surrender in the name of some
guy who doesn't have a coat of arms,
right? That would be weird. So, they
actually have to hire a nobleman to come
to the city and be their chief of police
to arrest people in the name of the Holy
Roman Emperor. One at a time, they'll
invite skilled military commander
nobleman. He'll come to the city. He'll
be put a star. He'll live in the palace,
which is also the prison. He'll arrest
people who enforce the law. They will
pay him handsomely. At the end of the
year, escort him to the gates and then
banish him from the city for life on
pain of death so that he cannot return
and make use of the power that he had in
the city to try to take over. So,
they're very wary of any noble nobleman.