Why was quantum computing not a thing in
the 1950s? Like it could have been. John
Vonoman good example. Absolutely
pioneering computation. Also wrote a
very important book about quantum
mechanics. A couple things that I think
are interesting. One is that of course
computation became far more salient sort
of late '7s early ' 80s. You know it
just became a thing which many more
people were interested in partially for
you know for very banal reasons. You
could go and buy a PC, you could buy an
Apple 2, you could buy a Commodore 64,
you could buy all these kinds of things.
Became apparent to people that these
were very powerful devices. At the same
time, in the quantum case, that was also
the time of the ball trap and and the
ability to trap single ions and and so
on. And up to that point, we hadn't
really had the ability to manipulate
single quantum states. You kind of got
these two separate things that just for
historically contingent reasons had both
sort of matured around sort of, let's
say, 1980 or so. a story about Richard
Fineman. He went and got one of the
first PCs and he was apparently just so
excited he actually tripped and and hurt
himself quite badly carrying his brand
new computing device. That's a very
historically contingent coincidence. But
having somebody who's very very talented
and and understanding of of quantum
mechanics, also just very excited about
these new machines, it's not so
surprising perhaps that that he's
thinking then what similar story could
you have told 10 years earlier? the
conditions don't exist for it.