One problem Mchule doesn't discuss
directly but does discuss indirectly is
that [music] it's very common for the
son of a hardworking ruler who realized
that he needs to work hard to please the
people. The son will grow up an entitled
jerk because his father understood that
he needed to do the hard work to gain
power. [music] But the kid who grew up
in the lap of luxury and has never known
anything than his father in power will
be entitled. So if you look at the Roman
emperors, the adopted Roman emperors,
the one where the emperor didn't have an
heir and then chose somebody who had to
work hard to earn that succession. Those
are the ones we remember as the really
good emperors, Traan, Hadrien, Marcus
Aurelius. And a lot of the worst
emperors are the ones who were direct
inheritants [music] because they grew up
in the lap of luxury like Comedus and
Caligula. And similarly, you have
situations like the Dukes of Ferrara who
worked very hard over several
generations to rise from being lords to
Marquis' [music] to dukes establishing
Ferrara as a major capital, making it
famous, making important marriage
[music] alliances. They have one
generation with the ducal title very
stably in hand. He works really hard to
make Ferrara powerful. His kids are a
bunch of entitled jerks who gouge each
other's eyes out in quarrels over
girlfriends and bring into disrepute
what had been earned with such effort by
their fathers.