Sometimes there are more steps to
something than you think. So in the
Renaissance they rediscovered these
ancient texts and then we got science
and that's true but it is an
oversimplification and too wide a zoo.
And if I said the French Revolution
Napoleon rose to power and spread
nationalized warfare across Europe and
then we landed on the moon. I've skipped
some steps and we know that about
modernity but we don't remember that
about earlier periods. For new ideas to
flourish and new ways of running the
world to happen you need a fertile
environment. It takes a while to get
enough books. You can't publish a
scientific journal until there are
journals. People talk about it sometimes
in terms of increasing literacy rates as
if higher literacy makes there be more
books instead of the other way around.
Florence has a male literacy rate of 90%
because everybody's in the merchant
world so you have to be able to send
letters. You have to be able to read
account books. But of those people how
many have read a book? Very few. The
difference between being literate and
being book literate is different in the
same way that some people watch
television don't watch very many films.
Other watch lots of films, right? You
can be literate and have never read a
book. And so literacy transforms into a
kind of access to scientific,
intellectual, legal, all sorts of
different kinds of worlds of [music]
ideas. And science is predicated upon
all of these other developments.