Capernicus' theory of of the planets. It
was less accurate than Tomy's theory.
Capernacus very famously proposed the
heliocentric model. Geocentrism had been
developed for a millennium by that point
and they had made many many tweaks and
and and very increasingly complicated ad
hoc fixes to to make it more and more
accurate. Capernicus proposed that the
orbits of the planets were perfect
circles and capernicus theory was a lot
simpler but much as accurate. It was
only Kepler that made it more accurate
than Tomley's theory. He started
proposing that uh you know if you take
say the orbit of say the earth and you
enclose it in I think maybe a cube the
outer sphere of that that encloses the
cube almost match perfectly the orbit of
Mars and so forth and there were six
planets known at the time five gaps
between them and there were five perfect
platonic solids and so he had this this
this theory which he thought was
absolutely beautiful that he could
inscribe these platonic solids between
the spheres of the planets and it seemed
to fit and it seemed to be to him like
you know God's design of the planets was
was matching this mathematical
perfection of the platonic solids. So he
needed data to confirm this theory and
at the time there was only one really
highquality data set. So Takubrai this
Danish astronomer had managed to
convince the Danish government to fund
this extremely expensive observatory
this in fact an entire island where he
had taken decades of observations of all
the planets. And so he had all this data
which Kepler could use to confirm his
theory. And then he worked out to kind
of his disappointment that um his
beautiful theory didn't quite work. Like
the data was sort of off from his um
platonic solid theory by you know about
10% or something. And he had all kinds
of fudges moving the circles around and
things and it it didn't quite work. But
he worked on this problem for for for
years and years and eventually he
figured out how to use the data to to
work out the actual orbits of the
planets. And that was an incredibly
clever genius amount of data analysis.
And then he eventually worked out that
the orbits were actually ellipses not
circles which was shocking to him. So he
worked out the two laws of planetary
motion. The ellipses also equal areas
sweep out equal times. And then 10 years
later after collecting a lot of data he
finally worked out this third law also
that the time it takes for a planet to
commit its orbit was proportional to
some power of the distance to the sun.
And these are the three famous Kepler
laws of motion. And he had no
explanation for them. It was just all
driven by by experiment. And it took
Newton a century late later to give a
theory that explained all three laws at
once.