I study the history of censorship.
They're always wrong from our
perspective about what they should be
worried about censoring. So here we are
in the French enlightenment. Voltater
and Rouso and the Marquita Assad and
Latreul articulations of materialist
atheism are flying around Europe. And
what is the Inquisition worried about?
It's worried about Jansenist treatises
about the nature of the Trinity.
Jansenism is sort of like a Calvinist
version of Catholicism. And they are so
much more worried about Jansenism than
they are about Voltater. That very uh
chapter in Matis's book I mentioned
where they're raiding the clandestine
bookshop and they're like Voltater fine.
The band Cyclopedi which is going to
revolutionize all thought in Europe.
Fine. Jansenous treatises about the
nature of the Trinity. Throw the book at
these guys. This is the worst thing.
They really are obsessed with this
incredibly petty minor heresy to the
degree that when the encyclopedi is
banned by Rome, they agree they're going
to have the ceremonial burning and they
march the encyclopedi up to the fire and
then they get some chances about the
nature of the trinity and burn those
instead because they don't want to burn
the encyclopedi. They love it. They want
to burn this other thing. And this is
always true.