You do have popes during this period who
are willing to go to war.
>> Very. [music]
>> Why doesn't the Vatican take over Italy?
>> One reason is nobody is going to elect a
young pope. Nobody wants one person to
be in power that long. So if you have 20
years, that's a long run. You usually
have closer to 10. That is a time to
conquer stuff, but it is not enough time
to consolidate [music]
that stuff. Popes are also always
running into problems with promises made
by the last pope. You know, here is a
city within the papal states.
Technically, I am the overlord of it.
However, two popes ago, when the pope
was losing a war and desperate, he
promised this mercenary that he could
have this city forever and his children
could as well. A problem with power is
legitimacy, right? How much the local
people actually believe in and respect
and value that particular government,
whether it's a republic or a monarchy.
And when you break that, you have to do
a lot of work to get buy in for the new
thing. And what repeatedly happens in
the papal states when a pope says, "I'm
going to oust the ruler of this city and
put in my guide." Is that the next pope
ousts it again and the next pope oust it
again or midway through the papacy the
people rebel and welcome back the person
who was there before. Because once
you've broken the line of legitimacy and
it's no longer obvious who should rule,
then all sorts of people will claim they
should rule and you have a long period
of rapid turnover before people get so
tired of civil war that they all agree,
okay, let's back this one guy just so
that we can end it. And have peace.