I'm working on a paper right now about
the video game Civ. Civ is the number
one teacher of history in the world and
it has shipped 70 million copies and 65%
of people on Earth who have technology
play video games. And what does Civ tell
you? Civ tells you that in antiquity a
turn is 50 years. And then in the middle
ages a turn is 25 years. And then once
you get into industrial revolution a
turn is 10 years and then 5 years. And
in modernity a turn is just one year.
Because in one year as much happens now
as happened in 50 years in antiquity.
And that lie is also what our textbooks
tell us. But it doesn't matter where we
zoom in. Anytime I go to a talk where
any historian is zooming in on any
decade in any time and place, it always
feels like it's moving as fast as our
present is moving.