Without papyrus, what you're writing on
is a dead sheet. And if you think of the
price of a head of lettuce and the price
of a leather jacket, you're
understanding the difference between a
sheet of papyrus and writing on a dead
sheep. So every page of a medieval book
is as expensive as that much of a
leather jacket. And a medieval book
handwritten costs as much as a house.
And so to have a library is to be not
just rich but mega rich. So only the
wealthiest cities contain anybody who
has a library. The great library of the
University of Paris, the library from
Europe's perspective has 600 books.
There's definitely more than 600 books
in this room. Every kiosk at an airport
selling Dan Brown novels has more than
600 books. This is nothing. And at the
same time as that, in the Middle East,
sultans have libraries of over a,000
books or 5,000 books. There are
libraries in subsaran Africa with
thousands of books. There are libraries
in China with thousands of books because
they in China have cheap paper and rice
paper. The Middle East has papyrus.
Europe and only Europe is writing on all
leather jackets.