This idea that people have that Newton
was the first modern scientist is
somehow wrong. There's some truth to it,
but he really had this very different
way of looking at the world that was
part superstitious and part modern. It
was a funny hybrid. He's sort of this
transitional figure in some sense. I
love this particular quote. Newton was
not the first of the age of
[clears throat] reason. He was the last
of the magicians, the last great mind
which looked out on the visible and
intellectual world with the same eyes as
those who began to build our
intellectual inheritance
>> [music]
>> rather less than 10,000 years ago. That
phrase, the last of the magicians,
really points at something. [music]
>> What do you think it means? Because the
things we know him for, where where is
the room for superstition?
>> Yeah, there's a reason why so many of
these people that were often alchemists,
they were often very interested [music]
in theology, they were often very
interested in things which from a modern
point of view appear very adjacent to
magic. [music] I mean, what are
scientists actually doing? We're writing
down squiggles on a on a page based on
observations in the world and then using
it to accomplish miracles. Like that's
the outside view, right? It's exactly
what magicians do. [music] If you're an
outsider, the ability to launch rockets,
the ability to create atomic bombs, the
ability [music] to do all of these
things on the basis of of squiggles on a
paper, you're writing down spells.