As you mentioned in Venice, they've
really scaled the printing press. As a
result, you have the metal working for
fine type setting, milling technology,
for water mills, windmills as advanced.
Why didn't Italy have the industrial
revolution?
>> If you're already the center of big
finance, big wool, and big oil,
>> yeah,
>> do you need an industrial revolution?
You're already economically on top
through the power of agriculture. What
was England producing? [music] Crappy
quality wool. England was so aware that
it couldn't process wool into high
quality without masses of olive oil
which it couldn't produce that England
just exported its crude wool to
Florence. So that's one reason that
industrialization doesn't kindle in
Italy. It doesn't feel like it needs new
industry. Another is it's so subdivided
because those rich cities are still
mostly independent whereas a centralized
crown in England is more able to pass
legislation to facilitate a massive
transformation. No city really wants to
be the one where the giant
industrialization is happening. It's
awful for the city.