When the Roman Empire dissolved in the
West, individual cities then needed to
self-govern. And this is true all across
Europe. And those individual cities
could no longer get the centralized
Roman government to oversee supply
routes, keep the roads free of bandits.
You had to support [music] things
yourself. So, the larger, wealthier
towns surrounded by good agricultural
land were more successful at converting
over to, "Okay, let's have a senate like
the old Roman senate. Let's have our top
families form a council. They will rule.
We'll set up a republic." A weaker town
is much more prone to one wealthy family
realizes that they can get goons and
take over and declare themselves the
monarch of the area. Or worse, this town
cannot self-sustain. It doesn't have
enough people there, can't get food,
they're afraid of being robbed by people
who are desperate. But outside of town,
there is a wealthy villa that belongs to
a noble family, and they have
bodyguards. "Hey, noble family, if I
move next to your villa and work for
you, will you protect me with your
bodyguards?" So, towns emptied out, and
villages, as in villa and its environs,
developed. So, Italy had great
agriculture. The more of Italy's cities
were able to sustain themselves as towns
[music]
and be republics than in other regions.