You actually do need a certain level of
distraction in your life. And maybe
there's a danger actually that modern
society is it's not just AI, but we've
become really good at optimizing
everything. You know, with with COVID
for example, we switched a lot to remote
meetings. Um and so everything was
scheduled now. And so
uh we kept busy at least uh
in academia, you know, we we met almost
the same number of people that we met um
in person, but everything had to be
planned. And what we lost out on was
sort of the the casual like
walking in the hallway, just meeting
someone, you know, while getting a
coffee. This um serendipitous
interactions that you may think are not
optimal, but actually really important.
I spent a year once at the Institute for
Advanced Study. There's no distractions.
You you you're there to just do
research. And like the first few weeks
you're there, like it's great. You're
getting all these papers written up that
you've been wanting to do for a long
time. You've been thinking about
problems for blocks of hours of a time.
But I find that if I had stayed there
for more than a several months, like I I
run out of of inspiration somehow. Like
I get bored. I actually, you know, surf
the internet a lot more. So I believe a
lot in serendipity. When I was a grad
student, when I had to look for a a
journal article, you had to physically
go to the library, check out the
journal, and read your article. And
sometimes the next article, you know,
you can just browse through and then the
next article is also interesting. Um
uh not that it wasn't, but but you could
accidentally find interesting things,
which is something which has basically
been lost now because you can just type
in you know, if you if you if you want
to access an article now, you just type
it into to a search engine or even an
AI, and you can get instantly what you
want. But you don't get so the
accidental things that uh that you you
might have gotten if you'd done it more
inefficiently.