When Nvidia first started, there were 60
3D graphics companies. We are the only
one that survived. If you would have
taken those 60 graphics companies and
asked yourself which one was going to
make it, Nvidia would be the top of that
list not to make it. You know, this is
long before you, but Nvidia's graphics
architecture was precisely wrong. And it
was an impossible thing for developers
to support. It was never going to make
it. We reasoned about it for good reason
for for from good first principles, but
we ended up in the wrong solution and
everybody would have counted us out and
here we are. And so I have enough
humility to recognize that, you know,
don't don't pick winners. There are so
many great amazing foundation model
companies and we try to invest in all of
them and it's part of our joy of doing
so. It's it's an imperative to our
business, but we also go out of our way
not to pick winners. And so when I
invest in one of them, I invest in all
of them. Either let them all take care
of themselves or take care of all of