Today I'm chatting with Ada Palmer,
who's a Renaissance historian,
novelist, and composer based
at the University of Chicago.
Today we're discussing your
book, Inventing the Renaissance.
Ada, thanks for coming on the podcast.
Been looking forward.
First question.
You've got in this period—late
15th century, early 16th century—in
Italy all these different
republics: Venice, Florence, Genoa.
That seems unusual both for the
time period and for the place.
One of the big reasons that the
Italian city republics are clustered
in Italy is that when the Roman Empire
dissolved in the West, individual
cities then needed to self-govern.
This is true all across Europe.
Those individual cities could no
longer get the centralized Roman
government to oversee supply routes
or keep the roads free of bandits.
You could no longer import
and export goods at scale.
You could no longer rely
on central infrastructure.
You had to support things yourself.
Larger, wealthier towns were able
to make this transition because they
could support themselves from the local
resources and the farms attached to them.
The larger, wealthier towns surrounded
by good agricultural land were
more successful at converting over.
Okay, let’s have a senate
like the old Roman Senate.
Let's have our top
families form a council.
They will rule.
We'll set up a republic.
A weaker town that can't support
itself as well is much more prone to
one wealthy family realizing that they
can get goons and take over, declaring
themselves the monarch of the area.
Or worse, this town cannot
self-sustain, it doesn’t have enough.
People there can't get food.
They are scared and afraid of being
robbed by people who are desperate.
But outside of town, there is a
wealthy villa that belongs to a noble
family, and they have bodyguards.
"Hey, noble family, if I move next
to your villa and work for you, will
you protect me with your bodyguards?"
So towns emptied out, and
villages—as in a villa and its
environs—developed as a result.
A village was a monarchal
structure in this sense.
It was the migration of people
out of a town into the protection
zone of a local lordling.
Then those villages grew to different
scales, some of them cities, some not.
Italy had great agriculture and
great agricultural land, so more of
Italy's cities were able to sustain
themselves as towns and be republics.
I feel like the big take of
your book is they were trying
to resuscitate Roman virtues.
What were the virtues that the Roman
emperors had which allowed this safety,
good government, et cetera, to work?
Stability.
And I don't understand the
connection between reading Cicero and
contemplating the virtues of a great
emperor to… science and technology.
Maybe there isn't one, but
do you think there is one?
What exactly is that connection?
As with many processes, the answer
is that there are multiple steps,
and it's complicated, and some
of the steps are realizing that
the earlier steps didn't work.
Petrarch, who lived through the Black
Death, and lives in a moment when Italy is
wracked by civil war and foreign mercenary
troops are raiding and pillaging.
Italy is wracked by bandits.
When Petrarch survives the
Black Death after losing so
many friends, he gets a letter.
Two of his friends are alive.
He had given up hope that anyone he
knew would survive, but two of his
younger scholar friends are alive.
They're going to come visit him.
On the way, they were attacked by bandits.
One of them was killed, and the other
was lost in the mountains and wounded,
and he didn't know that his friend
was alive for another year and a half.
The bandits are very real in this period.
Petrarch looks around him and says,
"This is an age of ash and shadow.
What we need is to imitate
the arts of the ancients.
Let's try to figure out
how the Romans did it."
And specifically, the
problem is our leaders.
Our leaders are selfish.
Our leaders care more about their
wealth and their family honor and their
power than they do about the people.
This is where Romeo and Juliet is
really helpful for us to understand.
Lord Montague and Lord Capulet,
as their goons are knifing each
other in the street, they care
about defeating each other.
Do they care about the good of Italy?
Do they care about the
good of the city of Verona?
No.
Their feud is harming the city
of Verona, and they don't care.
They demand that Romeo get away
with murder because he is their son.
That is not service to the state.
Petrarch reads about the ancient
Roman Brutus—not the one who killed
Caesar, but the ancestor to whom
that one was trying to live up.
Brutus was one of the first consuls of
Rome, and he learned while in office
that his sons were plotting to take
over the state and make him king.
So he executed his own sons
for treason against the state.
Can you imagine Lord Montague wanting to
execute Romeo for treason against Verona?
He would never do that.
When you're living in the plot of Romeo
and Juliet and you read about these
ancient Roman figures, as described
in the lofty biographies of someone
like Livy, you read them and you say,
"Wow, if only our leaders would act
like that." Well, how were they raised?
Can we raise our leaders the same way?
Can we make libraries filled
with what young Cicero read
and what young Brutus read?
What did they read?
They read Plato, and they read Homer.
So we need these things.
Can we recreate the educational
environment that produced them?
Petrarch suggests this.
His students and successors embrace
this idea and pour money into traveling
across the Alps to look for manuscripts,
traveling to Constantinople to purchase
manuscripts from the wealthier East
where books are common, and bringing
them back to assemble these libraries.
Then they raise tutors like Marsilio
Ficino, who can know Greek and Latin
and surround the young princes and
princesses of Europe with these
values in the hopes that they will
act like Brutus and not like Lord Montague.
This is based on an assumption
that education is very much like
osmosis, that if you're exposed
to something, you'll imitate it.
And the uptake of this is strong
because Italy is also full of upstart
rulers who just seized power five
minutes ago by having a coup in their
state and have no legitimacy and no
right to be ruling what they're ruling
and are resented by their people.
But they can dress up
like a Roman emperor.
And they can have a parade
with allegorical figures of
the virtues next to them.
And they can invest in an impressive
palace that has a pediment on the front
and looks like a Roman building to the
eyes of the period, and cover themselves
with the trappings of antiquity.
Then people might look at
them and say, "This guy is
different from what we've had.
This guy is like the Caesars.
The days of the Caesars were pretty good.
Maybe we want this guy.
Maybe he's not going to be a tyrant.
Maybe he's going to be a good prince,
and he's going to make a golden age."
And so the first dream is
idealistic: let's make better rulers.
The adoption is self-serving
and propagandistic: "Hey, I'm
a tyrant, but I can seem like
something better than just a tyrant.
If I make myself look like Julius Caesar,
then people will like and respect me."
Or in the case of Florence with
the Medici, "We are merchant scum.
We are dirt compared
to everybody around us.
We're not even one of the
important families of Florence.
We're three ranks down.
Even on the standards of merchant
scum, we're extra scummy merchant scum.
But if we can have Latin and Greek and
quote Cicero and seem like the ancients,
people will take us seriously and
respect us and talk to us even if we
don't have it." Let me give an example.
Imagine that you are an ambassador from
France, and you're on your way to Rome,
because a new pope has just been elected.
Whenever a new pope is elected, every
country in Europe has to send a special
ambassador whose job it is to deliver
a long-winded oration that says, "I
am the ambassador from a very wealthy
country and a very powerful prince."
And he's so glad you're the pope.
Congratulations.
Only you have to do that for an hour.
You have to give a gift to the pope, and
it has to be very impressive, and you
have to be a really important person.
You're the most important person
who can leave your country without
causing a political crisis.
You might be the heir to
the throne, for example.
Or you might be a more minor ambassador,
but you're at least the son of a count.
You're on your way to Rome, you're heading
along the length of Italy, you're going
to go through Florence, it's on the way.
Ugh.
There's nobody there worth
talking to because it's just
a pit of scum and villainy.
In fact, also filth and depravity
because, of course, Florence is
the sodomy capital of Europe.
To Florentine is the verb for anal sex
in several different European languages.
In the laws of France, you can
be indicted for sodomy on the
grounds that you have ever once in
your life even visited Florence.
That's considered evidence enough.
So you're on your way to this matchlessly
filthy dive of scum and villainy.
And then you approach the city,
and there are these statues.
They look like ancient statues, the
kind that are so lifelike that it's as
if they're about to breathe and move.
You've never seen an intact
new statue like that.
That isn't something we know how to do.
You ride through the city a bit, and it's
a large, impressive city, and you get to
the cathedral, and it has this massive
dome, way bigger than anything you've
ever seen except for old Roman ruins.
You come to the banker's house, and
your servant knocks at the door.
The banker greets you humbly at the door
and apologizes that his humble palace
is not worthy to host Your Excellency,
and you're like, "Yeah, it's not.
You're correct." He invites you in, and
the instant you step inside, you're in
a space like nothing you've ever seen
before with white light streaming in
through this airy, rounded windowed
courtyard that feels cleaner and more
outdoors than the outdoors did, because
something about the air is cool and fresh.
It's like nothing you've— Wait, wait.
It is.
It's like the Roman ruins in the
backyard of the castle where you grew up.
But we don't have the
ability to do that anymore.
All that's lost.
In the middle of the square is another
one of these bronze statues that
looks like it's about to come to
life, except it's shining and new.
It hasn't even turned green yet.
Around the courtyard are busts of
all the Roman emperors in order,
and above them are portraits of this
guy and the members of his family.
Off in the corner are some men
wearing robes that look like
the robes the ancients wear.
You say, "Who are those guys?"
He says, "Oh, they're Platonists.
They're speaking ancient Greek." You
say, "I thought I didn't understand that
language, but ancient Greek is lost.
We don't have ancient Greek." He says,
"We have lots of ancient Greek here."
You say, "And also, we don't
have the works of Plato.
They're also lost." "Oh,
we have lots of Plato here.
Look, here's my grandson, Lorenzo.
He's just written a poem in ancient
Greek about the three parts of the soul.
Would you like to hear him recite it?"
Now there's a ten-year-old boy
reciting a poem at you in ancient
Greek about the three parts of the
soul, and you're like, "Where am I?
None of this is possible. None of this
has existed for a thousand years."
That's the moment that Cosimo de'
Medici turns to you and says, "Would
you like to make an alliance with
Florence?" And you can say no.
You can say, "No.
My king is going to come over the
Alps with his enormous army, and we're
going to descend upon this city, and
we're going to sack it, and everyone's
going to let us because it has no
friends because it doesn't have any
nobility, so it can't marry anybody,
so it has no meaningful allies.
And also, it's in the middle of
this Guelph-Ghibelline feud, so
all of its neighbors hate it and
they're just going to let it burn.
We're going to take the enormous
piles of gold that are in your
basements and go home rich, and all
of this will be gone like a dream."
Or
you could say, "Yes,
let's make an alliance.
Give me a bronzesmith and an
architect and a Greek teacher and a
Platonist, and we're going to take
all of these things, and we're going
to do the French court like this.
Then when the ambassador from
Portugal comes, he's going to
feel like an uncultured fool,
just like I feel right now."
The power dynamic just
flipped upside down.
Suddenly, the condescending nobleman
is in awe of the merchant scum.
That's what the art and the culture
does as a propagandistic tool.
The next stage of it then is, "Okay,
we've raised these princes like this, and
they have the Latin, and they have the
Greek, and they can impress everybody."
Then they fight a bigger, nastier,
worse war than any of the earlier big,
nasty wars, with more deaths and more
betrayals and bigger cannons knocking
down cities and burning whole areas.
The wealth is centralized, so
the mercenaries are more numerous
because people can produce more.
The first generations raised by this
are supposed to be philosopher princes,
and instead we get Cesare and Lucrezia
Borgia, both of whom had Latin and Greek
and Cicero and Plato when they were kids.
Then they grow up,
and Cesare sets fire to half the world.
That is the war Machiavelli watched.
Machiavelli was raised on
all of the Cicero and Livy.
He was raised on the Petrarchan project.
He has this famous, beautiful letter
that he wrote in exile, where he's
describing his day to his friend.
Most of the day is wasted, and he
mucks around hunting for larks.
Then he goes to a pub and gets drunk in
the company of uncultured countrymen.
Then he goes home, and he gets dressed
in the court robes, the court finery
that he would wear back when he was
an ambassador to popes and kings.
Attired thus, he enters his library
to hold commerce with the ancients.
He loves this the way Petrarch
wanted him to love it.
But he observes these wars, and he
observes virtuous princes like Guidobaldo
da Montefeltro, who does every single
thing you're supposed to do virtuously.
He has all the Plato, and he has all
the libraries, and he has all the art.
And he gets betrayed and his city taken
away from him and loses everything.
And he watches terrible people
like Cesare Borgia and Julius II
make terrible choices and succeed.
He says, "Okay, clearly Petrarch was
wrong that just reading Cicero would
make successful rulers like the Caesars.
But I still feel in my heart
a deep power in the classics."
So he says, "What if the libraries
are what we need, but we need
to use them differently?"
He proposes what we would
think of as political science.
We observe historical examples.
We say, "Okay, here are five examples
of battles that happened next to rivers.
We'll put those examples side by
side and see what decisions the
commanders made to try to figure
out which one worked better."
We use history as a casebook of
examples of what worked and what didn't.
We imitate what worked, and
we avoid doing what didn't.
Instead of feeling that reading about good
men will make us good, we read about wise
choices, and we imitate those choices.
This is one of the reasons
Machiavelli is described by his
contemporaries as a historian.
He says we need to use history
and use the classics differently.
He proposes that.
He isn't very popular in his own day.
It takes a long time for that to catch on.
Many people for decades after him are
still trying to use absorption by osmosis.
But he's writing that in the early
1500s, so it's been a little over
a century since this started.
We have to remember how
long this process is.
From Petrarch's first call to Machiavelli
writing that is as long as from Yuri
Gagarin's space flight back to Napoleon.
The childhood of Napoleon to the space
race, that's Petrarch to Machiavelli.
We think of it as one time
period, but a lot changed.
They had a plan.
They tried the plan.
They brought the plan to its maximum.
They raised all the
princes in this new way.
The wars happened.
It clearly failed.
Machiavelli then thinks
about why it failed.
We're still only halfway
through the Renaissance.
Shakespeare's grandparents
have barely been born.
We have a lot more time to go.
So what do we need?
We need new ways of thinking about it.
We're reading the ancients,
and we have bigger libraries.
We have the printing press now.
We're having libraries in smaller towns.
More and more people can read.
It's easier and easier
to get an education.
More people are starting
to learn about science.
It also is important that they're
inventing micro technologies of
book production like footnotes
and glossaries in the margin
that explain the hard vocabulary.
When Petrarch's successors like Ficino
were young, you had to be a masterful
Latinist to read these ancients.
You had to have an enormous vocabulary.
There are no dictionaries.
There are no glosses.
There's nothing to help you.
Only a tiny slice of expert classicists
could actually read this stuff.
A hundred years later, there are
translations into the vernacular.
There are footnotes that
tell you the hard vocabulary.
Any med student can read Lucretius'
discussions of materialist information.
When Poggio found it, there were two dozen
people in the world who could read it.
A hundred years later, 30,000 people
can read it in the 30 print editions
that are printed before 1600.
When all different kinds of people read
it—med students, law students, people
in different countries, people in
different places—they ask new questions.
They wonder whether they
can test the hypotheses.
They do test the hypotheses.
They're the generation that
discovers that the heart is a pump.
They're the generation that takes
seriously the question, "Maybe
there are atoms, and maybe that's
how diseases work, and maybe we can
develop the germ theory of disease."
That's the 1560s, 1580s, 160
years after Lucretius comes back,
because it takes generations of work
to build the libraries, to have the
libraries, to use the libraries.
So when we get to 1600, which is almost
exactly 200 years after this begins, a
little bit more, we've had time to say,
"Let's build the libraries, have the
libraries, use the libraries, or realize
we failed in how we use the libraries,
and use the libraries differently."
That's the generation of Francis
Bacon and Galileo who say, "Hey,
let's use the information differently.
Let's use nature as a casebook
of examples the way Machiavelli
said we should use history.
Let's examine, let's doubt, let's
rethink, let's do stuff in new ways."
Just to make sure I understood,
the chain of causation here.
We've got to resuscitate the virtues of
the Romans, therefore read what they read.
To do that, you need
to build the libraries.
You build the libraries, you
resuscitate all those arts.
Then you just need to have people
be literate, have people think about
information in a new way to analyze it.
And that analysis lends itself not
just to the history of leaders, but
also to the nature of the world.
Whenever I hear a story about how
this is why the scientific revolution
happened, why the Industrial Revolution
happened, I'm like, but there are so
many stories and it's just hard to figure
out why this one over the other ones.
There's a dozen other
stories you could tell.
I had a previous guest, Joseph
Henrich, who has this theory that
the Catholic Church was breaking
down these old kinship-based networks
that the rest of the world had.
It was encouraging guilds, encouraging
these kinds of centers where people
could get together and discuss ideas.
There are probably twenty
other stories you could tell.
Why this story?
Two different reasons.
One, I think it's useful to think
about how for new ideas to flourish
and new ways of running the world to
happen, you need a fertile environment.
In the same way that for forests
to grow, you need enough topsoil.
It takes a while to get that topsoil.
It takes a while to get enough books.
You need to have enough books for a bunch
of people to be reading and thinking.
You also need to have networks of
information moving this stuff back
and forth so that they can have
discourses of ideas with each other.
You can't publish a scientific
journal until there are journals.
You need to have developed this
ecosystem of information and knowledge.
People talk about it sometimes in
terms of increasing literacy rates as
if higher literacy makes there be more
books instead of the other way around.
In fact, there's a lot more literacy than
people imagine in even medieval Italy.
Florence had a male literacy
rate of ninety percent.
As of the sixteenth century?
As of the twelfth century.
Because everybody's in the merchant world,
so you have to be able to send letters.
You have to be able to read account books.
You have to be able to calculate
your tab at a restaurant.
But of those people, how
many have read a book?
Very few.
They've read letters, they've
read tallies, they've read
indexes, they've made notes.
The difference between being literate
and being book-literate is different.
In the same way that some people
watch television but don't watch
very many films, while other
people watch lots of films.
You can be literate and have never
read a book because there might be
almost no books in the entire city in
which you grew up if it's 1200 or 1500.
But if it's 1600, there are definitely
books in any medium-sized town.
So literacy transforms into access to
scientific, intellectual, legal, all
sorts of different worlds of ideas.
The other person you quoted who's
talking about transformations in
networks of power from being less
family and clan-centered to being
more guild-centered… The guilds are
major generators of ideas as well.
The guilds can own libraries by 1600.
If you went to a guild hall, it will have
a bunch of books about its own trade.
That would not have been true in 1100.
Those changes are all real,
they're all intermixing, and
they're all parallel to each other.
You need all of these things together.
One of the focuses I have is
sometimes there are more steps
to something than you think.
We tell this story of the Renaissance,
of how they rediscovered these ancient
texts, and then we got science.
That's true, but it is an
oversimplification and too wide a zoom.
If I said that in the French
Revolution, Napoleon rose to power
and spread nationalized warfare
across Europe, and then we landed on
the moon, I've skipped some steps.
We know that about modernity, but we
don't remember that about earlier periods.
Obviously all the stories are somewhat
true, but to the extent that this is a
part of the story, you're building up
libraries of classics and … setting up
a network of information exchange that
leads to the Scientific Revolution…
The reason this feels salient right
now is that a lot of people have
this idea that they're going to
make AI go well by doing X thing.
Maybe some of those things work, but
it's at the same time frustrating
but also funny and interesting that
historically nobody has a good track
record of being able to say, "I
will do this thing so that this huge
unanticipated change in history will
go my way, or according to my values."
Right.
I think "go my way" as opposed to "go
well" is a really important distinction.
Petrarch
wanted a world with these values.
He thought, for example, that this
would be a triumph for Christianity
and what we would call Catholicism,
though there's only one Christianity
from his point of view at the time,
except for the East, which is different.
He was sure that when we found the
ancients, fundamentally all of their
philosophy would agree with Christianity.
The ancients were wise, therefore
they will be correct, and Plato will
ninety percent agree with Christianity.
It just needs a little shaker of the
Trinity on top to be Christianity.
When he says, "Go find these
ancients," he is in a world that
doesn't have the ancients yet.
He's just guessing what's
going to be in these books.
But he says, "If we find them,
they will uphold good values,"
and everyone believes him.
Then they go find them, and
they squabble with each other.
There are Hedonists and Epicureans and
Stoics and all sorts of chaotic things,
much more plural than he anticipated.
It makes a world that in turn has giant
wars, which he would not like, and a
crisis, and Machiavelli's critique of the
ancients, and then the new science and the
new philosophy, and eventually Galileo,
none of which resembles what Petrarch
imagined if he had specifically described
the future he was trying to make.
But then we get to the propagators
of Bacon's scientific method,
meaning Voltaire and Montesquieu,
who are also big campaigners for
inoculation against smallpox.
The first major disease eradications start
to begin under that immediate influence.
Science gets us to the germ theory
of disease gets us to modern
hygiene, which gets us to vaccines,
which gets us to penicillin and
the treatment for the Black Death.
Petrarch thought he would make
a world which shared his values.
Instead, he made a world that
doesn't share his values but is
capable of curing a disease he
never imagined would be curable.
If you showed him this
future, it would be scary.
It would be weird to him because
it does not embrace his values.
Our values are different.
He would be horrified by democracy.
He believed that only a tiny
elite has the capacity to rule.
If we had a time-traveling Petrarch,
he would really wrestle for a
long time to wrap his head around
democracy as a functional system.
He really thought in oligarchic terms.
But he would see the wonders we've
created, especially the fact that
we can treat the Black Death, and
he would weep for joy seeing that.
He did not create a world
that went as he wanted, but he
created a world that went well.
We have many examples of that.
Trains and bicycles come in, and
we get feminism because it's easier
for people, especially women, to
move freely and independently.
They can organize.
They can mobilize.
We get suffragettes.
Did the inventor of the train intend
for there to be women's liberation?
No.
Did it go the way he imagined?
Did it go well?
Yes.
It's
important here to zoom in a little
bit on Florence's own government
system and how and why it's weird,
in order to understand what rank
Machiavelli actually holds in it.
All of these republics, except
Florence, are modeled on ancient Rome.
The ancient Roman model was an
oligarchic republic in which within
the city there are certain noble
families, usually founding families
who made the city in the first place,
who are the senatorial families.
Hereditarily, when they come of
age, the men of the family are
automatically in the senate.
From among them are elected
the consuls, high senators,
or the head of state if there
is one.
You have a small slice of the
population that are fully enfranchised
members of the republic who
rule over the commoner majority.
That is how Venice works.
That is how Genoa works.
That is how Bologna and
Siena for the most part work.
That's how the Swiss Republic works.
That's how all of these republics work.
Florence was like that for quite a while,
but when republics fell, they usually fell
to noble families who are the foremost,
the strongest, the military class.
If you're a military leader in this
period, you have to have noble blood.
No soldier is going to follow a
commander who doesn't have noble blood.
That would be weird.
Those threats to the independence
of the republic almost always
came from the nobility.
After one particular near miss
in which the city was nearly
taken over, they decided to get
rid of the nobility of Florence.
They massacred most of them, cut their
heads off, put them on pikes, burned
their houses down, raked salt into the
earth, and had a party on their graves,
the way you do in the period when
you're getting rid of a class of people.
There were a few noble families
that they really liked who had
not been part of negative stuff.
They allowed them to officially
renounce their nobility.
They renounced their nobility,
changed their names, and
declared themselves commoners.
They set up a commoner republic.
What that meant was the senate
consisted of members of merchant guilds.
A member of a merchant guild here
means the owners of workshops.
It’s not the guy who sits at the
loom weaving, but the guy who
owns the warehouse full of looms
where the workers are working.
The head of the sculpture works,
the head of the architectural
firm, not the bricklayers who
are actually laying the bricks.
Bourgeoisie
is an anachronistic word, but we're
talking about the owners of the means of
production who are themselves commoners.
They are very wealthy, but from
the point of view of the diplomatic
corps of any other society, all of
the ruling people and all of their
ambassadors are noble-blooded.
If you're an ambassador, you're
automatically noble-blooded.
Nobody's going to take an
ambassador seriously who isn't.
From the perspective of every other
polity in the world, the rulers of
Florence are the rank of their valet.
There is no nobility left in the city.
In fact, Florence can't run its own
armies or head its own police, because
you're not going to surrender if you're
told to surrender in the name of some
guy who doesn't have a coat of arms.
That would be weird.
So they actually have to hire a
nobleman to come to the city and be
their chief of police to arrest people
in the name of the Holy Roman Emperor.
One at a time, they'll invite
a skilled military commander
nobleman who will come to the city.
He'll be podestà.
He'll live in the palace,
which is also the prison.
He'll arrest people.
He'll enforce the law.
They will pay him handsomely at the end
of the year, escort him to the gates,
and then banish him from the city for
life on pain of death so that he cannot
return and make use of the power that
he had in the city to try to take over.
They're very wary of any nobleman.
They've set up a really weird
republic—weird from the perspective of
everyone around them—in which a bunch
of merchants are trying to share power
by being lotteried into the senate.
You put names in a bag.
You examine all of the
merchant members of guilds.
You choose which ones are fit to
serve, meaning not ill and dying,
not insane, not so deeply in debt
that they could be manipulated by
the people whom they owe money to.
Their names go in a bag.
You choose nine guys at random.
They rule the city.
They are put in a palace where
they rule the city from that tower.
They're actually locked in the tower
for the duration of their time in
office because if they left the tower,
they could be bribed or kidnapped.
They rule the city for
two or three months.
At the end, they are thanked for
their service and escorted out, and
then a different nine guys share
power for the next three months.
It's a power sharing that is designed
to be tyrant-proof because you need
consensus of nine randomly selected
guys to decide to do anything.
Oh, it's not even a majority
vote, it's consensus?
It's consensus.
Previously you were describing
"kill the nobles, salt the earth".
I'm almost thinking early communists.
But then you say it's the heads of
the merchant guilds who are in charge.
I want to understand why
merchants and entrepreneurs
have notable status in Florence.
What is it about the
culture that makes it so?
Also, the Medici, the most powerful
people, their job is usury.
It's like the church—
It's important to remember they
were nobody when this set up.
They were a minor important family.
But the culture is getting started where
somebody like that could be respected.
How does that happen?
An important part of it is when you
have a merchant capital, everybody
works for somebody who works for
somebody who works for the boss.
If you are a major merchant in
Florence, you're importing and exporting
wool to and from all across Europe.
You have employees all across Europe.
You're buying mass bulk wool from England,
importing it to Florence to use olive oil
that you've bought from Naples to process
into high-quality wool, which you're
then exporting to Germany and France.
You are a very interconnected businessman.
You have a lot of contacts, you have a lot
of clout, and the employees who work for
you look to you for their safety net as
well as their political representation.
We're very accustomed in the modern
period to thinking of the government
as being our big safety net.
If we wonder who is going to fund
the hospitals, whose job is it to
take care of orphans, we think of
the government, or maybe the church.
But in this period, if you're
killed and you leave orphans
behind, it is your employer whose
duty it is to take care of them.
If you are injured and can no longer
work, it is your employer who will
support you for the rest of your life
while you are disabled and find you work
that you can do with that disability.
A huge portion of the
safety net is your employer.
Are you in trouble with the law?
Your employer will supply
your defense attorney.
Your employer will supply the persuasive
note to the judge that they would very
much appreciate if their person got off.
This is the system known as the patronage
system, and it existed in ancient Rome.
It exists and saturates the medieval and
the Renaissance worlds in which everyone
is in a very interconnected hierarchy.
So if you're a brewer and your son
gets in a barroom brawl and punches
somebody out and the person's nose
breaks and they die in the brawl and
your son is suddenly in trouble and you
say, "Oh no, I don't want my son to be
executed," you turn to your landlord.
Your landlord turns to his landlord.
They turn to one of these major families.
These major families are massive
landowners that own dozens of
apartments within the city.
Hundreds or thousands
of people work for them.
So it makes sense to everyone to be
represented that way, like having
a council of the CEOs of all of the
organizations that employees work
for, when your corporation also
supplies your social safety net and
you see your representation there.
It's also a world that's used to thinking
in terms of hierarchy and very unused
to thinking about real democracy.
It really doesn't have any confidence
in what we would recognize as democracy.
We talk about these republics, and
we're very excited by the fact that
they give more power to the people
than a monarchy does, but they're still
incredibly narrow oligarchic republics.
When we read Machiavelli, he talks
a lot about the popolo, which
we translate as "the people."
He talks about how important it is that
the popolo are respected and have a
voice, that the popolo are armed, and
the government shows respect for the
people by allowing them to be armed.
We read this and we're like,
"This feels really familiar.
This feels like documents of the
founding of the US where we're respecting
and arming and trusting the people."
Popolo meant the top 4%
economically of the population,
the members of the merchant guilds.
That's the popolo.
He's talking about a narrow-slice
oligarchy being heard, a narrow-slice
oligarchy being respected.
We didn't realize that in the
nineteenth century when we were
excitedly translating The Prince
and reading it as quasi-democratic.
We now have read more documents
of the period and realize
how people use these words.
Florence in this period goes through
five different forms of government.
It's this republic of nine
dudes in a tower, as you were
saying, before 1434, and then—
There's a gradual takeover.
There's a gradual, what we
could call regulatory capture.
But an interesting detail about Florence,
even as the Medici take over, is that the
Medici know the people of Florence are
very deeply invested in this republic and
very deeply invested in its institutions.
Therefore, they have to respect
those institutions and proclaim
respect for those institutions.
So they're going to sustain people in
the named offices that there used to be.
They're going to continue to
let the guilds be important
and have important offices.
There
was a mandatory outfit that people
wore who worked in the republic.
The garment over there in the
corner is a lucco fiorentino.
This was the garment you were
mandated by law to wear if you held
office in the Florentine Republic.
To us, we look at it and say, "It's
a long red robe. It looks very
Renaissance." To them, it looked like a
toga because of the way it was draped.
They thought of this as a toga.
They're cosplaying the Roman Republic.
Wearing a Florentine toga while
in office was something that you
did to represent your fealty to
Cicero and republican values.
The dukes made their men
continue to wear these.
In fact, the first Duke, Cosimo I, would
wear one to costume balls as if in his
heart he longed not to dress like a duke,
but to dress in a toga like a republican.
It's doubly ironic because when the
Roman Republic turns to the Roman
Empire, they still have the senate.
They still have all these
old institutions, even though
it's no longer a republic.
The Roman Senate keeps
meeting until 1200 AD.
It's sort of doubly ironic that they are
doing the same thing, but in the 1500s.
And it means that more rights are
granted to the people of Florence
than to other cities that fell
to monarchies at similar points.
The monarchs of Florence know they
have to be careful, they have to
respect rights to a certain amount,
and they can't run roughshod over them.
There's a really cool building
that I love in Florence.
If you've been there, there's the famous
bridge, the Ponte Vecchio, which has
little jeweler shops all along it.
When you get to the end of it, there's
this funny overhead corridor, the Vasari
Corridor, which was built by the dukes of
Florence to connect the old city palace
where the senate used to meet—where they
had to have their seat of power—to their
new palace across the river, which was
much bigger, where they could have grand
balls and things that dukes need to have.
Because they're so terrified of being
assassinated by their own people,
they built this overhead walkway
that goes from one end of the city
to the other so that they could walk
in safety without being assassinated.
This is a sign of a weak duke.
But also, when he was building it,
it's going across the roofs and
sometimes blasting off the second
stories of different people's houses.
Most people, when His Grace the
Duke says, "I'm gonna blast the top
story off your house," would say,
"Yes, Your Grace, please continue."
There are literally severed heads of
people who resisted still rotting on
spikes in front of the Palazzo Vecchio.
But they get to this one
point where there's a very old
tower, a 500-year-old tower.
This belongs to the Mannelli family,
who are descended from peers of Julius
Caesar and can trace their genealogy
all the way back to an old Roman gens.
When the duke says, "We want to
knock the top off your tower,"
they say, "No, this is our tower.
This tower has been ours since before
the Medici existed as a named family.
You may not knock the top off."
And the duke does not knock the top off.
The corridor goes around in this
awkward square around that tower,
because he knows that if he violates
something as traditional and core to
the civilization as the property rights
of somebody who has owned something for
a long time, there will be rebellion,
civil war, dissent, and resistance.
These are monarchs who know that
they are weak and are therefore
careful, and therefore more rights,
like property rights, exist.
Meanwhile, across the river in Ferrara,
Duke Alfonso I d'Este of Ferrara used
to wander around Ferrara buck naked with
a sword in one hand and his dick in the
other, to show off that nobody would
ever possibly try to harm a Duke d'Este.
He and his siblings used to do things
like, if they liked a musician, kidnap
them and lock them in a tower so that
nobody else could hear them, or if
they wanted each other's musician, send
goons to kidnap each other's musicians.
They also used to recreationally
murder each other's servants when the
siblings were tiffing with each other.
That is what you do when you
don't fear your people and when
you feel confident in power.
They are much closer to tyrants
than the Medici are ever able to
be, even after the republic falls.
That's what's so neat.
Because the resistance failed, if
we're looking at it in black and white.
The republic fell.
There wasn't a republic anymore.
There was a duke.
He took over, and the old system was gone.
But because the republic fought so hard
and because the people really believed
in it, the people had a lot more rights,
and the tyrant was a lot less tyrannical
because there had been that fight.
It's a great example of how even when
resistance loses, resistance wins.
I think there's an interesting parallel
to today, not to be too on the nose,
but sometimes people debate the odds
that America becomes a Putinist kind
of country within a couple of decades.
I think the odds are actually quite low.
Just because even though constitutionally,
or at least in precedent, the
president is very powerful, the
republican expectation is so strong.
The amount of resistance faced, even
when you successfully do something,
demotivates the next escalation.
The only thing that makes resistance
weak in the US is when people feel
as if partial victory is failure.
Remembering moments like how Florence's
resistance all the way to the end meant
that there was more liberty for the next
several centuries, even under the tyrant,
is what we need to remind ourselves, that
partial victory is an important thing.
Even if the worst were to happen and
there were to be tyranny, that tyranny
would be so much weaker because there
was a lot of resistance, and traditions
of resistance and structures would
develop that would continue to exist.
I think you should discuss the fact that
the Medici are the bankers for the papacy.
What does that mean?
Why is that necessary?
How are they able to make money off of
that from the interest on the float?
When Cosimo de' Medici swings the
contract as banker for the pope,
it's important to remember that when
you can't wire transfer money in the
pre-modern world, collecting taxes is a
very difficult and complicated system.
It is generally done by the
centralizing power that has the right
to tax delegating somebody local.
If you're in a town, there'll
be a local tax collector.
It's his job to go around to everybody
and collect taxes, send a portion of
those taxes home to the central power,
and keep a remainder to pay himself.
The central power will say, "We expect
X amount of taxes from this area."
When you hear about wicked tax
collectors, it's because if you are
told, "We want 10,000 florins worth of
tax from this town," but you extract
15,000, you can keep the other 5,000.
The 10,000 is what you need to send
to the central power, so the more
you extract, the more you get paid.
This delegate system, in which there's a
local tax collector and even a more local
tax collector below him who might collect
tax from a particular village, means
that you depend a lot upon the person
whose job it is to collect your taxes.
When Cosimo is papal banker, he is the
person collecting and channeling the money
from every church in Christendom when
everybody puts a coin into a collection
box or pilgrims come and put money.
All of the wealth that's supposed
to flow back to the papacy is
actually flowing to Cosimo.
Cosimo is passing it on to
the papacy after taking a cut.
That is a lot of money moving quickly.
There is also a lot of ability
to make contracts and contacts.
We all know how important networking is.
He rises in prominence from a banker
to somebody who has enough money to
effectively take over his state via
manipulating the guys-out-of-a-bag system.
To discuss that again briefly, if you
have a system where you lottery people,
sortition is the technical term for it.
This is a very old form of government.
Ancient Athens used it.
It actually works really well.
But like any institution,
it is corruptible.
In the same way that you can corrupt
voting by bribing people or manipulating
the machines or manipulating voters, you
can also corrupt sortition by bribing
the people who pull names out of the bag.
Or you can use the simpler
mechanism which Cosimo uses first.
If you're a giant bigwig in the city
and you employ a third of the people in
the city and they’re on your payroll,
and nine guys at random are chosen
out of a bag, three of them are going
to be your guys, just statistically.
If you tell all your guys, "I want
this policy, this policy, and this
policy, and if you have questions,
send for me and I'll tell you what to
do," when the plurality on a random
council all have a plan and it's your
plan, you effectively control the city.
In that way, the Medici effectively
controlled this lotteried system,
because they guaranteed that the
plurality, in a situation that doesn't
have a majority, will always be them.
But of course, there's a chance to that.
In 1430 and 1432, Cosimo
has bad luck, and the lottery draws
a lot of people who dislike him
and doesn't draw any of his guys.
They immediately declare him
a traitor to the state, arrest
him, and lock him in a tower.
And he bribes his way out.
He offers the equivalent of about
$300,000 to the guard outside the cell
and $700,000 to the captain of the
guard to smuggle him out of the tower.
He wrote in a letter later that they
were the two most foolish men he'd ever
met because he was Cosimo de' Medici.
He would happily have paid them
tens of millions of dollars to let
him out of there, but they weren't
ambitious enough to think to ask for
more than a few hundred thousand.
So he escapes, and then the next
election they happened to elect
entirely people who just loved Cosimo.
They invited him back to the city
in triumph, declared him father
of the fatherland, and arrested
and persecuted all of his enemies,
who turned out to be guilty of tax
evasion and all sorts of other things.
That was the moment
that his grip tightened.
And he's like, "I'm going to stop
simply controlling a plurality, and
I'm going to start bribing the people
who actually run the elections."
His famous quote about this is, "It is
dangerous to be rich and not powerful."
You
need the power to defend yourself
in a situation like King of the
Mountain, where when you're on top,
everyone will try to knock you down.
This is the system into
which Machiavelli is born.
His family has worked for the
Medici family for generations.
He grows up expecting to
work for the Medici family.
But the problem with heredity is
that sometimes you get a weak link.
And in the moment that Machiavelli is
in his early twenties, he is coming of
age, about to work in government for the
first time, a government in which he is
not, in fact, even fully enfranchised.
That's one of the fascinating things
about the degree of his patriotism.
You weren't allowed to serve in
government office fully—the lotteried
offices—if your family was deep in debt.
His grandfather had a
lot of unpaid tax debt.
So he worked his whole life for
a government of which he was
not even quite a full citizen.
That shows a deep love of country, but it
also shows that even people who could not
be in office deeply loved and cared about
this republic and the important liberty
they felt they had being ruled by the 5%
instead of being ruled by one dictator.
To us, that isn't a very big difference.
They’re still both not democracy.
We would say they’re both not liberty
in the sense that we want liberty.
But it's an inch more
liberty than monarchy.
Even that small amount of
liberty, people loved it.
People were willing to fight for it.
People were willing to go to the
streets, wave their banners, and
say "libertas" for the republic.
Because they were invested in it,
Machiavelli observes, they sustained it.
But eventually, one particular
Medici—I'm not saying names because
they all have the same names over and
over, and it's really confusing—comes
to power quite young and weak.
He's basically 20 when he's suddenly in
charge of a very precarious republic.
Right then, the French are
invading Italy, and he's scared.
He botches the diplomacy with France
and falls into disrepute, and the city
takes the opportunity to kick him out.
The subsequent regimes, which are an
independent republic again, are the
ones for which Machiavelli works.
He was part of the regime that
ruled while they were in exile.
When they returned, they
viewed him as an enemy.
He didn't actively organize to
resist them, but his name was
found on a list of potential people
that an anti-Medicean resistance
movement had intended to recruit.
He is arrested, tortured, exiled,
and in exile writes The Prince.
He dedicates it to the very
family that exiled him because
they now control Florence, and
he will only work for Florence.
He doesn't want his manual of the
great secrets of statecraft to be in
the hands of anybody but his homeland,
so that it will defend his homeland.
When Florence exiles you, they tell
you, "Go to this place and wait, and
if you're good, we'll invite you back."
Florence has been doing this for ages
because Florence actually used this
as the core of its diplomatic corps.
When you have no nobility, you
can't have ambassadors in the
full-on noble ambassador sense.
There's nobody in the city of
sufficient rank to go talk to the
kings, to play chess with the sultan,
and do all the things you have
to do to be a proper ambassador.
What Florence did instead is exile
people and say, "Okay, we're exiling you.
You go to Bruges.
Be our contact in Bruges.
You go to London.
Be our contact in London.
Be good.
Send us letters informing
us what's going on.
When we have diplomatic needs to talk to
the king, we're going to send letters to
you, and you're going to forward them.
If you're good, you get to come back."
So being in exile is sort of
being on probation, but also being
entrusted with state matters.
That's not quite what
they did with Machiavelli.
With Machiavelli, they banished him to
a hamlet in the middle of the Tuscan
countryside near nothing important and
said, "Go sit in the country and rot, and
if you're good, we'll invite you back."
What everyone expects is that Machiavelli
will break that promise and leave.
Because he's a well-known statesman,
a scholar, a playwright, and a
historian, and there are dozens of
cardinals in Rome and other cities
that would love to employ him.
Kings of England love
employing Florentines to
work for them as secretaries.
Kings of Naples love employing Florentines
to work for them as secretaries.
He might go get a job tutoring the
daughters of the Duke of Milan, the way
Francesco Filelfo did when he was kicked
out of Florence for opposing the Medici.
There are lots of places it's expected
an exiled Florentine intellectual
will go where he will have the ear of
power and be able to exert influence.
He will be a mover and shaker at the
court of Milan or Naples or England.
Instead, when they say to Machiavelli,
"Sit in the country and rot, this is
a test," he passes the test and sits
in the country faithfully and rots.
If he had wanted to go be an intellectual
power broker, the correct move is to
run off to Rome and say, "I will give
up the chance to go home the way Dante
did, but I will be a Florentine in
exile, and I will write important things.
I will live at the house of wealthy men
who will support me and give me the ear
of power, and I will exert my influence
in that way." He does not do that.
He stays in the country and he rots,
and he continues writing letters home
saying, "I will serve you or nothing.
Bring me home to serve my country."
That is a weird thing to do, and not
normal for the many other Florentine
intellectuals who experienced similar
banishments in the same period.
How do we know that he wasn't just
trying to get back into power?
The answer is you read
his personal letters.
You read the way he talks about
love of his country, and you read
the way he talks to his friends.
You read the letters he wrote when he
discusses writing The Prince, and you
read the comments he exchanges with the
other friends that he shared it with.
His other works—his comic play,
which was a big hit, his history of
Florence, which was well known at the
time—those he published and circulated.
The Prince he kept in very close private
circles, circulating it only with
trusted, intimate friends, and then
the copy that he sends in to Florence.
Yes, it's a job application:
"Please bring me back.
I will work for you.
I will be loyal.
I support my city more than any
particular iteration of my city.
I support my country more
than any particular regime or
group that might be in power.
Whatever is in power in my
city, I will be faithful to it."
You see him expressing that
in lots of different ways.
When in The Prince he says you can and
should do all of these ruthless things
to keep power, we have to remember that
the end justifies the means when the
end is the survival of your country.
It's not that the end, in
general, justifies the means.
Machiavelli feels very strongly that
regime changes bring civil violence,
and civil violence sheds blood.
He has seen the streets of his
city run with blood before.
He thinks that even life under a tyrant
is better than life in a civil war,
which is usually not life at all,
given the massacre of the people and
external conquest that are likely as
a result of another regime change.
So he says, "Don't push for regime change.
Even if the regime is tyrannical, more
people will survive by sticking with
the tyrant than by changing the regime."
I want to talk about
the printing press.
One thing I didn't realize before
reading your book is that not only does
Gutenberg go bankrupt after making the
most significant invention of a millennia,
but his apprentices also go bankrupt.
This is at a time when people like
Cosimo are willing to pay on the order of
hundreds of thousands of dollars per book.
So with the guy who invents a way to make
this way cheaper, how is this possible?
The problem is printed books are a
mass-produced commodity in a world
that does not have distribution
networks for mass-produced commodities.
Mass production is incredibly
rare in this period.
Coins are mass-produced,
but that's really about it.
Almost everything is artisanally produced.
When you have a mass-produced
product, you need a distribution
mechanism before you can sell it.
The great example is that technically
e-books existed the first time
anyone typed a book on a computer.
Certainly in the 1970s there
was such a thing as an e-book.
But there was no market for e-books until
the Kindle came out and made a commodity
way to buy and sell e-books, then the
e-book industry came into existence.
So the e-book as a commodity
is several decades younger than
the e-book technically existing.
In the same way, you're Gutenberg.
You have figured out how to
produce 300 copies of a book for
the cost of one copy of a book.
You do so.
You print your Bible.
You have 300 Bibles.
You sell seven of them to the seven
people in your small landlocked German
town who are legally allowed to read
the Bible in a period in which only
priests are allowed to read the Bible.
Congratulations, Mr. Gutenberg,
you have 293 Bibles, and you can't
sell them, and you go bankrupt.
There has to be a distribution
mechanism for books to find their
market because there are certainly
300 people in Europe that want this,
but there are not 300 people in one
location where it's being produced.
So Gutenberg goes bankrupt.
The bank seizes his press.
They try to go into the business.
The bank goes bankrupt.
There is so much overhead.
You spend hundreds of thousands of
dollars on the production cost of the
books, and then you get nothing back.
Gutenberg's apprentices build presses.
They go bankrupt.
They flee their debts, flee the country,
leave Germany, and go to Venice.
Venice is the airport
hub of the Mediterranean.
Venice is where you change boats.
If you're sailing from A to B,
you go to Venice, you change
boats, you get to the next place.
The hub system has always worked well.
So if you're printing in Venice, you
print 300 Bibles, you give ten Bibles
to each of thirty ships' captains
going to thirty different cities.
They can sell them.
The first economically
sustainable circulation of print
is enabled by the hub system.
Then book fairs come into
existence in which printers will
spend all year printing a book.
They go with a thousand copies of
their book to a book fair where
there are a thousand other printers.
They all trade, and then they go
home to their town with five copies
each of 200 books instead of a
thousand copies of one book, and
then they sell them in bookshops.
Things like the Frankfurt Book Fair,
which still exists today, developed
as the distribution mechanism.
There's a slow growth
and a slow saturation.
That's really cool because one of the
things people think is unique about
our present information revolution is
that we're living in this sequence of
successive information revolutions.
We had the computer, the
computer was exciting.
Then we had the personal computer, then we
had the internet, the cell phone, social
media, and now we have different social
media networks coming in successively
causing crises one after the other.
And then we have LLMs and
other applications of machine
learning and generative AI.
It's easy to think of each of these as
different tech revolutions, as if we've
just had ten tech revolutions in a row.
But really, they are all deeper
penetration of one tech revolution:
the development of the computer.
These are all applications of computers.
In the same way, the printing press
comes in in 1450, and it isn't
done shaping the world instantly.
It
takes forty years to even
be economically sustainable.
It's not until the 1490s that
printers are making money.
And then in the 1510s, it's time for
pamphlets and pamphlet distribution.
Now there's news, and news is suddenly
done by print, and that's a revolution
on the same scale as the difference
between computers and cell phones.
We get the Reformation, which is enabled
by pamphlets in exactly the same way that
the Arab Spring is enabled by cell phones.
Then we get the newspaper, another
new application of the same technology
that follows, like social media.
It's one information revolution
having multiple successive
revolutionary applications as it
disseminates and eventually saturates.
It moves on a timescale quite similar
to the timescale in which the digital
one is happening as well, so that
print keeps hitting Europe with
successive revolutions for 150 years.
And every couple of decades, or
every decade, there'll be a new bang.
Suddenly it's possible to get a
printed pamphlet from Wittenberg
to London in seventeen days.
Oh my God, we can coordinate our
resistance movement against the Catholics.
Boom.
The Reformation happens.
That wasn't possible even a decade earlier
when it took months to get a pamphlet
from one end of Europe to the other.
So it's best to think of these very
much in parallel, the print revolution
and the digital revolution, as one big
technological change in information
that then has successive applications
as that one technology finds new forms
and disseminates more deeply and keeps
having consequences over decades.
It's not multiple separate revolutions.
It's one ongoing information revolution.
Maybe other eras also have this and I just
haven't read the books about them, but
from your book, I thought, "Oh, history
just seems to be happening really fast,
and seems to have sped up, especially
religious and political history."
Obviously, the things happening in
Italy, but even aside from that, you
have Martin Luther and the Reformation,
and then just twenty years later England
splits off from the Catholic Church,
which is unprecedented in two millennia.
Then it has a bunch of tumults
that flop, flop, flop so that
every decade feels different.
Here you are in 1506 being
nostalgic for how the world was
completely different in 1490.
And you're like, "That's pretty fast."
Here we are in 2026 often
feeling nostalgic for how
things were in the year 2000.
Is it fair to trace that back
to the printing press or its
offshoots, or is it just embedded?
It's more that history
has always moved fast.
But when we teach it in high school,
we're trying to move over large
chunks of time quickly, and so
we pretend that it moved slowly.
We have this lie that there
were long periods of stagnation.
But you can zoom in anywhere, and
you're going to find every decade feels
different, and people in the 1320s
are nostalgic for people in the 1300s.
It's always felt like history
was moving very quickly, and
things rose and things fell.
It's the lies we tell ourselves in
history books written in the 19th century
that are trying to group all of these
things together and make modernity
special that confuse us about this.
I'm working on a paper right
now about the video game Civ.
Civ is the number one teacher
of history in the world.
It has shipped 70 million copies,
and 65 percent of people on Earth
who have technology play video games.
Civ is the number one teacher of
history, bar none, since 1991.
What does Civ tell you?
Civ tells you that in antiquity, a turn
is fifty years, and then in the Middle
Ages, a turn is twenty-five years.
Once you get into the Industrial
Revolution, a turn is ten years, and
then five years, and in modernity,
a turn is just one year because in
one year, as much happens now as
happened in fifty years in antiquity.
That lie is also what
our textbooks tell us.
But it doesn't matter where we zoom in.
Any time I go to a talk where any
historian is zooming in on any
decade in any time and place, it
always feels like it's moving as
fast as our present is moving.
I guess the difference is that
technologically, we know that
they weren't moving as fast.
Technologically, they were moving fast.
We just don't care about
those technologies anymore.
That’s interesting.
They were constantly
inventing all sorts of things.
We just take them for granted.
The invention of chairs with backs, the
invention of scissors, the invention of
improved metallurgy so that steel could
do things steel couldn't do before.
There was always technological
change happening.
I'm in the middle of reading an
amazing book about how, when you
look at the paintings of Raphael
and the few paintings we have by
Michelangelo, the colors look like
they're really glowing, like gemstones.
How did that happen?
When you compare them to paintings
from just a hundred years earlier
somehow the colors are flatter.
I'm not talking about the
anatomy being more realistic.
That's separate, but
the colors are flatter.
The answer is there was a sequence of
revolutionary adaptations in how to
process oil and how to process colors
and mix them together, and then those
were used to create fake gemstones,
and there was a major industrial leap
forward in the fake gemstone industry.
Then people who were making picture
frames realized they could use
the same techniques from the fake
gemstones to make fake gold by painting
yellow over the surface of tinfoil.
And then those were used by
artists who were like, "Wait, I
want to make things that look like
they glow like fake gemstones."
There were eleven major technical
revolutions over the course of 120
years that led to those colors changing.
Obviously progress has been happening
in individual fields over time.
But in this macroscopic view, and
this is a big part of your book,
there's a reason that people living
in the fourteenth century would say,
"Look, the best time to be alive was
when the Romans were around, and since
then it's just been the Dark Ages."
If they stood in relation to the Roman
Empire as we stand to them, we would
obviously notice that the world has
seen so much progress since then.
It clearly seems like the pace...
It's hard to figure out when we
are lying and when we are right
where we say the pace picked up.
One thing that makes the pace
pick up in modern day is simply
the population grew and grew and
grew and is now much, much larger.
The majority of people who ever lived
in the entire history, since humans
have been humans and not hominids,
have lived in the last 200 years
because the population became massive.
How did the population become massive?
Our agriculture and
our hygiene enabled it.
How did our agriculture
and our hygiene improve?
Half of that is continuing on
the artisanal level to invent new
things in the same way that the
artists invented better colors.
Agricultural workers invented
better technologies, and agriculture
was constantly improving.
You're correct that with the
arrival of the systematic scientific
method just after 1600, there is a
deliberate societal desire to create
intentional anthropogenic progress.
I'll zoom in on the arguments made in
1600, then I'll zoom out and unpack them.
In 1600, the idea is that history
up until now has been unsystematic.
People have discovered things at
random, but we can create a method
in which we observe the world and use
inductive reasoning to figure things
out from those observations to create
systematic descriptions of the secret
motions that underlie nature, and
from that work out technologies that
are good and useful for humankind.
If, as we make our observations of nature,
we publish them and share them with
each other, we can create a community
of scientists that will share all of
these discoveries with each other and
with the world and therefore benefit it.
This is where, when I'm doing this in
the classroom, I deliberately provoke and
shock my students with the fun claim that
Leonardo da Vinci was not a scientist.
What I mean by that is that to be a
scientist is to publish your results
and share them with a community of
other scientists so that they can
test them, so that the whole human
civilization progresses a little bit.
When my friends who are chemists or
my friends who are particle physicists
discover something, the next goal is
to share that discovery with everyone
so everyone's knowledge advances.
What does Leonardo do?
He writes everything he discovers
down in coded mirror writing so that
nobody but him can possibly use it.
He refuses to share even with his
students and assistants the secrets of
what he's doing because Leonardo does
not want to contribute to human progress.
Leonardo wants to make unique
masterpieces so that hundreds of
years later, people will see them and
marvel and say, "How did he do it?
No one else has ever been able
to replicate that method."
He wanted to be marveled at by the
future exactly the way he and his peers
marveled at the works of the ancients.
They look at something like the Colosseum
or the Pantheon in Rome with its enormous
dome, and they say, "How did they do it?
If only we could work that
out, we could make one and then
make sure no one else could."
Brunelleschi, who built Florence's famous
beautiful dome, deliberately burned all
of his notes and schematics so that nobody
else would be able to replicate his work.
That is an inventor, and an engineer, but
in the sense of a community of scientists,
this is not a servant of human progress.
This is actually a saboteur of
human progress, if anything, who
deliberately makes progress and then
tries to cut it off at that point
so that no one else can be his peer.
That is what you did as a learned
inventor in the 1400s and in the 1500s.
But as you get to 1600, the
suggestion is different, and here
I'm going to use Francis Bacon's
gorgeous simile of the three insects.
There are three types of
knowledge wielders, says Bacon.
First, there is the ant, who is
the encyclopedist, who gathers
information from all around the world.
He learns everything he can, and he
piles it up into a great big pile.
He makes an anthill, and he sits on top.
If he has the biggest anthill,
the biggest pile of knowledge,
then he's proud of having made it.
But all he does is
assemble it and possess it.
It's a beautiful library,
but nothing comes from it.
The second type is the system weaver,
the spider who spins elaborate webs of
beautiful, intricate, logical theory.
You admire them, and you can get
entranced and ensnared in them
easily because they're so beautiful.
They're almost hypnotic.
But there's nothing real in them.
They're all just spun out of the
body of the spider himself, the
theorist theorizing from his own mind.
The third kind, says Bacon, is the
honeybee, who, gathering from among
the fruits of nature, processes what
he gathers through the organ of his
own being to produce something which
is sweet and useful for humankind.
That is the scientist who gathers
from nature to produce something
sweet and useful for humankind.
With this rhetorical call, and with
Francis Bacon's portrait on the title
page, the English Academy of Sciences
is founded and starts publishing.
The standard switches over from "You
are not a great achiever because you
built the dome" to "You are a great
achiever because you worked out how it
can be done, and you shared that sweet
and useful thing with all of humankind."
Bacon says if we do this, if we make
academies of sciences, we can make
sure that every human generation lives
in a better condition than the past.
We'll have better
agriculture, fewer famines.
We will have refrigeration.
We'll have chicken in winter.
We will have all of these
things that we aspire to.
If we collaborate, each generation's
experience will be better than the last.
He says that to be a scientist is
the ultimate act of charity because
there is no greater act of charity
than to give a gift to every human
who will ever live after you.
That is the rhetoric of what you
would feel was happening if you're
alive in the 1620s and 1630s.
Galileo is publishing his observations,
and Descartes is publishing his systems.
They've just discovered that the heart
is a pump and that they were totally
wrong about the four humors theory.
The blood circulates, and they're
trying to figure out what it does.
They have magnification, and
they can see worlds of complex
patterns on the wing of a flea.
It sounds like the whole world
is suddenly coming into view, and
we're at the beginning of progress.
If we zoom out, we would say there'd
been progress the whole time.
People had always been inventing things.
Agriculture in France was better
in 1300 than it was in 1000.
Plows got better, seed got better,
cabbages were bred to be bigger.
People worked out better pots.
There were always artisanal inventors.
In fact, that's a lot of
what Bacon is observing.
He worked in the patent office as
a young man, and he would see a
carpenter come in to patent: "I
have invented a better chisel.
I've invented a thing that goes like this.
I'm going to patent it." He would
realize that it was workers and
workmen and handicraftsmen who were
inventing the really useful tools.
He wanted to make this systematic.
We would say there was always
anthropogenic progress.
In 1630, they realize there
is anthropogenic progress.
They think there hasn't been.
They think they're beginning, and
that history up until this point has
been stagnant, but now it's going
to suddenly be full of invention as,
for the first time, there will be
deliberate anthropogenic progress.
Really, we would say there always
was and that it's accelerating,
and at this point, we realize it
and articulate and describe it.
You've probably seen lots of graphs
of history with the hockey stick
graph structure, where it's flat
for a long time and then zhoops up.
They'll put that zhoop after the
invention of the scientific method.
It depends on what we're graphing,
whether that zhoop is appropriate.
It also depends on how much
you zoom in or zoom out.
It's true, we do get to inventions
that result in enormous increases
in population 150 years after Bacon.
Would we have anyway, even if
it hadn't been systematized?
Probably a bit later, and we would
have a slightly flatter hockey stick.
But we would still have hockey sticked.
In the same way that when you put
mice on an island without mice, they
breed and they breed and they breed
and they breed and they hockey stick.
Humans would also have hockey sticked.
But would we have hockey sticked later?
Would we have hockey
sticked with more pain?
When mice hockey stick, they also
starve to death and eat each other.
We haven't done that yet.
Go us.
Was that science?
Probably.
There are a lot of factors to it.
So is it true that everything
accelerated after 1620?
In
one sense, yes.
In another sense, it's a continuation
of a curve that was already curving.
I think you might have answered
a question I was about to ask.
The book you recommend on your website,
The Renaissance in Italy, I keep
forgetting the name of the author.
Italian names are tough.
Guido Ruggiero.
In some part, he has this question: Look,
in Italy, as you mentioned, in Venice,
they've really scaled the printing press.
As a result, you have the
metalworking for fine typesetting.
Separately, milling technology for
water mills and windmills is advanced,
along with gears for watches.
So he asks, why didn't Italy
have the Industrial Revolution?
I
wonder, do you stand by the answer you
just gave, or is it a different theory?
Part of it.
But another is, we cannot underestimate
how much richer per square meter
Italy is than everywhere else.
Italy is the breadbasket, and it's also
the center of Big Oil, which is to say
Big Olive Oil, which was both fuel oil for
light and industrial oil for production,
as well as cooking and eating oil.
And the other major major industry
of the period, which is Big Wool.
If you're already the center of Big
Finance, Big Wool, and Big Oil, do
you need an industrial revolution?
You're already economically on top
through the power of agriculture.
It makes sense for it to have been
a sort of industrial backwater area.
What was England producing?
Crappy quality wool?
England was so aware that it couldn't
process wool into high quality without
masses of olive oil, which it couldn't
produce, that England just exported
its crude wool to Florence in order
to have Florence, with its olive oil
reserves, produce the fine quality.
Think about how a wool suit isn't
itchy, but a wool blanket often is.
That wool suit isn't itchy because
lots of olive oil went into
the process of producing it, at
least at pre-modern tech levels.
So do you want England to produce
your itchy wool that people will
only pay a small amount for,
or do you want to export it?
It makes sense for it to have
been somewhere industrially
ambitious that wasn't already
economically on top to have done it.
That's one reason that industrialization
doesn't kindle in Italy.
Italy is agricultural
land and a finance world.
It doesn't feel like it
needs a new industry.
Another factor is mining.
This land is more valuable as
a farm than it is as a mine.
You don't want to rip it up.
Another is it's so subdivided
because those rich cities are
still mostly independent, whereas
a centralized crown in England is
more able to pass legislation to
facilitate a massive transformation.
No city really wants to be the one where
the giant industrialization is happening.
It's awful for the city.
Note that the industrialization of
the Industrial Revolution was mostly
outside of the wealthier centers of
England in the second-tier towns.
They grow massively into huge
industrial areas like Lancaster.
So those are a plural bunch of reasons.
But I would have also thought that the
competitiveness between different Italian
city-states would have made it so that
if they get better textile machines
before you, it's a disaster because
they're right there.
This is not going to sound
plausible to anybody, but it's true.
We've been looking at some documents
recently which pretty much confirm
that they did figure out how
to make industrial looms in the
1400s, and they didn't want to.
They wanted to make
luxuriant artisanal fabrics.
This, by the way, was another
interesting thing from the book.
With the first printed books,
there's not this market of commodity
things that are produced cheaply
that the average person is going
to be like, "Oh, if I can get
this for $10.99, I'll go buy it."
So they're trying to make this
thing look like it was produced
as artisanal luxury grade.
Right.
The first printed fonts look like
handwritten scripts, and often have a
blank space to illuminate it so that
it looks just as fancy as manuscripts.
One thing I wanted
to ask you, back to the printing press.
Not only does printing get
cheaper, but around this time,
paper itself also gets cheaper.
So not just reading, but
writing gets cheaper.
Do you as historians see a marked
change in this period in the amount
of records that are taken and,
as a result, our understanding?
A huge amount rests on whether
you have a cheap writing surface.
Rather than looking first at the
Renaissance, let's look at what
we think of as the fall of Rome.
One of the biggest things that happens
there is that Western and Northern
Europe lose access to papyrus.
Papyrus is the cheap writing
surface of antiquity.
It is an easy plant-based writing surface.
You take this tall, thin water reed
that is fibrous like asparagus.
You slice it into ribbons.
You set them out in the sun, a
bunch of them parallel to each other
sitting on a stone like noodles.
You put a second row of noodles
perpendicular to that on top,
and then they dry in the sun,
and they are naturally sticky.
They stick to each other.
They produce a sheet.
Practically no labor has gone into this.
You've sliced, you've laid out, boom.
Papyrus is a very inexpensive writing
surface, and this is what enables
Rome to have a bureaucracy and to
have libraries in any mid-sized city.
People can send letters back and forth.
There can be enormous tax records.
Sometimes when Egypt and Rome are
at war, Egypt will be like, "No,
we are angry. We'll stop exporting
papyrus." No papyrus to Rome, and
then Rome's infrastructure will fall
apart overnight because you can't do
anything if you can't write stuff down.
Papyrus is a warm weather plant.
It is killed by frost.
You cannot grow it
north of the frost line.
So France, Spain, even most of
Italy, you can only grow papyrus
down in the very tip down in Sicily.
Without papyrus,
what you're writing on is a dead sheep.
If you think of the price of a
head of lettuce and the price of a
leather jacket, you're understanding
the difference between a sheet of
papyrus and writing on a dead sheep.
Every page of a medieval
book is as expensive as that
much of a leather jacket.
A handwritten medieval book handwritten
on parchment costs as much as a house,
so that a small pocket copy of a
book costs as much as a studio condo.
A big illuminated fancy Bible, you're
spending on that what you would
spend on a villa in the countryside.
This is an enormous expense.
To have a library is to be
not just rich, but mega-rich.
Only the wealthiest cities
contain anybody who has a library.
The great library of the University
of Paris—the library from Europe's
perspective—has six hundred books.
There's definitely more than
six hundred books in this room.
Every kiosk at an airport
selling Dan Brown novels has
more than six hundred books.
This is nothing.
At the same time as that, in the Middle
East, sultans have libraries of over a
thousand books or five thousand books.
There are libraries in Sub-Saharan
Africa with thousands of books.
There are libraries in China with
thousands of books because they
have cheap paper, rice paper.
The Middle East has papyrus.
Europe, and only Europe, is
writing on a leather jacket.
What changes around this time?
How is Europe able to get paper?
Still zooming in on the fall of Rome.
Rome had lots and lots
of books on papyrus.
They start falling apart
because papyrus is brittle.
Most of our knowledge from
antiquity is not lost at the burning
of the Library of Alexandria.
It's lost between 400 and 600 A.D.
when the papyri are falling apart.
Here you are with a library of a
thousand books, and you can only
afford to make a hundred new books.
You have to choose which hundred of
these thousand to save because there
literally is not enough industry
on your continent to make enough
leather to copy down all this text.
You have to pick.
The majority of what we lost
from antiquity, we lost then.
We lost it when the
papyri were falling apart.
This also distorted what survived because
most of the copying out was done by monks.
When you have a thousand books and you
can only save a hundred of them and you're
a monk, you're like, "What will I save?
I know, Saint Augustine. I love Saint
Augustine." This is why we have more
surviving work by Saint Augustine than
the entirety of all pagan classical Latin.
The subjective tastes of the people
in power at the moment the papyri
were falling apart ended up being an
unintentional moment of censorship that
biased what survives from antiquity.
Paper technology hits Europe in 800 A.D.,
so we're talking about a four-hundred-year
famine of a cheap writing surface.
Paper is nowhere near as cheap
as papyrus because you need to
gather rags from used clothing.
You immerse them in water, and you beat
them violently using a mill for a very
long time until they become a pulp.
You then scoop that pulp up on a
screen, and the fibers lock together.
It's sort of a slurry
that looks like grits.
You lift up the slurry, and it locks
together into a sheet of paper.
It's not as cheap as just growing
papyrus, and it's much more labor.
You have to build a paper mill.
If parchment is a leather jacket
and papyrus is buying a head of
lettuce, this is somewhere in between.
What's in between a
leather jacket and a...
This feels like a trick question.
This is somewhere in between,
getting yourself a dozen frozen
prepackaged meals, which are
complex and have many ingredients.
A lot of industry went into
producing the actual packaging,
more so than a head of lettuce.
So it's ten times as expensive,
but it's still a tenth as
much as the leather jacket.
Paper comes in, and people
are very wary of it.
Paper is clearly not
as strong as parchment.
Parchment is really tough stuff.
People start using paper for rough
drafts, letters, sketchbooks.
When you're doing the sketch before doing
a painting, you might do that on paper.
But Europe has paper for four hundred
years before the earliest state document
is ever written on paper, to give you
a sense of how people are wary of it.
It disseminates slowly.
It's still expensive.
It requires industry and production, but
it is a tenth as expensive as leather.
Paper disseminates slowly through Europe.
Again, this is one of these things where
there was always technological change,
and all technological changes are gradual.
Paper comes in in 800.
It's being trusted by 1200.
When printing begins, they're printing
on paper, but they even print on vellum.
If you're a really rich person,
you would be like, "Please print
two copies on vellum for me."
Dukes like the Dukes d'Este, Isabella
d'Este—the sister of the duke who walked
around buck naked to show off that he
could—specially ordered all of her books
to be printed on vellum even when the
rest of the print run was on paper.
These are the very books being
produced in Venice by the apprentices
of Gutenberg who ran away.
At that moment in the 1490s, if you're
really rich, you might be invested
in these newfangled printed books,
but you're still not trusting paper,
even though paper has been there
for six hundred years at that point.
So again, gradual adoption of
technologies and gradual trust in paper.
They're still using parchment for things,
gradually less and less, but substantially
over the course of the 1600s.
You can even find things written on
parchment in the 1700s and 1800s.
British Parliament still did its
records on parchment up until ten
years ago, and the Vatican still does
its official records on parchment now.
This is a digression, but the
numbers of how expensive a book is
didn't make sense to me just based
on how much scribe time it took.
You say it's $600,000 per
book, and then separately, it's
five months of scribe time.
I'm like, how much are
the scribes getting paid?
But if it's the paper...
What changes with Gutenberg?
The paper and the ink.
But a lot of it is scribe time.
But Gutenberg still needs paper, right?
Yeah, Gutenberg needs paper.
That's why he goes bankrupt.
He borrows the equivalent of about
$1.5 million to buy paper, and
then doesn't make back $1.5 million
worth of material when printing it.
This is what makes printing a risk.
You have to start buying
the paper up front.
You need to buy it in a big lot
so that it matches, because people
don't want the paper to suddenly be
a different color within their book.
You're investing a lot up front, and
you're not getting anything back until
you produce this slow print run, which
is why printers start printing pamphlets.
They can have one press that's
slowly printing a valuable book
that will take six months to print.
Next to it they have another press
that's printing pamphlets where in two
days they've printed a fashion report on
what everyone was wearing at the royal
wedding, which they can sell right away.
It's much cheaper, but it means
they have something they can
sell two or three times a week.
So you have the pamphlet
following the book, printing
cheap news, printing scandal rags.
Why is it cheaper?
Because the material is cheaper?
Just because it's only five pages long.
Oh, I see.
Got it.
I could grab one if you want to see one.
So if we look at some examples.
I'll show you these one by one.
For example, this is a pamphlet.
Naked pages, short text,
hand-stitched together.
It would take two or four days
because you print the front
side and then the back side.
It's cheap.
It's ephemeral.
You print a thousand of them.
You sell a bunch around the town.
You sell a bunch to news writers who are
going to and from other cities, who will
buy them and bring them to the next town.
If you've printed news in Milan,
people who are going to Florence will
want to buy your news to go there.
It might be a report of a siege.
It might be
what people were wearing
at the royal wedding.
My favorite title of a pamphlet was
"The Scandalous Tale of a Doctor from
Padua and How He Seduced His Maid,
Murdered His Wife, Murdered the Maid,
Cut Out Her Heart and Ate It, and
How He Was Justly Punished by God."
That was the title of the pamphlet.
These things circulated around.
Some of them were nonsense,
some of them were real news.
Most were combinations.
But you can sell something like
this cheaply in a couple of days.
Often they would have a cheap blue cover.
You have seen this color before.
This is the color of laundry
lint, because fundamentally
laundry lint is what paper is.
You take rags of old clothes, you put them
in water, you beat them until they become
a pulp, and you skim it out with a sieve.
Laundry lint is what rag paper is.
If you don't bleach it, it's this generic
blue-gray color, which is sort of the
average color of what human beings wear.
That's a copy of The Gentleman's Magazine,
another example of technology taking
a leap forward in the 18th century.
When they invented the newspaper, they
immediately had the problem of, "Oh, no.
Newspapers contradict each other.
We don't know what's true.
We have to fact-check stuff."
That one has a great fold-out.
I think there's a procession or something.
That is what everybody
wore at the state funeral.
Instead of photographs, we have this
fancy, "Here is what everyone was wearing
at the state funeral." Very exciting.
Your laundry lint, if you don't bleach it,
remains the color that it on average was.
In the 18th century, they have newspapers.
The newspapers are reporting
news, but they don't quite say
the same thing as each other.
The problem becomes, how
do we know who to trust?
The Gentleman's Magazine was developed,
and every week they would publish a
roundup of that week's news saying
what each newspaper said about it,
where they contradicted each other,
analyzing who's right and wrong.
It was the fact-checking.
This is the first magazine.
It invented the word "magazine"
being used in this context.
It was an intellectual response
to the fake news problem of how we
reconcile what happens with newspapers.
You see these many iterations: they
invent the printing press, then they
invent the pamphlet, then they invent
the newspaper, then they invent the
magazine to cope with the newspaper.
The newspaper is invented to cope with the
pamphlet because you don't know whether
to trust the scandalous tale of the doctor
from Padua and how he murdered his wife.
Is he real?
We don't know.
But if somebody publishes a newspaper
that serially prints news every
week, they have a reputation.
They have to be respectable.
You're not going to subscribe to them
if you catch them printing nonsense.
The serial nature of a newspaper was
a form of accountability that made
people willing to trust it over time.
The newspaper is a way of
fact-checking the pamphlet.
The pamphlet is a way of making money
while you're printing your longer book.
I will also let you
have a look at papyrus.
Thank you.
You can see the plaid pattern
of the papyrus because it is
made of two layers of strips.
And there's a papyrus scroll.
That's modern papyrus.
The thing about papyrus is
that in addition to being
cheap, it's very brittle.
It works better in a scroll than
it does folded over because the
folded edge cracks really easily.
If you try to make this into a codex
book, it's going to be very fragile.
Here you go.
This is a real 17th-century letter in
absolutely indecipherable handwriting.
On parchment?
On parchment.
You can even tell, because that's cheap
parchment, which side was the outside of
the animal and which side was the inside.
The handwriting is in some sense
bad, but it's also very well aligned.
Tiny and precise.
But here is good parchment.
It is hard to believe
that it's animal skin.
These are pages from a book
of hours from about 1480,
individually hand-calligraphed.
You can see that one
has a hole through it.
They wrote around the hole because it's
too valuable to not use that sheet.
These are paper thin.
You can barely tell, if you look
carefully, which side was the
outside of the animal and which
was the inside because one side
has tiny little speckles of pores.
Where is this from?
A book of hours.
This is probably a French book of hours.
A book of hours is a personal prayer book.
Bible quotes, objects of meditation.
The book would be fat and small.
This was the most common
manuscript in the Middle Ages.
You would carry it around in your
pocket, and you'd pull it out different
times of day for personal prayer.
But it also has big margins so that
you can take notes in it, write down
addresses, have friends write notes in it.
You use it almost like a day planner.
It's the smartphone of the period
in which you make all your notes
or write down people's names.
You might have celebrities you
meet sign your book of hours.
All sorts of neat things go
into the margins as you use
this to organize the day.
That would
be extremely interesting as a collector's
item, random people's book of hours
and what kinds of things they recorded.
Oh yeah.
Think of a leather jacket, but how much
more industrial effort went into making
leather literally paper-thin like this.
Huge amounts of industrial effort go
into making the pages of such a book.
My favorite example of this kind of
distribution and diffusion taking
longer than you would think for a
very fundamental technology—well,
this is now my favorite example, so
my second favorite example—is oil.
I interviewed Daniel Yergin, who wrote
this big book about the history of oil.
In the 1860s, Drake strikes
oil in Pennsylvania.
It's
in the 1910s that the car is
invented, the internal combustion
engine is put into a thing which
you sell millions of copies of.
Until then, oil is just used for
kerosene, which is just for lighting.
The actual gas is just thrown away.
In fact, when the light bulb was
invented, people were wondering whether
Standard Oil was going to go bankrupt
because the main use case had gone away.
Oh, neat.
I always think of Julius Caesar's
description of Britain when
the Romans first get there.
He says, "The people of Britain
are so poor, they can't afford to
burn wood, so they burn rocks."
We know he's talking about coal.
Oh, I thought it was satire.
No, he's talking about coal.
They had coal in the days of Julius
Caesar, but they didn't figure
out its massive industrial utility
until many, many years later.
There is this interesting question
of why the Romans didn't have the
Industrial Revolution because they
had these huge silver mines in
Spain and elsewhere, but no coal.
You have the Industrial Revolution
when you feel you need to.
That's the thing about Gutenberg as well
that a lot of people don't think about.
People are like, "Gutenberg was
an inventor and invented a thing,
and then it had an impact." No.
He was living in the middle of a library
building boom in which there was a
huge demand for books that spiked.
He invented the invention in
response to that cultural change.
It isn't by chance that we got
the printing press in 1450.
There was a huge boom of library
buildings starting in the 1410s,
and inventors were trying to figure
out ways to make books cheaper.
They were making smaller books.
They were using paper more.
Paper surges before the Gutenberg
movable type printing press.
So Gutenberg isn't a random
genius out of nowhere.
It was the moment that
people needed more books.
We were going to get the invention.
One thing you say in passing in
the book is Martin Luther comes up
at the exact right time, because
you've got Savonarola in the 1490s,
and he's another prophet type.
I guess he's the modern analog of somebody
like Khomeini in Iran, setting up a
theocratic government, but too early.
Machiavelli you say is too late because
the censorship is already in place.
What is the censorship that is in
place by the time of Machiavelli?
What is the alternative world?
Machiavelli, remember, is
contemporary with Luther.
It's just that he circulates his
stuff very briefly and very privately.
He doesn't want a pamphlet version
of his ideas out there because he
only wants Florence to have it.
Luther hits the sweet spot
when the pamphlet distribution
network had just developed.
When Savonarola printed pamphlets,
they only circulated around Florence
and its neighbors, Siena and Pisa.
It took months for them to get farther.
His movement was quickly crushed.
When Luther makes the Ninety-five
Theses public, they're in print
in London seventeen days after
he releases them in Wittenberg.
The pamphlet runners go foom, foom, foom,
and get the news there, and things are
printed overnight and come out that fast.
But it seems like you're hinting that
within the next two decades, there's
a new censorship regime across Europe.
A new censorship regime responds.
The censorship regime is very effective
at shaping what is printed in books,
but can never keep up with pamphlets.
In the same way that
the government can pressure CNN,
the government can't pressure random
people on a social media network.
You're not going to be able
to keep up with that speed.
One of the funny problems that the
Inquisition always had when trying to
persecute printers is that printers worked
in the information distribution industry.
They were the people who paid the news
writers, whose job it is to move as
fast as humanly possible between cities.
Which meant that news
always reached them first.
If a printer was ever convicted by
the Inquisition, they would find
out before the Inquisition could
possibly get there to arrest them.
The Inquisition never succeeded
at arresting printers.
They'd always skipped town by the time
the Inquisition got there, because
if you employ the news writers,
you find out first what's going on.
The Inquisition can't keep up.
When we look at censorship, there's
an intersection of four factors as
to whether censorship is possible.
One of them is law: Is it legal
for the censorship to happen?
Another one is the technology.
Is it actually possible
to censor this thing?
You cannot censor whatever moves the
information fastest because it will move
the information faster than you can move.
Even if that one printer had to skip
town, he will set up shop somewhere else,
a new person will take over his shop,
and the information will still move.
So pamphlets become unpoliceable.
You can try to police them, you can
partially police them, but keeping
pamphlets from moving around… They're
anonymous, they're quick, they're
produced overnight, they move quickly.
You just can't keep up with them.
Couldn't they just punish print
shops for publishing things?
Just say, "This is what we like,
and if you do something we don't
like, we'll punish you," which is
how censorship in China works, for
example.
They did.
So the printer skips town.
The printer moves to the next town.
There is a cost to that.
There's a human cost to evading that.
You've had to leave your home and
friends behind and move to a new
place, but they don't get you.
It's also very easy to deny that
the pamphlet came from you at all.
The print industry proves very difficult
to censor, and we're experiencing
the same thing with social media.
Everyone is like, "Censor the pornography
on this social media channel,"
and they're like, "We just can't.
It's too fast.
There's too much." Or, "Censor
the hate speech." "We just can't.
It's too fast, there's too much."
There are too many pamphlets,
and they could crack down on
one particular pamphlet shop.
We have records of this.
There's a brilliant analysis in
Anton Matytsin's book, The Specter of
Skepticism in the Age of Enlightenment.
He has a great description from the notes
of a raid on a clandestine bookshop.
This wasn't the printer, this was the
underground bookshop that was selling
illegal books, and they're raided.
It has all the details of how
angry the people were about
different things that the shop had.
So there was censorship and there were
crackdowns, but it was a censorship that
could not actually prevent circulation.
It could restrict it, it could
make it harder, it could make it
scary, but it couldn't prevent it.
Before books become cheap,
unless you're fantastically wealthy,
you're reading the same couple of
books—if you've ever read a book—again
and again throughout your life.
Cosimo de' Medici's father owned,
I think it was twelve books.
I want to understand the intellectual
significance of rereading the
exact same book again and again.
Maybe the reason Petrarch loved Cicero
so much is, imagine reading the same book
twenty times, hitting the same joke again
and just meditating on every single point.
There's got to be a difference
in intellectual culture as a
result of treating these things
as the equivalent of the Bible.
You really feel like you get
to know the person intimately.
You develop a personal relationship
with the ancient author.
You are participating in a conversation
across the diaspora of time.
It's a one-way conversation.
You're responding to them, the
future will respond to you.
But there is a great deal of intimacy.
Petrarch talks about his friend Cicero
and being betrayed by his friend Cicero.
He finds new works of Cicero that he
hadn't read including some of Cicero's
letters in which Cicero is not following
his own stoic philosophical precepts
and is being petty, yelling at people
about real estate, and getting all
upset after his daughter's death.
You know how people get manic when
there's been a death in the family
and start quarreling about everything?
Cicero gets like that, and
Petrarch is heartbroken.
To him it means even the wisest
man in history could not conquer
that urge to become irrational
and petty in the face of grief.
If even Cicero became irrational and
petty in the face of grief, does that
mean humanity is doomed to forever be
irrational and petty in the face of grief?
He talks about Cicero breaking his
heart and his foot, because the
book fell on his foot and broke
it, and he got a bad infection,
and he was bedridden for months.
Totally different topic, but
in
1492, Columbus comes to the New World.
They discover the New World.
What is the reception of this news?
I was just at a conference a week
ago in which we confirmed that
there's a Vatican document from 1100
or maybe 1200—I forget the exact year—that
recognizes the existence of Vinland, i.e.
Canada, where they got the
information from the Vikings.
Oh, interesting.
They thought it was just
a little thing, but yeah.
So they're rediscovering the New World.
Would it be the equivalent of
finding out there are aliens today?
Why wasn't it considered more significant?
Why wasn't the consensus, "This is
the main thing happening right now,
we've discovered the New World"?
When I teach my class on the 1490s,
the students, many of whom are
American, always have trouble wrapping
their heads around people thinking
that the New World isn't a big deal.
A big part of it is that they find the
Caribbean islands, and they find the
coast, and they think this is small.
The way I put it to my students is,
the news comes back, we've found
something across the water to the west.
It might be even as big
as the Canary Islands.
They've found something, but they
don't realize they've found something
the scale of Europe and Africa.
Actually, it's not as big as
Europe and Africa, but they
found something humongous.
That's part of it.
Another part of it is no matter how
big and important something far away
is, it's hard to bring your mind
out of the petty squabbles that are
happening right around you, especially
when they feel like life or death.
If it's 1492, what is happening?
France is about to invade Italy.
Europe might be embroiled in the
largest war it's seen in fifty years.
The papacy has just been
taken over by Spain.
Spain is suddenly trying to
throw its weight around in Europe
in a way that's unprecedented.
The Ottomans have just invaded Italy
and Hungary and might be coming again.
Also over there, there's a new thing.
Okay, great.
We'll worry about that when we're not
having three wars at the same time.
But guys, we're having
three wars at the same time.
Oh my God.
And then Martin Luther hits Europe
like a ton of bricks when they still
haven't even figured out that this
is a continent and not an island.
In the same way, if you're in a country
and it's having a tumult, you worry a
lot about its tumult, even if a larger
tumult is happening in a faraway country.
It's hard to bring your mind
out of Europe at crisis to be
like, "Hey, this is a thing."
The other is they're inventing
lots of new things, and it falls
into the sphere along the rest.
They're discovering the existence
of sub-Saharan Africa, where they
thought there was basically one
country's worth of stuff, south of
the Sahara, Ethiopia and nothing else.
Then they're like, "Oh my God, there's
a whole big thing that sticks out."
They're also discovering
that the heart is a pump.
That's a bit later, but
they're discovering all sorts
of stuff at the same time.
The discovery of the New World,
especially when they realize how big it
is, becomes an intellectual challenge
where they say, "Wait, does this mean
all the maps we've had are wrong?
Does this mean the ancients
were wrong about geography?
Does it mean the world is a lot bigger
than we used to think the world is?
Let's worry about that the same way
we worry about revolutionizing our
mathematics and figuring out that
the sun doesn't go around the Earth."
These are things that
are paradigm shifting.
But on the other hand, does it matter
whether the sun goes around the Earth
or the Earth around the sun when the
French are invading right now and we
need to get the defenses going, and
there's a giant civil war happening,
and we're about to be betrayed?
It does matter, but it
also doesn't matter.
Any decade is concerned by its
tumults and often fails to recognize
the importance of what's around it.
That’s true of every decade.
One fun game when I study the history
of censorship, which I work a lot
on—my next non-fiction book is
gonna be a book on the history of
censorship—whatever they're looking at,
they're always wrong, from our
perspective, about what they
should be worried about censoring.
If we had a time machine and our goal is
to go give them advice… Here we are in
the French Enlightenment, Voltaire and
Rousseau and the Marquis de Sade and La
Mettrie's articulations of materialist
atheism are flying around Europe.
What is the Inquisition worried about?
It's worried about Jansenist treatises
about the nature of the Trinity.
Jansenism is sort of like a
Calvinist version of Catholicism.
Do you want to have an incredibly
terrifying authoritarian God who hates
you and tells you that your soul is
a worthless spider that deserves to
be hurled into fire, but also have
to obey the arbitrary pope in Rome?
Then Jansenism is for you.
It has all the grimness of Calvinism
and all of the authoritarian
centrality of the Roman Catholics.
This was a heresy that was abroad
in the Enlightenment, and they are
so much more worried about Jansenism
than they are about Voltaire.
Remember that very chapter in Matytsin's
book I mentioned where they are
raiding the clandestine bookshop.
They're like, "Voltaire, fine.
The banned Encyclopédie, which is gonna
revolutionize all thought in Europe, fine.
letters of Diderot, Rousseau, fine, fine.
Jansenist treatises about
the nature of the Trinity!
Throw the book at these guys!
This is the worst thing!" They really
are obsessed with this incredibly petty
minor heresy to the degree that when
the Encyclopédie is banned by Rome…
France likes the Encyclopedia.
This is Diderot and d’Holbach’s
big project of universal education,
to print an encyclopedia that
will collect all world knowledge.
They articulate it as, "Should a
new dark age come upon humankind and
even one copy of the encyclopedia
survive, it will be sufficient to
reconstruct all human progress."
That's the goal of this thing.
It's advancing incredibly radical ideas
about biology, about statecraft, about
reforming the law to be rational instead
of traditional, all sorts of stuff.
When that is banned by Rome, Paris is
commanded... Paris loves this book.
The king likes this book.
The queen likes this book.
She's on record saying it was so cool
being able to look up the technology
that was used to make her silk pantyhose.
She just loves it.
Everybody loves it.
France allows it to circulate
despite its controversial content.
But Rome says, "No, you
must ban this book."
So they agree they're gonna have the
ceremonial burning, and they march
the Encyclopédie up to the fire.
Then they get some Jansenist treatise
about the nature of the Trinity and
burn those instead, because they
don't want to burn the Encyclopédie.
They love it.
They want to burn this other thing.
This is always true.
If we had a time machine for the
Inquisition in the 1540s, we would
say, "Guys, Machiavelli, he's really
important. He's really revolutionary.
You gotta be looking at this."
Or we would say Lucretius's De rerum
natura, which I did my dissertation
on… Many people are familiar with
Greenblatt's book, The Swerve, which
credits a lot of change to the materialist
science that this poem articulates.
There's a much more complex story,
which you know is told in my book,
which refers to Greenblatt's.
If anyone enjoyed The Swerve, you would
really enjoy the more detailed zoom-in
that Inventing the Renaissance has.
But we would say, "Guys,
you should censor this."
We literally have letters of inquisitors
writing to each other saying, "We don't
need to bother censoring Lucretius.
Only learned people can read it,
and they know perfectly well that
the false stuff is false, so it'll
just circulate and it's fine.
What we need to worry about
censoring is all of these fine
minutiae of Protestantism."
The 1545
edition of the Index of Banned Books
says in its introduction, "We shall put
the names of arch-heretics in all caps."
When I first read that, I was like,
"Ooh, I want to see all my favorite
arch-heretics be in all caps."
I eagerly flip to M, and
Machiavelli is not in all caps.
He was not important
enough from their position.
The all caps authors are all
minor Protestant theologians.
They're all people like Calvin and
Zwingli and Luther and Melanchthon.
They're all doing stuff that
we would say does not matter.
But an era is always wrong about what
ideas and what circulation and what
changes are the really big ones and
are always much, much more worried
about, "Oh my God, the Prince of Spain,
which princess is he gonna marry?
This is going to determine whether
Spain is or isn't annexed by Germany.
This is the most important
thing that has ever happened
in the entire stream of time."
People are like, "We've
discovered another continent,"
and they're like, "We don't care.
We just wanna know who's
gonna marry Charles."
That's a very profound observation.
It was really interesting to learn from
your book that of all the thousands of
people killed during the Inquisition,
one guy was executed for atheism.
Science-related stuff.
And even he had these ideas
of reincarnation or...
I think probably the number executed
for atheism would be about 100.
There are 12 total trials
of scientists about science.
Galileo is one.
Giordano Bruno is one.
Giordano Bruno is the only one executed.
Of those 12 trials, only
three were convicted.
Hundreds of thousands of trials for
Judaizing, which is theoretically
contaminating Christianity with
Jewish thought, and all of these
other minutiae of oppression and
segregation of populations, executions
for paganism, meaning practicing your
indigenous religion in a colonized
space… Hundreds of thousands of
executions for that, one for science.
I recently got interested in
the story of Kepler just because
the way he discovers the laws of
planetary motion is so whimsical
with the theory of Platonic objects.
While he's going through Brahe's
data and coming up with the laws of
planetary motion, he is the imperial
mathematician for the Habsburg
emperor, which basically means that
he's doing astrology for a general.
Will we win the battle or whatever.
Then he gets excommunicated, not
for the laws of planetary motion,
but because he's a Lutheran.
In
fact, his mother is tried for witchcraft.
Again, has nothing to do with science,
it’s just because she's also a Lutheran.
Milton of Paradise Lost fame wrote our
first big defense of the free press.
This is in the moment in the early
1600s when England doesn't yet
have systematic censorship law.
It has ad hoc, "Hey, this book is bad,"
but it doesn't have systematic, "You must
submit all books to a censor," the way
the Catholic world does by that point.
The Catholic world developed it
in order to fight Protestantism.
There's a lot of support for creating
censorship in England at the time
because there's anxiety about Papists
plotting against our nice non-Catholic
country, trying to undermine it.
There's a general feeling of anxiety.
There's
also deliberate moral panic whipped up
by politicians and power-seeking people
who whip up a deliberate moral panic
about books, the same way in 1954 there
was a moral panic about comic books or
the same way there was a moral panic
about Dungeons & Dragons in the '90s.
There's a moral panic about scary
and dangerous books and pamphlets.
So there's a movement to create
state censorship for the first
systematic time in England.
Milton writes this big treatise
about why freedom of the press
is important, the Areopagitica.
It’s a beautifully written
rhetorical piece that presents the
importance of how we must trust
truth to rise purely to the top.
We must let free voices move, otherwise
you're gonna create a situation where
people are writing for the censor
first and for the public second.
It will constrain people's
thoughts in the way that we know
chilling effects and fear do.
It's a beautiful treatise.
He fails.
The censorship regime passes.
Paradise Lost is published
under the censorious regime.
It goes through the censorship.
The one line they tell him
to change is about astrology.
They're like, "It's perfectly fine
having Satan be your charismatic
protagonist and God be kind of a
jackass, and also having Satan spout
ferocious anti-monarchical rhetoric
copied from revolutionary pamphlets
that are circulating in the British
colonies so that he's actually parroting
republican, anti-monarchical rhetoric,
very dangerous stuff in the treatise.
That's fine.
But this one line about a comet
causing a thing to happen, no, no, no.
Astrology is gonna
confuse people's souls."
You're like, "Guys, speaking as a time
traveler, you're so wrong about what
you're censoring." They always are.
You have one sentence which
I couldn't trace down, which
I found very interesting.
You said, "In the late 17th century,
the most extensive library in
all of Europe is the one in the
Vatican run by the inquisitors."
Not the library, the most
extensive experimental laboratory.
Daniele
Macuglia is the scholar there.
That's from his dissertation.
I think it's been published
now, but I don't know if
it's actually out in English.
It's out in Italian.
He works on the Inquisition and
the immediate aftermath of Galileo.
They saw themselves as guarantors of
truth and of accuracy in information.
So they decided after Galileo that they
had a duty to verify the truth of the
books that they were sent to censor.
If people were going to be doing
mechanical experiments, they needed
to repeat the mechanical experiments
to see whether they were true.
So they effectively invented peer
review, which is to say they invented
a second laboratory trying to
recreate the results of the first.
There are these amazing people who by
day are inquisitors and by night are
going home to write their own scientific
treatises as they do these experiments.
It's not what we expect, but
history is never what we expect.
Seems like a good place to close.
Ada, thank you very much.
Thank you.