An interesting detail about Florence
even as the Medici take over is that the
Medici know the people of Florence are
very deeply invested in this republic
and very deeply invested in its
institutions. And we have to therefore
respect those institutions and proclaim
respect for [music] those institutions.
So we're going to sustain people in the
named offices that there used [music] to
be. If there was a mandatory outfit that
people wore who worked in the republic,
which there was, the garment thing over
there [music] in the corner is an
underway Luca Fiorentino. This was the
garment you were mandated by law to wear
if you held office in the Florentine
Republic. To us we look at it and we're
like it's a long red robe, it looks very
Renaissance. To them it looked like a
toga. They're cos playing the Roman
Republic.
>> It's actually doubly ironic because when
the Roman Republic turns to a Roman
Empire, they still have the Senate, they
still have all these old institutions.
They are doing the same thing but back
in the in the 1500s. [music]
>> And it means that more rights are
granted to the people of Florence than
to other [music] cities that felt to
monarchies at similar points. Because
the monarchs of Florence know they have
to be careful.