So, we're very accustomed in the modern
period to thinking of government as
being our big safety net. And if we
wonder who is going to fund the
hospitals, we think government or maybe
the church. But in this period, if
you're killed and you leave orphans
behind, it is your employer whose duty
it is to take care of them. If you are
injured and can no longer work, it is
your employer who will support you for
the rest of your life while you are
disabled and find you work that you can
do with that disability. Are you in
trouble with the law? your employer will
supply your defense attorney. This is
the system known as the patronage system
and it existed in ancient Rome. It
exists and saturates the medieval and
the Renaissance worlds. And so it makes
sense to everyone to be represented that
way, like having a council of the CEOs
of all of the organizations that
employees work for when your corporation
also supplies your social safety net and
you see your representation There.