When I teach my class on the 1490s, the
students, many of whom are American,
always have trouble wrapping their heads
around the people thinking that the new
world isn't a big deal. A big part of it
is that they find the Caribbean islands
and they find the coast and they think
this is small. The way I put it to my
students is the news comes back, we've
found something across the water to the
west. It might be even as big as the
Canary Islands. They've found something,
but they don't realize they've found
something humongous. That's part of it.
Another part of it is no matter how big
and important something far away is,
it's hard to bring your mind out of the
petty squables that are happening right
around you, especially when they feel
like life or death. If it's 1492, what
is happening? France is about to invade
Italy. Europe might be embroiled in the
largest war. It's seated 50 years. The
papacy has just been taken over by
Spain. Spain is suddenly trying to throw
its weight around in Europe in a way
that's unprecedented. Also, over there,
there's a new thing. Okay, great. We'll
worry about that when we're not having
three wars at the same time. But guys,
we're having three wars at the same
time. So in the same way that if you're
in a country and it's having a tumult,
you worry a lot about its tumult. Even
if a larger tumult is happening in a far
away